<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Indonesia - Norway BIT (1969)</name>
    <code>T1969-5</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">IDN</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">NOR</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1969-11-26</date_signed>
    <date_into_force/>
    <date_terminated>1994-10-01</date_terminated>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type>Replaced by new treaty</termination_type>
    <docreference>1989</docreference>
    <comments>http://arbitration.org/sites/default/files/bit/indonesia_norway_english.pdf</comments>
    <source>http://treaty.kemlu.go.id/</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>Replaced by new treaty</IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{IDN,NOR}_1969-11-26.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <relation type="IT_REPLACED_BY" document-code="T1991-65">Indonesia - Norway BIT (1991)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Agreementbetween the Governmentof the Republic of Indonesia and the Government of the Kingdom of Norway Concerning the Encouragement and the Reciprocal Protection ofInvestments.</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>DESIRING to create favourable conditionsfor capital investment s in both States and to intensify the cooperationbetween private enterprises in both States with a view to stimulating theproductive use of resources,</p>
      <p>RECOGNIZING that a contractual protectionof investments will serve this aim,</p>
      <p>HAVE AGREED as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="I">
        <p>In accord with its laws and regulationseach Contracting Party shall consider favourably applications for investmentsof capital in its territory for the purpose of establishing lasting economicrelations, by</p>
        <p>a) nationals of the other ContractingParty, provided they are domiciled in the territory of their nationality , or</p>
        <p>b) corporations domiciled or registered inthe territory of the other Contracting Party, being corporations in whichnationals of that Contracting Party have a substantial interest.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="II">
        <p>The protection accorded to investors by theprovisions of this Agreement shall apply :</p>
        <p>a) in the territory of the Republic ofIndonesia only to investments which have been approved by the IndonesianGovernment in accordance with the foreign investment legislation currently inforce (Law No. 1 of the year 1967),</p>
        <p>b) in the territory of Norway only toinvestments made in accordance with the Norwegian exchange regulationscurrently in force, and declared by the Norwegian Ministry of Foreign Affairsto be covered by the present agreement</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="III">
        <p>Neither Contracting Party shall in itsterritory impose on the activities of enterprises in which such approvedinvestments are made by nationals or corporations of the other ContractingParty conditions which are less favourable than those imposed in its territoryon activities in connection with any similar enterprise, whether owned by itsown nationals or corporations or by nationals or corporations of thirdcountries.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="IV">
        <p>(1 ) Neither Contracting Party shall takemeasures of expropriation or of nationalization or any other measures theeffect of which, either directly or indirectly, is to dispossess nationals orcorporations of the other Contracting Party of their investments, except forthe public benefit and against compensation, and not being contrary to existingobligations.</p>
        <p>The legality of such expropriation,nationalization or measures as aforesaid shall be subject to review by dueprocess of law.</p>
        <p>(2) If either Contracting Partyexpropriates or nationalizes investments of nationals or corporations of theother Contracting Party, or if it takes any other measures the effect ofwhich, either directly or indirectly, is to dispossess such nationals orcorporations of their investments, it shall provide prompt payment of effectiveand adequate compensation.</p>
        <p>(3) Such compensation shall represent the commercial value of the investments at the time of expropriation,nationalization or at the time of taking any other measures as aforesaid, it shallbe actually realizable and freely transferable, and shall be made without unduedelay. Provision shall have been made in an appropriate manner at or prior tothe time of expropriation, nationalization or the taking of such other measuresas aforesaid for determination and payment of such compensation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="V">
        <p>National or corporation of eitherContracting Party who suffer losses in relation to such approved investmentsowing to war or other armed conflicts, revolution, a state of nationalemergency, or revolt in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall beaccorded treatment no less favourable than that which the latter ContractingParty accords to its own nationals or corporations or nationals or corporationsof third countries as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation orother similar valuable consideration. Such payments shall be freelytransferable.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="VI">
        <p>If a Contracting Party makes payment to anyinvestor under a guarantee it has accorded in respect of an approved investment,the other Contracting Party shall recognize :</p>
        <p>a ) the assignment, whether under the lawof the country of the guarantor or pursuant to a legal transaction in thatcountry, of any right or claim by the investor to the former Contracting Party,as well as,</p>
        <p>b) the subrogation of that ContractingParty to any such right or claim which that Contracting Party shall be entitledto assert to the same extent as its predecessor in title.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="VII">
        <p>Either Contracting Party shall authorizethe transfer in the original currency of :</p>
        <p>a) the net return yielded by an investmentcovered by the present Agreement including, inter alia, interest, dividends,royalties, payments for licenses and other such claims of nationals or ofcorporations domiciled or registered in the other country;</p>
        <p>b) depreciation of capital assets,.amortization, or the proceeds of the total or partial liquidation of suchapproved investments, including possible increases in or additions to theseinvestments in the country in which they have been affected;</p>
        <p>c) an adequate portion of the wages,salaries and other remuneration of nationals holding permits to stay and workin the territory of either Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="VIII">
        <p>(1 ) Any dispute between the ContractingParties arising out of the interpretation or implementation of the present Agreement,which has not been settled within six months through diplomatic channels, shall, at the request of either Party, be submitted to a tribunal of arbitrationconsisting of three members. The Chairman of the tribunal shall be a citizen ofa third country and shall be appointed by common consent of the ContractingParties. Should the Parties fail to agree on the appointment of the Chairman ofthe tribunal, either Party may request the President of the International Courtof Justice to make the&#xB7; appointment. Each Party appoints its own arbitrator; ifa Party abstains from appointing an arbitrator, the latter may be appointed bythe Chairman of the Tribunal.</p>
        <p>(2) Each Contracting Party will observe andcarry out awards given by the tribunal.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="IX">
        <p>(1) The present Agreement shall beprovisionally applied from the date of its signature .</p>
        <p>(2) The present Agreement shall enter intoforce when the Governments of the two Contracting Parties have notified each otherthat their constitutional requirements for the entering into force of theAgreement have been fulfilled, and shall remain in force for a period offifteen years. It shall continue in force for further periods of fifteen years,unless notification of termination is given by either Government twelve monthsbefore the expiration of any fifteen years period.</p>
        <p>(3) In case of a notification oftermination of the present Agreement, the provisions of Articles I - VIII shallcontinue to be effective for a further period of fifteen years in respect ofinvestments made before such notification of termination was given.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>In witness whereof, the Parties heretoacting through their representatives duly authorized for this purpose, have signedthe present Agreement in two copies in the English language at Yakarta this dayof November 24, 1969.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic ofIndonesia</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Kingdom of Norway</p>
    </conclusion>
    <attachments>
      <p>
        <b>PROTOCOL</b>
      </p>
      <p>At the time of signing the Agreementbetween the Government of the Republic of Indonesia and the Government ofNorway concerning the Encouragement and the Reciprocal Protection of Investments,the undersigned Plenipotentiaries have, in addition, agreed on the followingunderstanding which shall be regarded as an integral part of the said Agreement:</p>
      <div type="article" title="Re article iii">
        <p>The Government of the Republic of Indonesiawhile confirming the award of most-favoured-nation treatment to Norwegian investmentsand activities connected therewith in Indonesia, reserves its position withregard to national treatment of Norwegian investments and activities in view ofthe present stage of development of the Indonesian national economy.</p>
        <p>Full national treatment of Norwegianinvestments and activities in Indonesia will be extended within the scope ofLaw No. 1 of the year 1967. Beyond this, however, the Government of theRepublic of Indonesia may extend facilities to Indonesian national enterpriseswhich do not fully apply to Norwegian enterprises.</p>
        <p>Signed in Djakarta on November 24, 1969.</p>
        <p>For the Government of the Republic ofIndonesia</p>
        <p>For the Government of the Kingdom of Norway</p>
      </div>
    </attachments>
  </main>
</treaty>
