<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Germany - Philippines BIT (1964)</name>
    <code>T1964-12</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">DEU</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">PHL</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1964-03-03</date_signed>
    <date_into_force/>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">de,en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <comments>Treaty was never ratified by Philippines</comments>
    <source>https://dserver.bundestag.de/btd/05/001/0500140.pdf</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>de,en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Treaty between the Federal Republic of Germany and the Republic of the Philippines&nbsp;concerning the Promotion and Protection of Investments</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>THE FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANY</p>
      <p>and</p>
      <p>THE REPUBLIC OF THE PHILIPPINES</p>
      <p>DESIRING to intensify economic cooperation between&nbsp;both States,</p>
      <p>INTENDING to create favourable conditions for investments&nbsp;by nationals and companies of either State in the&nbsp;territory of the other State, and</p>
      <p>RECOGNIZING that contractual protection of such investments&nbsp;will stimulate private business initiative and&nbsp;increase the prosperity of both nations,</p>
      <p>HAVE AGREED AS FOLLOWS:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall in its territory promote as&nbsp;far as possible investments of nationals or companies of&nbsp;the other Contracting Party and shall endeavour to admit&nbsp;such investments in accordance with its constitution,&nbsp;laws and regulations. lt shall accord such investments&nbsp;fair and equitable treatment.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2">
        <p>(1) Investments owned by, or under the effective control&nbsp;of, nationals or companies of either Contracting&nbsp;Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall&nbsp;not be accorded by that party treatment less favourable&nbsp;than it accords to any other similar investment in its&nbsp;territory.</p>
        <p>(2) Neither Contracting Party shall subject activities&nbsp;of nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party&nbsp;in connection with their investments, as well as the&nbsp;management, use or enjoyment of such investments, to&nbsp;conditions less favourable than it imposes on activities&nbsp;in connection with any other similar investment in its&nbsp;territory.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3">
        <p>(1) Investments of nationals or companies of either&nbsp;Contracting Party shall enjoy full protection and security&nbsp;in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(2) The investments of nationals or companies of either&nbsp;Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting&nbsp;Party shall not be expropriated except for the public&nbsp;benefit and against compensation. Such compensation&nbsp;shall represent the equivalent of the investment affected&nbsp;at the time of expropriation; it shall be actually realizable, freely transferable, and shall be marle without delay.</p>
        <p>Adequate provision shall have been made at or prior&nbsp;to the time of the deprivation for the determination and&nbsp;the giving of such compensation. The legality of any&nbsp;such deprivation and the amount of compensation shall&nbsp;be subject to review by due process of law.</p>
        <p>(3) Nationals or companies of either Contracting Party&nbsp;who owing to war or other armed conflict, revolution or&nbsp;revolt in the territory of the other Contracting Party suffer&nbsp;the loss of investments situated there, shall be accorded&nbsp;treatment no less favourable by such other Contracting&nbsp;Party than that party accords to any other&nbsp;similar investment in its territory as regards restitution,&nbsp;indemnification, compensation or other valuable consideration.&nbsp;With respect to the transfer of such payments&nbsp;each Contracting Party shall accord to the requests of&nbsp;nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party a&nbsp;treatment no less favourable than is accorded to comparable&nbsp;requests made by nationals or companies of any&nbsp;third State.</p>
        <p>(4) The provisions of paragraphs (1), (2) and (3) above&nbsp;shall likewise apply to returns from investments.</p>
        <p>(5) The nationals and companies of either Contracting&nbsp;Party shall enjoy most-favoured nation treatment in the territory of the other Contracting Party in respect of the&nbsp;matters provided for in the present Article.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4">
        <p>Either Contracting Party shall guarantee to the nationals&nbsp;or companies of the other Contracting Party the&nbsp;transfer of the capital, of the returns from it and, in the&nbsp;event of liquidation, of the net proceeds from such Iiquidation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5">
        <p>If a claim arising out of a guarantee given for an investment&nbsp;is asserted against a Contracting Party, the latter&nbsp;shall, without prejudice to its rights under Article 10,&nbsp;be authorized on the conditions stipulated by its predecessor&nbsp;in title to exercise the rights having been assigned&nbsp;to such party by law or having been ceded to it by the&nbsp;predecessor in title (devolved interest). As regards the&nbsp;transfer of payments to be made by virtue of the devolved&nbsp;interest to the Contracting Party concerned, paragraphs&nbsp;(2), (4) and (5) of Article 3 as well as Article 4&nbsp;shall apply mutatis mutandis.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6">
        <p>(1) To the extent that those concerned have not made&nbsp;another arrangement admitted by the appropriate agencies&nbsp;of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investment&nbsp;is situated, transfers under paragraphs (2), (3)&nbsp;or (4) of Article 3, under Article 4 or Article 5 shall be&nbsp;made without delay and at the rate of exchange effective&nbsp;for current transactions on the day the transfer is made.</p>
        <p>(2) The rate of exchange effective for current transactions&nbsp;shall be based on the par value agreed with the&nbsp;International Monetary Fund and shall lie within the&nbsp;margins above or below the parity admitted under Section&nbsp;3 of Article IV of the Articles of Agreement on the&nbsp;International Monetary Fund.</p>
        <p>(3) If at the date of transfer no rate of exchange within&nbsp;the meaning of paragraph (2) above exists in respect of&nbsp;the Contracting Party concerned, the official rate fixed&nbsp;by such Contracting Party for its currency in relation to&nbsp;the US dollar or to another freely convertible currency&nbsp;or to gold shall be applied. If no such rate has been&nbsp;fixed, the appropriate agencies of the Contracting Party&nbsp;in whose territory the capital is invested shall admit a&nbsp;rate of exchange that is fair and equitable.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7">
        <p>If the legislation of either Contracting Party or international obligations existing at present or established&nbsp;hereafter between the Contracting Parties in addition to&nbsp;the present Treaty result in a position entitling investments&nbsp;of nationals or companies of the other Contracting&nbsp;Party to a treatment more favourable than s provided&nbsp;for by the present Treaty, such position shall not be&nbsp;affected by the present Treaty Either Contracting Party&nbsp;shall observe any other obligation it may have entered&nbsp;into with regard to investments within its territory by&nbsp;nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8">
        <p>(1) The term "investment" shall comprise every kind&nbsp;of asset, and more particularly, though not exclusrvely:</p>
        <p>a) movable and immovable property as well as any other&nbsp;rights in rem, such as mortgages, liens, pledges,&nbsp;usufructs, and similar rights;</p>
        <p>b) shares or other kinds ol interest in companies;</p>
        <p>c) titles to money or to any performance having an economic&nbsp;value;</p>
        <p>d) copyrights, industrial property rights, technical processes,&nbsp;trade-names, and goodwill;</p>
        <p>e) business concessions under public law</p>
        <p>Any alteration of the form in which assets are invested&nbsp;shall not affect their classification as investment, provided&nbsp;that such alteration is not contrary to the admission,&nbsp;if any, granted in respect of the assets originally invested</p>
        <p>(2) The term "returns" shall mean the amounts yielded&nbsp;by an investment as net profit or interest for a specific&nbsp;period</p>
        <p>(3) The term "nationals" shall mean</p>
        <p>a) in respect of the Federal Republic of Germany: Germans&nbsp;within the meaning of the Basic Law for the&nbsp;Federal Republic of Germany;</p>
        <p>b) in respect of the Republic of the Philippines: citizens&nbsp;of the Philippines within the meaning of Article IV&nbsp;of the Constitution of the Republic of the Philippines</p>
        <p>(4) The term "companies" shall mean</p>
        <p>a) in respect of the Federal Republic of Germany: any&nbsp;juristic person as well as any commercial or other&nbsp;company or association with or without legal personality,&nbsp;having its seat in the territory of the Federal&nbsp;Republic of Germany and lawfully existing consistent&nbsp;with legal provisions, irrespective of whether the&nbsp;liability of its partners, associates or members is&nbsp;limited or unlimited and whether or not its activities&nbsp;are directed at profit;</p>
        <p>b) in respect of the Republic of the Philippines: any&nbsp;juristic person as well as any commercial or other&nbsp;company or association with or without legal personality,&nbsp;having its seat in the territory of the Republic&nbsp;of the Philippines and lawfully existing consistent&nbsp;with legal provisions, irrespective of whether&nbsp;the liability of its partners, associates or members islimited or unlimited and whether or not its activities&nbsp;are directed at profit</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9">
        <p>The present Treaty shall also apply to investments&nbsp;made prior to its entry into force by nationals or companies&nbsp;of either Contracting Party in the territory of the&nbsp;other Contracting Party in accordance with the latter's&nbsp;legislation. This provision shall not affect the Agreement&nbsp;of 27 February 1953 on German External Debts.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10">
        <p>(1) Disputes concerning the interpretation or application&nbsp;of the present Treaty should, if possible, be settled&nbsp;by the Governments of the two Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>(2) lf a dispute cannot thus be settled, it shall upon&nbsp;the request of either Contracting Party be submitted to&nbsp;an arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>(3) Such arbitral tribunal shall be constituted for each individual&nbsp;case as follows: each Contracting Party appointing&nbsp;one member, and these two members shall then&nbsp;agree upon a national of a third State as their chairman&nbsp;to be appointed by the Governments of the two Contracting&nbsp;Parties. Such members shall be appointed within two&nbsp;months, and such chairman within three months, after&nbsp;either Contracting Party has made known to the other&nbsp;Contracting Party that it wants the dispute to be submitted&nbsp;to an arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>(4) If the periods specified in paragraph (3) have not&nbsp;been observed, either Contracting Party may, in the absence&nbsp;of any other relevant arrangement, invite the President&nbsp;of the International Court of Justice to make the&nbsp;necessary appointments. If the President is a national of&nbsp;either Contracting Party or if he is otherwise prevented&nbsp;from discharging the said function, the Vice-President&nbsp;should make the necessary appointments. If the VicePresident&nbsp;is a national of either Contracting Party or if&nbsp;he, too, is prevented from discharging the said function,&nbsp;the member of the International Court of Justice next in&nbsp;seniority who is not a national of either Contracting&nbsp;Party should make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>(5) The arbitral tribunal shall reach its decisions by a&nbsp;majority of votes. Such decisions shall be binding. Each&nbsp;Contracting Party shall bear the cost of its own member&nbsp;and of its counsel in the arbitral proceedings; the fee of&nbsp;the chairman and the remaining costs shall be borne in&nbsp;equal parts by both Contracting Parties. The arbitral tribunal&nbsp;may make a different regulation concerning costs.&nbsp;In all other respects, the arbitral tribunal shall determine&nbsp;its own procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11">
        <p>The provisions of the present Treaty shall remain in&nbsp;force also in the event of any conflict arising between&nbsp;the Contracting Parties, without prejudice to the right of&nbsp;taking such temporary measures as are permitted under&nbsp;the general rules of international law. Measures of this&nbsp;kind shall cease to exist not later than on the date of the&nbsp;actual termination of the conflict, irrespective of whether&nbsp;or not diplomatic relations have been re-established.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12">
        <p>With the exception of the provisions in Number 10 of&nbsp;the Protocol, referring to air transport, the present Treaty&nbsp;shall also apply to Land Berlin, provided that the Government&nbsp;of the Federal Republic of Germany has not&nbsp;made a contrary declaration to the Government of the&nbsp;Republic of the Philippines within three months from the&nbsp;entry into force of the present Treaty.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13">
        <p>(1) The present Treaty shall be ratified, and the instruments&nbsp;of ratification shall be exchanged as soon as possible&nbsp;in Bonn.</p>
        <p>(2) The present Treaty shall enter into force one month&nbsp;after the day of exchange of the instruments of ratification.&nbsp;lt shall remain in force for a period of five years,&nbsp;and shall continue in force thereafter for an unlimited&nbsp;period except if denounced in writing by either Contracting&nbsp;Party one year before its expiration. After the expiry&nbsp;of the period of five years, the present Treaty may&nbsp;be denounced at any time by either Contracting Party&nbsp;upon giving one year's notice.</p>
        <p>(3) In respect of investments made prior to the date of&nbsp;termination of the present Treaty, the provisions of Articles&nbsp;1 to 12 shall continue to be effective for a further&nbsp;period of twenty years from the date of termination of&nbsp;the present Treaty.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>DONE at Manila on this Third day of March, Nineteen&nbsp;Hundred and Sixty-Four, in four originals, two each in&nbsp;the German and English languages, all four texts being&nbsp;equally authentic.</p>
      <p>For the Federal Republic of Germany:</p>
      <p>Franz Ferring</p>
      <p>Charg&#xE9; d'Affaires a.i. of the Federal Republic of Germany</p>
      <p>Dr. Kurt Daniel</p>
      <p>Ministerialdirigent in the Federal Ministry&nbsp;of Economic Affairs&nbsp;and Chairman of the German Delegation</p>
      <p>For the Republic of the Philippines:</p>
      <p>Librado D. Cayco</p>
      <p>Acting Secretary of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of the Philippines</p>
    </conclusion>
    <attachments>
      <div type="annex" title="Protocol">
        <p>On signing the Treaty concerning the Promotion and&nbsp;Protection of Investments, concluded between the Federal&nbsp;Republic of Germany and the Republic of the Philippines,&nbsp;the undersigned plenipotentiaries have, in addition,&nbsp;agreed on the following provisions which should be regarded&nbsp;as an integral part of the said Treaty:</p>
        <p>(1) To Article 1</p>
        <p>Investments made in accordance with the present&nbsp;Treaty and the laws and regulations of either Contracting&nbsp;Party within the area of application of that party's&nbsp;legal system by nationals or companies of the other&nbsp;Contracting Party, shall enjoy the full protection of the&nbsp;present Treaty.</p>
        <p>(2) To Articles 1 and 2</p>
        <p>Either Contracting Party reserves the right to require&nbsp;as a prerequisite to the admission of an investment within&nbsp;its territory a "certificate of admission" which it shall&nbsp;issue to investments it considers admissible pursuant to&nbsp;Article 1. Such certificate of admission may specify favours,&nbsp;immunities, and conditions deviating from Article&nbsp;2 which the admitting party grants or imposes in&nbsp;respect of the investment concerned. Such deviations&nbsp;shall only be effective if the deviating measures have&nbsp;been described in detail and laid down individually&nbsp;in the certificate of admission. The provisions of&nbsp;Article 2 shall to that extent not be applicable. It shall&nbsp;be understood that neither Contracting Party may specify&nbsp;conditions deviating from the other provisions of the&nbsp;Treaty.</p>
        <p>(3) To Article 2</p>
        <p>(a) Nothing in Article 2 shall be construed to entitle nationals&nbsp;or companies of the Federal Republic of Germany&nbsp;to the special rights and privileges accorded&nbsp;by the Republic of the Philippines to nationals and&nbsp;companies of the United States of America by virtue&nbsp;of existing agreements. Neither shall Article 2 be&nbsp;construed to entitle nationals or companies of the&nbsp;Federal Republic of Germany to any special right or&nbsp;privilege reserved by Article XIII, Section 1 and Article&nbsp;XIV, Section 8 of the Constitution of the Republic&nbsp;of the Philippines to citizens, corporations, associations&nbsp;or entities of the Republic of the Philippines.</p>
        <p>(b) To paragraph 1</p>
        <p>Either Contracting Party reserves the right not to&nbsp;recognize investments as within the meaning of "control"&nbsp;where the control was transferred to a national&nbsp;or company of the other Contracting Party for the&nbsp;purpose of enabling a national or company of a third&nbsp;State to obtain the privileges granted by the present&nbsp;Treaty.</p>
        <p>(c) To paragraph 2</p>
        <p>aa) The following shall more particularly, though not&nbsp;exclusively, be deemed " activity" within the meaning&nbsp;ol paragraph 2 of Article 2: the purchase of raw or auxiliary materials, of power or fuel, or of&nbsp;means of production or operation of any kind, the&nbsp;marketing of products inside or outside the country.&nbsp;Without prejudice to the right of either Contracting&nbsp;Party to deviate from Article 2 as provided&nbsp;for in Protocol Number 2, if the following&nbsp;measures are not applied under the same circumstances&nbsp;to any other similar investment in the territory&nbsp;of the Contracting Party concerned, such&nbsp;measures shall be deemed "conditions less favourable"&nbsp;within the meaning of paragraph 2 of Article&nbsp;2: any restriction or impeding of the activities&nbsp;referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 2 or of&nbsp;the use, management or enjoyment of an investment&nbsp;as well as any measure having similar effects. Measures that have to be taken for reasons&nbsp;of public security and order, public health or morality&nbsp;shall not be deemed "conditions less favourable".</p>
        <p>bb) Paragraph 2 of Article 2 shall not apply to entry,&nbsp;sojourn, and activity as an employee.</p>
        <p>(4) To Article 2 and paragraph 3 of Article 3</p>
        <p>The term "any other similar investment" as referred to&nbsp;in Article 2 and paragraph 3 of Article 3 shall be deemed&nbsp;to comprise any investment of a like nature in the territory&nbsp;of the Contracting Party concerned regardless of&nbsp;whether such investments have been made by nationals&nbsp;or companies of any third State or by any other individual&nbsp;or company.</p>
        <p>(5) To Article 3</p>
        <p>(a) Expropriation shall mean the taking in whole or in&nbsp;part of any investment as well as the restricting of&nbsp;any investment the effect of which is tantamount to&nbsp;such taking.</p>
        <p>(b) The provisions of paragraph 2 of Article 3 shall also&nbsp;apply to the transfer of an investment to public&nbsp;ownership as well as to the subjection of an investment&nbsp;to public control or to similar interventions by&nbsp;public authorities the effect of which is tantamount&nbsp;to expropriation as defined in paragraph (a) above.</p>
        <p>(c) Neither Contracting Party shall, in expropriating an&nbsp;investment, subject nationals or companies of the&nbsp;other Contracting Party to treatment less favourable&nbsp;than it imposes on its own nationals or companies.</p>
        <p>(6) T o Article 4</p>
        <p>"Liquidation" within the meaning of Article 4 shall be&nbsp;deemed to include any disposal effected for the purpose&nbsp;of completely or partly giving up the investment concerned.</p>
        <p>(7) To Article 6</p>
        <p>(a) A transfer shall be deemed to have been made "without&nbsp;delay" within the meaning of paragraph 1 of Article&nbsp;6 if made within such period as is normally required&nbsp;for the completion of transfer formalities. The&nbsp;said period shall commence on the day on which the&nbsp;relevant request has been submitted and may on no&nbsp;account exceed one year in respect of transfer of&nbsp;capital or liquidation proceeds as referred to in Article&nbsp;4, and six months in respect of all other transfers.</p>
        <p>(b) lf at the time of transfer a Contracting Party applies&nbsp;to current transactions a rate of exchange other than&nbsp;that referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 6 that has&nbsp;been expressly or tacitly approved by the International&nbsp;Monetary Fund such rate of exchange shall be&nbsp;applicable in the place of the rate of exchange referred&nbsp;to in paragraphs 2 and 3 of Article 6.</p>
        <p>(8) To Article 8</p>
        <p>(a) Returns from an investment as well as returns from&nbsp;re-invested returns shall enjoy the same protection&nbsp;as the original investment.</p>
        <p>(b) Without prejudice to any other method of determining&nbsp;nationality, any person in possession of a national&nbsp;passport issued by the appropriate authorities&nbsp;of either Contracting Party shall be deemed to be a&nbsp;national of that party.</p>
        <p>(9) To Article 10</p>
        <p>Nothing in Article 10 shall be construed to preclude&nbsp;nationals or companies of either Contracting Party from&nbsp;seeking relief in the local courts.</p>
        <p>(10) Either Contracting Party shall refrain from any&nbsp;measures which, contrary to the principles of free competition,&nbsp;may prevent or hinder sea-going vessels or aircraft&nbsp;of the other Contracting Party from participating&nbsp;in the transport of goods intended for, or of persons travelling&nbsp;in connection with, an investment within the&nbsp;meaning of the present Treaty. This also applies to goods&nbsp;acquired in the territory of either Contracting Party or&nbsp;of any third State with funds of an enterprise in which&nbsp;capital within the meaning of the present Treaty is invested;&nbsp;it applies furthermore to persons travelling on&nbsp;behalf of such an enterprise.</p>
        <p>DONE at Manila on this Third day of March Nineteen&nbsp;Hundred and Sixty-Four, in four originals, two each in&nbsp;the German and English languages, all four texts being&nbsp;equally authentic.</p>
        <p>For the Federal Republic of Germany:</p>
        <p>Franz F e r r i n g</p>
        <p>Charg&#xE9; d'Affaires a . i . of the Federal Republic of Germany</p>
        <p>Dr. Kurt Daniel</p>
        <p>Ministerialdirigent in the Federal Ministry&nbsp;of Economic Affairs and&nbsp;Chairman of the German Delegation</p>
        <p>For the Republic of the Philippines:</p>
        <p>Librado D. Cayco</p>
        <p>Acting Secretary of Foreign Affairs&nbsp;of the Republic of the Philippines</p>
      </div>
    </attachments>
    <attachments>
      <div type="annex" title="Exchange of Letters">
        <p>Manila, March 3, 1964</p>
        <p>Mr. Chairman,</p>
        <p>With reference to the Treaty between the Republic of&nbsp;the Philippines and the Federal Republic of Germany&nbsp;concerning the Promotion and Protection of Investments&nbsp;signed today, I have the honour to inform you that the&nbsp;following understanding has been reached in the course&nbsp;of our negotiations:</p>
        <p>For the purpose of promoting investments by German&nbsp;nationals or companies in the territory of the Republic&nbsp;of the Philippines, the Republic of the Philippines will&nbsp;grant in accordance with its laws the necessary permits&nbsp;to German nationals whose training or experience is&nbsp;specially required by an investment and who desire to&nbsp;enter and stay in the Republic of the Philippines to carry&nbsp;on activities in connection with such investment, except&nbsp;as reasons of public order and security, of public health&nbsp;or morality may warrant otherwise.</p>
        <p>I should be grateful if you could kindly confirm the&nbsp;understanding set out above.</p>
        <p>Accept, Mr. Chairman, the assurances of my highest&nbsp;consideration.</p>
        <p>Melchor P. Aquino</p>
        <p>Chairman of the Philippine Delegation</p>
        <p>The Chairman of the German Delegation</p>
        <p>Ministerialdirigent Dr. Kurt Daniel</p>
        <p>Manila</p>
        <p/>
        <p/>
        <p>The Chairman&nbsp;of the German Delegation</p>
        <p>Manila, March 3, 1964</p>
        <p>Mr. Chairman,</p>
        <p>I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter&nbsp;dated March 3, 1964, which reads as follows:</p>
        <p>"With reference to the Treaty between the Republic&nbsp;of the Philippines and the Federal Republic of Germany&nbsp;concerning the Promotion and Protection of Investments&nbsp;signed today, I have the honour to inform you&nbsp;that the following understanding has been reached in&nbsp;the course of our negotiations:</p>
        <p>For the purpose of promoting investmen ts by German&nbsp;nationals or companies in the territory of the Republic&nbsp;of the Philippines, the Republic of the Philippines&nbsp;will grant in accordance with its laws the necessary&nbsp;permits to German nationals whose training or&nbsp;experience is specially required by an investment and&nbsp;who desire to enter and stay in the Republic of the&nbsp;Philippines to carry on activities in connection with&nbsp;such investment, except as reasons of public order and&nbsp;security, of public health or morality may warrant&nbsp;otherwise.</p>
        <p>I should be grateful if you could kindly confirm the&nbsp;understanding set out above."</p>
        <p>I have the honour to confirm the understanding set out&nbsp;above.</p>
        <p>Accept, Mr. Chairman, the assurance of my highest&nbsp;consideration.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kurt Daniel</p>
        <p>The Chairman&nbsp;of the Philippine Delegation</p>
        <p>H. E. Ambassador Melchor P. Aquino</p>
        <p>Manila</p>
        <p/>
        <p/>
      </div>
    </attachments>
  </main>
</treaty>
