<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Indonesia - Switzerland BIT (1974)</name>
    <code>T1974-1</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">CHE</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">IDN</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1974-06-06</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1976-04-09</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated>2016-04-08</date_terminated>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">fr</orig_language>
    <termination_type>Unilaterally denounced</termination_type>
    <docreference>2007</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>Unilaterally denounced</IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{CHE,IDN}_1974-06-06.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>fr</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <relation type="IT_OVERLAP" document-code="T2018-43">EFTA - Indonesia FTA (2018)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Agreement between the Government of the Swiss Confederation and the Government of the Republic of Indonesia concerning the encouragement and mutual protection of investments</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>Signed on 6 February 1974</p>
      <p>Entry into force on 9 April 1976.</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall promote investments in its territory by nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party and admit such investments in accordance with its laws and regulations.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall protect within its territory investments made in accordance with its laws and regulations by nationals or companies of the other contracting party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3">
        <p>For the purposes of this Convention:</p>
        <p>a) The term "nationals" means:</p>
        <p>Natural persons who, according to the laws of each Contracting Party, shall be treated as nationals of that State.</p>
        <p>b) The term "companies" means:</p>
        <p>1. As regards the Swiss Confederation, communities, schools or foundations as well as having legal personality or limited partnerships and other communities of persons without legal personality incorporated under Swiss law or in which nationals of Switzerland, directly or indirectly, a preponderant interest;</p>
        <p>2. In respect of the Republic of Indonesia, any limited liability company established in the territory of the Republic of Indonesia or any community having legal personality incorporated according to its legislation.</p>
        <p>c) The term "investment" includes all categories of assets and in particular, though not exclusively.</p>
        <p>1. The movable and immovable property as well as any other rights in rem such as mortgages, liens, security interests, usufruits and similar rights;</p>
        <p>2. The actions or other forms of equity participation;</p>
        <p>3. Monetary claims and rights to any performance having an economic value;</p>
        <p>4. Property rights, copyrights, industrial processes, technical know-how, trademarks, trade names and goodwill;</p>
        <p>5. The concessions under public law, including extract concessions to search for or exploit natural resources.</p>
        <p>d) The term "proceeds" means:</p>
        <p>The amounts reported by an investment for a period specified in the form of net profit or interests.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall in its territory fair and equitable treatment to investments, property rights and interests of nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party and shall not hinder by unjustified discriminatory measures or the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment, increasing and, where appropriate, the liquidation of such investments and other securities.</p>
        <p>2. Each Contracting Party shall issue, insofar as an admission procedure is required, the required authorisations or companies to ensure that nationals of one contracting party to make investments in the territory of the other contracting party. authorizations shall also be issued if the laws or regulations of the contracting parties is required for the performance of contracts or technical assistance, administrative trade as well as well as for advice and other qualified persons of foreign nationality, provided that such contracts have been concluded or that such activities are carried out within the framework of investment permitted covered by this Convention.</p>
        <p>3. Subject to the provisions of the protocol attached to this Convention, the treatment accorded by each contracting party in its territory to investments by nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party shall be at least equal to that granted by each contracting party to its own nationals or companies or to the treatment accorded to nationals or companies of the most favoured nation, if it is more favorable.11</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party in whose territory investments have been made by nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party shall accord to such nationals or companies the free transfer.</p>
        <p>2. The technical or administrative procedures of such transfer shall be subject to the legislation or orders and regulations in force in the territory of which the investment has been made.</p>
        <p>3. The free transfer shall be granted for:</p>
        <p>a) The net profits, dividends, interests and other current income arising out of an investment;</p>
        <p>b) The depreciation and depreciation of capital and contractual payments;</p>
        <p>c) The proceeds of the partial or total liquidation of the investment, including possible value;</p>
        <p>d) Costs related to staff of foreign nationality and the management of the investment;</p>
        <p>e) Royalties and licence fees and other payments in respect of administrative and technical assistance provided by the staff of foreign nationality; and</p>
        <p>f) The authorized additional contributions of capital necessary for the maintenance or development of the investment.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6">
        <p>1. Neither Contracting Party shall take any measures of expropriation, nationalization or dispossession, other direct or indirect, against the investments, property rights or interests of nationals or companies of the other contracting party unless the measures are taken in the public interest, that the legal requirements are observed and that is made effective and adequate compensation.</p>
        <p>2. The amount of compensation, which shall be fixed at the time of expropriation, nationalization or dispossession, other shall be paid in the currency in which the investment authorization has been made.</p>
        <p>3. The compensation shall be paid without undue delay at the national or company which is entitled to this.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7">
        <p>1. This Convention shall also apply to investments in the territory of a Contracting Party in accordance with its legislation by nationals or companies of the other contracting party prior to the entry into force of this Convention, but not later than 10 January 1967, the date of the entry into force of the Indonesian Law on Foreign Investment Law No. 1, of 1967. "O 1" of 1967.</p>
        <p>2. In respect of investments made prior to 10 January 1967, each Contracting Party shall not be affected by the provisions of this Convention.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8">
        <p>The more favourable terms than those of this Agreement which have been agreed to by one of the Contracting Parties with nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party shall not be affected by this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9">
        <p>1. If any dispute should arise between the contracting parties concerning the interpretation or the implementation of the provisions of this Convention, it shall be settled through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2. If both contracting parties fail to settle the dispute shall be submitted, at the request of either contracting party to an arbitral tribunal composed of three members. each Contracting Party shall appoint an arbitrator. the two arbitrators so nominated shall appoint a chairman who shall be a national of a third State.</p>
        <p>3. If one of the Contracting Parties has not appointed its arbitrator and has not followed the invitation of the other contracting party to make such appointment within two months of the arbitrator shall be appointed, upon request by the latter Contracting Party by the President of the International Court of Justice.</p>
        <p>4. If the two arbitrators cannot reach an agreement about the choice of the Chairman within two months after their appointment the latter shall be appointed upon the request of either Contracting Party by the President of the International Court of Justice.</p>
        <p>5. If in the cases specified in paragraphs 3 and 4 of this article, the President of the International Court of Justice is prevented from exercising his mandate or if he is a national of either Contracting Party, the appointment shall be made by the Vice-President and if the latter is prevented or if he is a national of either Contracting Party, the appointment shall be made by the most senior member of the Court who is not a national of either of the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>6. Unless the Contracting Parties decide otherwise, the tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
        <p>7. The decisions of the Tribunal shall be taken by a majority of votes and shall be final and binding on the contracting parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10">
        <p>1. This Agreement shall enter into force on the day on which the two Contracting Parties shall have notified each other through diplomatic channels that their constitutional formalities required for the entry into force of this Agreement have been completed; it shall remain valid for a period of ten years.</p>
        <p>2. A Less than be denounced by either contracting party at least six months before the expiry of the current period, the validity of this Convention shall be deemed to be tacitly renewed for another period of five (5) years and so on.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11">
        <p>In the event of termination of this Agreement, the provisions laid down therein shall apply even during the period allowed investments admitted by the contracting parties before the denunciation of this Convention.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12">
        <p>This Agreement shall be applied provisionally by the contracting parties from the date of its signature.</p>
        <p>In WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned plenipotentiaries, being duly authorized, have signed this Convention.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>Desiring to enhance economic cooperation between the two States,</p>
      <p>In order to create favourable conditions for investment capital in both States and intensify cooperation between private enterprises of the two countries in the fields of economic productivity and science and technology,</p>
      <p>Recognizing the need to protect investments of nationals and companies of the two States and fostering the transfer of capital for the economic prosperity of both countries and nationals,</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
