<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Egypt - Morocco BIT (1976)</name>
    <code>T1976-5</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">EGY</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">MAR</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1976-06-06</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1978-09-07</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated>1998-07-01</date_terminated>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <termination_type>Replaced by new treaty</termination_type>
    <docreference>1374</docreference>
    <comments>New agreement signed on 14 May 1997. Source: Arbitration.org http://arbitration.org/sites/default/files/bit/egypt_morocco_arabic.pdf</comments>
    <source>https://manshurat.org/node/30509</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{EGY,MAR}_1976-06-03.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>Replaced by new treaty</IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>
    <relation type="IT_REPLACED_BY" document-code="T1997-89">Egypt - Morocco BIT (1997)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>
        <b>Agreement to encourage and protect investments between the Governments of the Arab Republic of Egypt and the Kingdom of Morocco</b>
      </p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Arab Republic of Egypt and the Kingdom of Morocco, desiring to consolidate the economiccooperation between the two countries, with the aim of creating favourableconditions for the investments made by the nationals of both countries withinthe territories of the other country, and taking into account the fact that theencouragement and protection of these investments will lead to an increase inthe flow of capital, thus achieving economic prosperity in the two countries,</p>
      <p>Realisingthat the protection of the reciprocal investments would stimulate private economicactivities, have agreed on the following:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1">
        <p>Each of theContracting Parties accepts and encourages in its territory, according to itslaws and regulations, the investments by the private or legal persons of the nationalsof the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2">
        <p>Each of theContracting Parties undertakes to provide full protection to the investments inits territory by the private or legal persons of the nationals of the otherContracting Party, and guarantees that these investments will be granted fairand equitable treatment.</p>
        <p>In order toachieve this purpose, each of the Contracting Parties shall grant to theaforementioned investments the benefit of the same treatment and protectiongranted to the investment by private or legal persons of its nationals, or nationalsof any third country.</p>
        <p>This treatmentdoes not include the benefits granted by any of the Contracting Parties, tonationals of a third country through its membership or its association with acustoms union, a free market, or a free trade area.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3">
        <p>Neither ofthe Contracting Parties shall take measures of expropriation or dispossessionin its territory with respect to the abovementioned investments, unless it isrequired for reasons of public interest.</p>
        <p>In thiscase, each of the Contracting Parties undertakes to pay a fair compensation to theconcerned investor from the other Party.</p>
        <p>In cases whichharm the investments of the nationals of any of the Contracting Parties in theterritory of the other Contracting Party, and with the exception of naturaldisasters, they are granted the same treatment that is extended by the other Contracting Party to its nationals in regard to the compensations, guarantees orany other procedures aimed at the reparation of damages and losses.</p>
        <p>The system oftransferring the compensation referred to in the second paragraph of this Articleis to be the same system defined by the requirements of Article 4 concerning the total or partial liquidationof investments.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4">
        <p>The two Contracting Parties shall allow the transfer of the following funds related tothe investments, in accordance with the legislation in effect at each of thetwo countries:</p>
        <p>Real netprofits, interest, and dividends attributable to the investors, whether a privateor legal persons belonging to one of the two countries.</p>
        <p>Proceeds resultingfrom the total or partial liquidation of the investments.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall act in accordance with its legislation to facilitatethe practice of the professional activity of the private persons belonging tothe other Contracting Party if such activity is necessary for the investmentsestablished in its territories.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6">
        <p>1. Both of thegovernments of the Contracting Parties shall work on the settlement of anydispute or difference of opinion regarding the interpretation or application ofthis agreement.</p>
        <p>2. In theevent of failure to reach an agreement, either of the two Contracting Partiesrefer the dispute to an arbitration tribunal.</p>
        <p>3. Theformation of the arbitration tribunal in each case, as follows:</p>
        <p>Each of the Contracting Parties chooses a member of the tribunal, and then the two members choose a presidentwhom should be a national of a third country and be appointed with the consentof the governments of the two Contracting Parties. The two members shall beappointed within two months and the president within three months from date ofeither party notifying the other party of its desire to refer the dispute to anarbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>4. In the event that the two Contracting Parties have not observed the durationsspecified in paragraph(3) , then either of the Contracting Parties can, in the absence of anyagreement to the contrary, invite the president of the International Court ofJustice to make the necessary appointments, and if the president of theInternational Court of Justice is a citizen of either of the Contracting Parties and he has an impediment toperforming this task, then  theVice-President is invited to carry out this role, and if the Vice-President wasa citizen of either of the two Contracting Parties, or if he  also has an impediment to performing thistask then the member of the International Court of Justice next in seniority isinvited to perform this task, provided that he is not a citizen of any of the Contracting Parties and has no impediment that prevents him from making the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>5. Thedecisions of the arbitral tribunal are issued by the majority of votes,and  its decision is final and binding,and each of the two Contracting Parties covers the expenses of its member in thetribunal while the president's expenses, as well as the rest of the expenses, areto be distributed over the two Contracting Parties. The arbitral tribunalhas the authority to determine the system for the distribution of expenses as well as determining the proceduralrules related to it.</p>
        <p>6. Prior tosubmitting any dispute to the arbitral tribunal, it is necessary for bothparties to exhaust all diplomatic and other means to reach a solution to theproblem subject of the dispute.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7">
        <p>Only the investment made by the investors after the entry into force of this Agreement shall benefit from the provisions of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8">
        <p>Each of the Contracting Parties shall notify the other party of the fulfilment of therequired procedures in its territories for the entry into force of thisAgreement, and this agreement shall operate from the date of the latest notification.</p>
        <p>This Agreement is concluded for a period of ten years, renewable for the same periodunless one of the two parties announces in writing its termination one year prior to the fulfilment of eachperiod.</p>
        <p>If terminated, this Agreement shall stay in effect in relation to the investmentsalready established for a period of ten years from the date of suchestablishment.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>Done in Cairo on Al-Haher; P7 Madi Al-Am: 51,399 (corresponding to 6 June 1976) in two original copies in the Arabic language, and was signed by representatives of the Government of the Arab Republic of Egypt and the Government of the Kingdom of Morocco.</p>
      <p>(Zakaria Dat Tawfiq Abdel Fattah)</p>
      <p>Minister for Foreign Affairs </p>
      <p>(Abdel Latif Al Ghassasi)</p>
      <p>Minister of Trade, Industry and Minerals on behalf of the Minister for Foreign Affairs</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
