<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Austria - Romania BIT (1976)</name>
    <code>T1976-16</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">AUT</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">ROU</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1976-09-30</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1977-11-08</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated>1997-07-01</date_terminated>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en,fr,de,ro</orig_language>
    <termination_type>Replaced by a new treaty</termination_type>
    <comments/>
    <source>UNTC</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>Replaced by a new treaty</IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en,fr,de,ro</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>TREATY BETWEEN THE REPUBLIC OF AUSTRIA AND THE SOCIALIST REPUBLIC OF ROMANIA CONCERNING THE RECIPROCAL PROMOTION, GUARANTEE AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Republic of Austria and</p>
      <p>The Socialist Republic of Romania,</p>
      <p>Purposing to intensify economic co-operation between the two States,</p>
      <p>Desiring to create favourable conditions for investments effected by Romanian juridical&nbsp;persons in Austria and by Austrian nationals and companies in Romania,</p>
      <p>Recognizing that the reciprocal promotion and protection of investments in accordance&nbsp;with this Treaty will help to stimulate business initiatives,</p>
      <p>Desiring to improve further the conditions for the execution of economic and industrial&nbsp;co-operation projects as regards protection of the interests of the partners in such&nbsp;projects, including legal protection for assets of every kind,</p>
      <p>Conscious of the importance of the contribution which improved business contacts&nbsp;and the resulting increased trust in business relations could make to the development of commercial and economic relations, as provided for in the Final Act of the Helsinki&nbsp;Conference on security and co-operation in Europe,</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="DEFINITIONS">
        <p>For the purposes of this Treaty:</p>
        <p>(1) "Investment" means possession of the following rights by an Austrian national&nbsp;or company in Romania or by a Romanian juridical person in Austria in accordance with&nbsp;the legislation of the two countries applicable to investments:</p>
        <p>(a) Ownership of, and other rights in rem relating to, movable property</p>
        <p>(b) Interests in limited-liability and joint-stock companies;</p>
        <p>(c) Copyrights, patents, trade marks, designs, know-how and goodwill;</p>
        <p>(d) Contractual claims to money or to performances having a monetary value, including&nbsp;tenant rights, with an effective period of validity of more than six months;</p>
        <p>(2) "Returns" means net amounts derived from an investment in the form of&nbsp;dividends, profits and other income. Undistributed returns shall be treated as an increase&nbsp;in assets and shall accordingly enjoy, as part of the investment, the same protection as&nbsp;the latter;</p>
        <p>(3) "Juridical person" means, in relation to the Socialist Republic of Romania, a&nbsp;Romanian enterprise constituted under Romanian law and having its seat in Romania;</p>
        <p>(4) "Companies" means, in relation to Austria, juridical persons and commercial&nbsp;partnerships constituted under Austrian law and having their seat in Austria, whether the&nbsp;liability of their partners or members is limited or unlimited and whether or not their&nbsp;activities are directed at profit. The term shall also include the State in respect of nonautonomous&nbsp;business enterprises carried on by the State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="PROMOTION AND GUARANTEES">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party shall admit in its territory, in accordance with its&nbsp;legislation, investments as provided for in this Treaty by Austrian nationals and companies&nbsp;in Romania or by Romanian juridical persons in Austria, shall promote such investments&nbsp;as far as possible and shall grant the necessary permits.</p>
        <p>(2) Investments effected in accordance with paragraph 1 shall enjoy in the territory&nbsp;of the other Contracting Party protection and guarantees as provided for in this Treaty.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="MOST-FAVOURED-NATION TREATMENT">
        <p>(1) In accordance with article 1, paragraph 1, each Contracting Party shall ensure&nbsp;in its territory that investments of Austrian nationals and companies in Romania or of&nbsp;Romanian juridical persons in Austria receive just and equitable treatment, which shall&nbsp;be at least equivalent to the treatment accorded by each Contracting Party to investments&nbsp;of third countries with which similar treaties are in force.</p>
        <p>(2) If the legislation of a Contracting Party, or international obligations existing&nbsp;at present or established hereafter between the Contracting Parties in addition to this&nbsp;Treaty, result in a more favourable r&#xE9;gime for investments as provided for in this Treaty,&nbsp;such r6gime shall not be affected by the present Treaty.</p>
        <p>(3) Each Contracting Party shall observe any other obligation which it may have&nbsp;assumed with regard to investments by Austrian nationals and companies in Romania or&nbsp;by Romanian juridical persons in Austria.</p>
        <p>(4) Obligations of the Contracting Parties as referred to in paragraph 3 shall include&nbsp;only obligations assumed by the competent agencies of the Contracting Parties in the&nbsp;exercise of public authority.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="EXPROPRIATION AND COMPENSATION">
        <p>(1) A Contracting Party shall expropriate investments effected in accordance with&nbsp;this Treaty only on the basis of its legislation and only in the public interest, against full&nbsp;compensation. Such compensation shall be made without delay and shall be actually&nbsp;realizable and freely transferable. Provision shall be made at the time of expropriation, for the determination and giving of the entire compensation.</p>
        <p>(2) For the purposes of paragraph 1, the term "expropriation" means the taking&nbsp;of an investment by an act of sovereign power-including nationalization-or any other&nbsp;act of sovereign power having the same or similar effects.</p>
        <p>(3) Austrian nationals and companies in Romania or Romanian juridical persons&nbsp;in Austria who, owing to war, armed conflict or acts which endanger public order, suffer&nbsp;the loss of investments situated in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall receive&nbsp;from that Contracting Party appropriate compensation, which shall cover the loss suffered.</p>
        <p>(4) In respect of all matters provided for in this article, the Contracting Parties&nbsp;shall accord to claims by Austrian nationals and companies in Romania or by Romanian&nbsp;juridical persons in Austria treatment no less favourable than is accorded to comparable&nbsp;claims by nationals, juridical persons and companies of third States.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="DISPUTES CONCERNING INVESTMENTS">
        <p>In the event of any dispute concerning compensation in accordance with article 4&nbsp;between an Austrian national or company in Romania or a Romanian juridical person in&nbsp;Austria and the Contracting Party in whose territory the investment was effected, either&nbsp;Party shall be entitled, once the final decision of the competent national authority has&nbsp;become effective, to submit the dispute for conciliation or arbitration to the International&nbsp;Centre for Settlement of International Disputes in accordance with the Convention on the&nbsp;settlement of investment disputes between States and nationals of other States of 18 March 1965.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="TRANSFER">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall, in accordance with its legislation in force, permit the&nbsp;transfer without delay, in the currency in which the investment was effected or in any&nbsp;other agreed convertible currency, of the following sums:</p>
        <p>(a) Returns from the investment and other income derived therefrom;</p>
        <p>(b) Proceeds from the liquidation of investments, and compensation in accordance with&nbsp;article 4;</p>
        <p>(c) Emoluments of persons who are in possession of a work permit in connection with&nbsp;an investment effected in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="CURRENCY">
        <p>(1) Unless those concerned in an investment have made some other arrangement&nbsp;approved by the competent agencies of the Contracting Party in whose territory the&nbsp;investment is situated, transfers under articles 4, 5 and 6 shall be made without delay in&nbsp;the freely convertible currency in which the investment was effected or in any other&nbsp;agreed freely convertible currency, at the rate of exchange in effect on the date of the&nbsp;transfer.</p>
        <p>(2) Transfers shall be deemed to have been made "without delay" within the meaning of paragraph 1 when made within such period as is normally required for the&nbsp;completion of transfer formalities. The said period shall commence on the date on which&nbsp;the application,, together with the necessary documents, has been duly submitted to the&nbsp;competent agency and shall under no circumstances exceed two months.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="RECOGNITION OF THE ASSUMPTION OF RIGHTS AND OBLIGATIONS">
        <p>If a Contracting Party, in accordance with its legal order, assumes on the basis of&nbsp;a guarantee the rights and obligations arising from an investment, including those relating&nbsp;to duties and taxes, the other Contracting Party shall recognize such assumption of rights and obligations.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="TAXES">
        <p>With the exception of articles 4 and 5, the provisions of this Treaty shall not apply&nbsp;in connection with the levying of taxes.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="AGREEMENTS CONCERNING COMPETENCE">
        <p>For the purpose of the assertion of claims arising from investments or the returns&nbsp;therefrom or of other claims having a direct legal connection with investments, the&nbsp;Contracting Parties shall recognize:</p>
        <p>1. Agreements in writing whereby the partners in an investment have subjected themselves,&nbsp;in respect of any civil or commercial case, to the competence of the courts of&nbsp;a Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>2. Agreements in writing whereby the partners have undertaken to submit all or some&nbsp;disputes that have arisen or may in future arise between them from a specific legal&nbsp;relationship, whether contractual or non-contractual, to an arbitral proceeding in the&nbsp;territory of a Contracting State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="ENFORCEABILITY OF DECISIONS">
        <p>(1) Decisions in a civil or commercial case rendered in the territory of a Contracting&nbsp;Party by a court which was competent pursuant to an agreement under article 10, paragraph&nbsp;1, shall be recognized and enforced in the territory of the other Contracting Party,&nbsp;provided that they fulfil the following conditions:</p>
        <p>1. Recognition or enforcement of the decision is not contrary to the public policy of the&nbsp;Contracting Party in whose territory it is to be recognized or enforced;</p>
        <p>2. The finality of the decision does not preclude its recognition or enforcement;</p>
        <p>3. The case in question was not within the exclusive competence of a court of the&nbsp;Contracting Party in whose territory the decision is to be recognized or enforced or&nbsp;of a court of a third State;</p>
        <p>4. In the case of a decision by default, the summons or writ instituting the proceedings&nbsp;was served in due time either on the party in default, against whom the decision is&nbsp;to be enforced, or on his representative; if service had to be effected in the territory&nbsp;of the Contracting Party in which the decision is to be enforced, this shall have been&nbsp;done in accordance with the procedures for judicial assistance;</p>
        <p>5. The decision has become final under the law of the Contracting Party in whose territory&nbsp;it was rendered; if enforcement is sought, the decision shall also be enforceable under&nbsp;the law.</p>
        <p>(2) Paragraph 1, subparagraphs 1, 2, 3 and 5, shall also apply to compositions&nbsp;with creditors made in the territory of the Contracting Party before a court which was&nbsp;competent pursuant to an agreement under article 10, paragraph 1.</p>
        <p>(3) Paragraph 1 shall also apply to arbitral awards made in the territory of a&nbsp;Contracting Party on the basis of an arbitration agreement under article 10, paragraph 2;&nbsp;paragraph 1, subparagraphs 1, 2, 3 and 5, shall also apply to a composition with creditors&nbsp;made in an arbitral proceeding, if such proceeding is based on an arbitration agreement&nbsp;under article 10, paragraph 2.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="PROCEDURAL PROVISIONS">
        <p>(1) The party requesting recognition or enforcement of a judicial decision shall&nbsp;produce:</p>
        <p>1. An officially signed and sealed copy of the decision showing beyond a doubt that the&nbsp;decision relates to a claim within the meaning of article 10;</p>
        <p>2. In the case of a decision by default, judicial certification of the manner and date of&nbsp;service of the summons or writ instituting the proceedings on the party in default;</p>
        <p>3. Judicial certification that the decision has become final and, where appropriate, is&nbsp;enforceable;</p>
        <p>4. The original or a certified copy of the agreement under article 10, paragraph 1.&nbsp;(2) If enforcement of a composition with creditors made before a court is requested,&nbsp;a copy of the composition, judicial certification that it is enforceable and the original or&nbsp;a certified copy of the composition under article 10, paragraph 1, shall be produced.</p>
        <p>(3) If recognition or enforcement of an arbitral award or enforcement of a composition&nbsp;with creditors made in an arbitral proceeding is requested, the Party shall produce the following documents:</p>
        <p>1. A copy of the arbitral award or of the composition;</p>
        <p>2. Certification that the arbitral award has become final and, where appropriate, is enforceable or that the composition is enforceable;</p>
        <p>3. In the case of a decision by default, certification of the manner and date of service&nbsp;of the summons or writ instituting the arbitral proceeding on the party in default;</p>
        <p>4. The original or a certified copy of the composition under article 10, paragraph 2.</p>
        <p>(4) Consideration of the request for recognition or enforcement shall be limited to&nbsp;the conditions specified in article 11 of this Treaty and the documents to be produced&nbsp;under this article. There shall be no review in excess of the foregoing.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13">
        <p>Obligations of the two Contracting Parties under multilateral agreements to which&nbsp;they are parties shall not be affected by articles 10 to 12.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="14" title="EXISTING INVESTMENTS">
        <p>This Treaty shall also cover investments which were effected by Austrian nationals and companies in Romania or by Romanian juridical persons in Austria, in accordance&nbsp;with the legislation of the other Contracting Party, in the territory of that Party prior to&nbsp;the entry into force of this Treaty.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="15" title="DISPUTES BETWEEN THE CONTRACTING PARTIES">
        <p>(1) In case of disputes concerning the interpretation or application of this Treaty,&nbsp;the Contracting Parties shall initiate consultations through the diplomatic channel with a&nbsp;view to achieving an amicable settlement.</p>
        <p>(2) If a dispute cannot be settled in this manner within one year from the date on&nbsp;which a Contracting Party has proposed to the other Contracting Party the initiation of&nbsp;the consultations referred to in paragraph 1, the dispute may, at the request of either&nbsp;Contracting Party, be submitted to an arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>(3) Such arbitral tribunal shall be constituted for each individual case as follows:&nbsp;each Contracting Party shall appoint one member and the two members shall agree on a&nbsp;chairman, who shall be a national of a third State and shall be appointed by the Governments&nbsp;of the two Contracting Parties. The members shall be appointed within two&nbsp;months, and the chairman within five months, from the date on which a Contracting&nbsp;Party has informed the other Contracting Party that it wishes to submit the dispute to an&nbsp;arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>(4) If the time-limits specified in paragraph 3 are not met, either Contracting Party&nbsp;may, in the absence of any other agreement, request the President of the International&nbsp;Court of Justice to make the necessary appointments. If the President is a national of&nbsp;either Contracting Party or if he is unable to act for any other reason, the Vice-President&nbsp;shall make the appointments. If the Vice-President is also a national of either Contracting&nbsp;Party or is also unable to act, the next most senior member of the International Court of&nbsp;Justice who is not a national of either Contracting Party shall make the appointments.</p>
        <p>(5) The arbitral tribunal shall decide disputes submitted to it in accordance with&nbsp;international law. The arbitral tribunal shall take its decisions by majority vote. Its&nbsp;decisions shall be binding.</p>
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall bear the expenses of its own member and the costs of&nbsp;its representation in the proceedings before the arbitral tribunal; the expenses of the&nbsp;chairman and the remaining costs shall be borne in equal parts by the two Contracting&nbsp;Parties.</p>
        <p>(6) The arbitral tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="16" title="FINAL PROVISIONS">
        <p>(1) This Treaty shall be ratified, and the instruments of ratification shall be exchanged&nbsp;at Bucharest.</p>
        <p>(2) This Treaty shall enter into force 60 days after the date of exchange of the&nbsp;instruments of ratification. It shall remain in force for a period of 10 years and shall&nbsp;thereafter be extended indefinitely, unless denounced in writing through the diplomatic&nbsp;channel by either Contracting Party one year before its expiry. After the expiry of the&nbsp;period of 10 years, the Treaty may be denounced at any time on one year's notice.</p>
        <p>(3) In respect of investments effected prior to the expiry of this Treaty and returns&nbsp;therefrom pertaining to the period of validity of this Treaty, the provisions of the Treaty&nbsp;shall continue to apply for a further period of 10 years from the date of expiry.</p>
      </div>
    </preamble>
    <conclusion>
      <p>DONE at Vienna, on 30 September 1976, in two original copies in the German and&nbsp;Romanian languages, both texts being equally authentic.</p>
      <p>For the Republic of Austria:</p>
      <p>E. BIELKA</p>
      <p>For the Socialist Republic of Romania:</p>
      <p>I. AVRAM</p>
      <p/>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
