<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>France - Indonesia BIT (1973)</name>
    <code>T1973-6</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">FRA</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">IDN</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1973-06-14</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1975-04-29</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated>2015-04-28</date_terminated>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en,fr</orig_language>
    <termination_type>Unilaterally denounced</termination_type>
    <comments/>
    <source>https://treaties.un.org/doc/publication/unts/volume%20985/volume-985-i-14398-english.pdf</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>Unilaterally denounced</IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{FRA,IDN}_1973-06-14.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en,fr</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <relation type="IT_OVERLAP" document-code="T1980-21">EEC - ASEAN Contries Cooperation Agreement (1980)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE FRENCH REPUBLIC AND THE REPUBLIC OF INDONESIA ON THE ENCOURAGEMENT AND PROTECTION OF FRENCH INVESTMENTS IN INDONESIA </p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the French Republic and the Government of the Republic of Indonesia, </p>
      <p>Desiring to reinforce economic cooperation between both States, and anxious to intensify cooperation between enterprises of both States, and more specifically with the purpose of promoting investments by French nationals or legal persons in the territory of the Republic of Indonesia by the insurance of such investments by the Government of the French Republic; </p>
      <p>Conscious of the contribution which can be made to this purpose by the conclusion of an agreement concerning the encouragement and protection of French investments in Indonesia; </p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows: </p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1">
        <p>The  Government  of the  French  Republic  shall  promote  as  far  as possible the investment of capital of French nationals or legal persons in the territory of Indonesia and the Government of the Republic of Indonesia shall admit  such in vestments  in  accordance with  its  legislation  and  administrative  procedure.</p>
        <p>The Government of the Republic of Indonesia shall accord to such French investments fair and equitable treatment for both the practice of professional activities related to these investments and for the management, operation, enjoyment and use of said investments. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2">
        <p>The  Government  of the  French  Republic,  after  having  examined each project of investment to be made in the territory of the Republic of Indonesia by French  nationals  or legal persons  according to  its  rules  and  procedures,  will  be  authorized  to  guarantee under  a contract of insurance with the French  investors  concerned,  provided  however  that  a  document  of admission  of the  French  investment has  been issued  by the Government of the  Republic  of Indonesia.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3.">
        <p>The document  of admission as  mentioned  in  the preceding Article 2 of this Agreement shall contain the terms and conditions under which the French investment  in  the  territory  of the  Republic  of Indonesia  has  to  be  made,  and  it  shall particularly  contain  the  right  of the  French  investor  concerned  to  have  recourse  to the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID), if in the case of a dispute between the French investor and the Government of the Republic of Indonesia no  amicable  solution  has  been  reached  within  five  months.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4.">
        <p>To  the investments  of French nationals  or legal persons  in  the territory of the Republic of Indonesia shall be accorded by the Indonesia Government a treatment, especially  in the field of  safety, protection and taxation, no less favourable than that which it  accords in its  territory to any similar investment made by its own nationals or legal persons, or by nationals or legal persons of third States, with due regard to the stipulations contained in the Protocol attached to the present Agreement and forming an integral part hereof. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5">
        <p>1. In the event that the French Government, pursuant to Article 2 of this Agreement,  makes payments to its nationals or legal persons under a guarantee it has assumed in  respect of an investment in the territory of the Republic of Indonesia,  the  Indonesian  Government  shall  recognize  that  the  French  Government becomes  by this  fact  fully subrogated with respect to the rights of those French na tionals  or legal  persons towards  the Government of the  Republic  of Indonesia.</p>
        <p>2. The said payments shall not affect the rights of the guaranteed French na- tional or legal person to have recourse to the International Centre for Settlement of In- vestment Disputes (ICSID) pursuant to Article 3 of this Agreement, or to pursue action brought before [the above-mentioned ICSID until the dispute is settled. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6.">
        <p>1. The  Government  of the  Republic  of  Indonesia  shall  not  take measures  of expropriation  or  of nationalization or any other measures the effect  of which,  either directly or indirectly,  is  to dispossess French nationals or legal persons of  their  investments  in  the  territory  of  the  Republic  of  Indonesia,  except  for  the public  benefit  without  aiming  particularly  at  French  investments  and  against  pay ment  of effective  and  adequate  compensation.</p>
        <p>2. Such compensation shall represent the commercial value of the investment at the time of expropriation, nationalization or dispossession, and it shall be actually realizable, freely transferable and be made without undue delay. </p>
        <p>3. Provisions shall be made in an appropriate manner at or prior to the time of expropriation, nationalization or dispossession for the determination and payment of such compensation. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7.">
        <p>The present Agreement shall apply only with respect to investments in projects made by French nationals or legal persons in the territory of the Republic of Indonesia which are insured for guarantee by the French Government and are ap proved in writing by a document of admission issued by the Government of the Re public  of Indonesia  pursuant  to  the Foreign  Capital  Investment  Law of  1967  (Law No.  1  of 1967)  as  subsequently  amended.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8">
        <p>1. Disputes  concerning  the  interpretation  or  implementation  of the present Agreement shall be settled by means of diplomatic negotiations between the  Governments  of both  Contracting  Parties.</p>
        <p>2. If both Contracting Parties are unable to reach an agreement within a period of five months, the dispute shall, upon request of either Contracting Party, be submitted to an arbitral tribunal composed of three members. Each Contracting Party shall appoint one arbitrator and these two arbitrators shall nominate a third arbitrator as chairman who shall be a national of a third State. </p>
        <p>3. If either Contracting Party has not appointed its arbitrator and has not followed the invitation of the other Contracting Party to make such appointment within two months, the arbitrator shall be appointed upon the request of that Contracting Party by the President of the International Court of Justice. </p>
        <p>4. Ifthe two arbitrators are unable to reach an agreement on the choice of the third arbitrator within two months after their appointment, the latter shall be appointed upon the request of either Contracting Party by the President of the International Court of Justice. </p>
        <p>5. If, in the cases specified under paragraphs 3 and 4 of this article, the Presi- dent of the International Court of Justice is prevented from carrying out the said function or if he is a national of either Contracting Party, the appointment shall be made by the Vice-President, and if the latter is prevented from carrying out the said function or if he is a national of either Contracting Party, the appointment shall be made by the next senior Judge of the Court who is not a national of either Contract- ing Party. </p>
        <p>6. Unless the Contracting Parties decide otherwise, the tribunal shall deter- mine its own procedure. </p>
        <p>7. The tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes and such decision shall be final and binding on both Contracting Parties. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9">
        <p>1. The present Agreement shall enter into force on the day the two Contracting Parties notify each other by diplomatic notes that their constitutional requirements  for  the  entering  into  force  of this  Agreement  have  been  fulfilled,  and shall remain  binding  for  a period of ten  years.</p>
        <p>2. Unless either of the Contracting Parties shall have given notice of termination six months before the expiry of the current period, the validity of the present Agreement shall be deemed to have been tacitly extended for a further period of each time ten years. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10.">
        <p>In  case  of termination  of  the  present  Agreement,  the  provisions thereof shall continue to be effective for the investments covered by this Agreement and admitted by the Contracting Party prior to the notification of termination of the present  Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11">
        <p>The Contracting Parties will apply provisionally the present Agreement  as  from the  date of its  signature</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned Representatives, duly authorized thereto, have signed the present Agreement. </p>
      <p>Done at Jakarta, this 14th day of June, 1973, in four originals, two in English and two in French, each text being equally authentic. </p>
      <p>For the Government of the French Republic:</p>
      <p>[Signed] G. NEBOT</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of Indonesia: </p>
      <p>[Signed]&nbsp; G. Roesli Noor </p>
    </conclusion>
    <attachments>
      <div type="annex" title="PROTOCOL">
        <p>At the time of signing the Agreement between the Government of the French Republic and the Government of the Republic of Indonesia concerning the Encouragement and Protection of French Investments in Indonesia, the undersigned Plenipotentiaries have in addition agreed on the following understanding which shall be regarded as an integral part of the said Agreement: </p>
        <p>Referring to Article 4 </p>
        <p>For the purpose of protecting the Indonesian national economy, the Government of the Republic of Indonesia may have already granted some facilities to Indonesian enterprises which do not fully apply to French enterprises. When, pursuant to present or subsequent legislation, the Indonesian Government extends additional advantages to Indonesian investors, the Indonesian Government shall, in order to ensure fair and equitable treatment, grant identical or compensating facilities to French investors engaged in similar economic activities. </p>
        <p>In any case the Government of the Republic of Indonesia will grant to the French investments the same treatment that it has extended or will extend to the in- yestment of the most favoured third country. </p>
        <p>Done at Jakarta, this 14th day of June, 1973, in four originals, two in English and two in French, each text being equally authentic. </p>
        <p>For the Government of the French Republic:</p>
        <p>[Signed] G. NEBOT</p>
        <p>For the Government of the Republic of Indonesia:&nbsp; </p>
        <p>[Signed]  G. Roesli Noor </p>
        <p>Vol. 985, 1-14398 </p>
      </div>
      <div type="annex" title="Exchange of Letters">
        <p>DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS REPUBLIC OF INDONESIA </p>
        <p>Jakarta, 14 June, 1973 </p>
        <p>Dear Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of even date which reads as follows: </p>
        <p>"I have the honour to inform you that the document of admission as mentioned under Article 2 of the Agreement between the Republic of Indonesia and the French Republic on the Encouragement and Protection of French Investments in Indonesia of today'&#x80;&#x99;s date will include at least the following provisions with regard to transfers: </p>
        <p>1. The Government of the Republic of Indonesia assumes the right of free transfer of: </p>
        <p>-&#x80;&#x94; the net profits, interests, dividends, royalties, depreciation of capital assets and any current income, accruing from investment activities of French nationals; </p>
        <p>-&#x80;&#x94; the proceeds of the total or partial liquidation of any investment, including possible increases in or addition to this investment, made by French investors; </p>
        <p>-&#x80;&#x94; an appropriate portion of the earnings of French nationals who are authorized to work in the territory of the Republic of Indonesia; </p>
        <p>- funds in repayment of loans recognized as investments; </p>
        <p>-&#x80;&#x94; the compensation for dispossession mentioned in Article 6 of the abovementioned Agreement, </p>
        <p>2. The abovementioned transfers shall be made at the official exchange rate applicable on the date of transfer without any discriminatory rate of exchange for this kind of operations. </p>
        <p>3. Any authorization to transfer shall be issued, and any transfer shall be carried out, without undue restriction and without delay, in conformity with the most favourable relevant rules in force in the territory of the Republic of Indonesia. </p>
        <p>I shall be grateful to receive your confirmation of the abovementioned understanding reached between our two Delegations. </p>
        <p>Accept, Sir, the renewed assurances of my highest consideration." </p>
        <p>I have the honour to confirm the abovementioned understanding reached between our two Delegations, </p>
        <p>Accept, Sir, the renewed assurances of my highest consideration, </p>
        <p>[Signed] </p>
        <p>G. Roesli Noor </p>
        <p>Chairman of the Indonesian Delegation </p>
        <p>Mr. G. Nebot </p>
        <p>Chairman of the French Delegation </p>
        <p>Jakarta </p>
        <p/>
      </div>
    </attachments>
  </main>
</treaty>
