<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Saint Lucia - United Kingdom BIT (1983)</name>
    <code>T1983-9</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">GBR</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">LCA</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1983-01-18</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1983-01-18</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>2871</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{GBR,LCA}_1983-01-18.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T2008-19">CARIFORUM - EC EPA (2008)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND AND THE GOVERNMENT OF SAINT LUCIA FOR THE PROMOTION AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTs</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and the Government of Saint Lucia;</p>
      <p>Desiring to create favourable conditions for greater investment by nationals and companies of the one State in the territory of the other State;</p>
      <p>Recognising that the encouragement and reciprocal protection under international agreement of such investments will be conducive to the stimulation of individual business initiative and will increase prosperity in both States;</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>(a)  &#x2018; investment ' means every kind of asset and in particular, though not exclusively, includes: movable and immovable property and any other property rights such as mortgages liens or pledges; shares, stock and debentures of companies or interests in the property of such companies; claims to money or to any performance under contract having a financial value; intellectual property rights and goodwill; business concessions conferred by law or under contract, including concessions to search for, cultivate, extract or exploit natural resources;(i) Movable and immovable property and any other property rights such as mortgages liens or pledges;</p>
        <p>(ii) Shares, stock and debentures of companies or interests in the property of such companies;</p>
        <p>(iii) Claims to money or to any performance under contract having a financial value;</p>
        <p>(iv) Intellectual property rights and goodwill;</p>
        <p>(v) Business concessions conferred by law or under contract, including concessions to search for, cultivate, extract or exploit natural resources;</p>
        <p>(b)  &#x2018; returns ' means the amounts yielded by an investment and in particular, though not exclusively, includes profit, interest, capital gains, dividends, royalties or fees;</p>
        <p>(c)  &#x2018; nationals ' means: in respect of the United Kingdom: physical persons deriving their status as United Kingdom nationals from the law in force in the United Kingdom; in respect of Saint Lucia: physical persons deriving their status as citizens of Saint Lucia under the Citizenship of Saint Lucia Act, 1979 (No. 7 of 1979);(i) In respect of the United Kingdom: physical persons deriving their status as United Kingdom nationals from the law in force in the United Kingdom;</p>
        <p>(ii) In respect of Saint Lucia: physical persons deriving their status as citizens of Saint Lucia under the Citizenship of Saint Lucia Act, 1979 (No. 7 of 1979);</p>
        <p>(d) &#x2018; companies ' means: in respect of the United Kingdom: corporations, firms or associations incorporated or constituted under the law in force in any part of the United Kingdom or in any territory to which this Agreement is extended in accordance with the provisions of Article 11; in respect of Saint Lucia: corporations, firms or associations incorporated or constituted under the Commercial Code of Saint Lucia, or other companies as may be agreed by Exchange of Notes between the Contracting Parties;(i) In respect of the United Kingdom: corporations, firms or associations incorporated or constituted under the law in force in any part of the United Kingdom or in any territory to which this Agreement is extended in accordance with the provisions of Article 11;</p>
        <p>(ii) In respect of Saint Lucia: corporations, firms or associations incorporated or constituted under the Commercial Code of Saint Lucia, or other companies as may be agreed by Exchange of Notes between the Contracting Parties;</p>
        <p>(e) &#x2018; territory ' means: in respect of the United Kingdom: Great Britain and Northern Ireland and any territory to which this Agreement is extended in accordance with the provisions of Article 11; in respect of Saint Lucia: the whole of Saint Lucia.(i) In respect of the United Kingdom: Great Britain and Northern Ireland and any territory to which this Agreement is extended in accordance with the provisions of Article 11;</p>
        <p>(ii) In respect of Saint Lucia: the whole of Saint Lucia.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and protection of investment">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party shall encourage and create favourable conditions for nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party to invest capital in its territory, and, subject to its right to exercise powers conferred by its laws, shall admit such capital.</p>
        <p>(2) Investments of nationals or companies of either Contracting Party shall at all times be accorded fair and equitable treatment and shall enjoy full protection and security in the territory of the other Contracting Party. Neither Contracting Party shall in any way impair by unreasonable or discriminatory measures the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal of investments in its territory of nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party. Each Contracting Party shall observe any obligation it may have entered into with regard to investments of nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="National treatment and most-favoured-nation provisions">
        <p>(1) Neither Contracting Party shall in its territory subject investments or returns of nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party to treatment less favourable than that which it accords to investments or returns of its own nationals or companies or to investments or returns of nationals or companies of any third State.</p>
        <p>(2) Neither Contracting Party shall in its territory subject nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party, as regards their management, use, enjoyment or disposal of their investments, to treatment less favourable than that which it accords to its own nationals or companies or to nationals or companies of any third State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Compensation for losses">
        <p>(1) Nationals or companies of one Contracting Party whose investment in the territory of the other Contracting Party suffer losses owing to war or other armed conflict, revolution, a state of national emergency, revolt insurrection or riot in the territory of the latter Contracting Party shall be accorded by the latter Contracting Party treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or other settlement, no less favourable than that which the latter Contracting Party accords to its own nationals or companies or to nationals or companies of any third State.</p>
        <p>(2) Without prejudice to paragraph (1) of this Article, nationals and companies of the one Contracting Party who in any of the situations referred to in that paragraph suffer losses in the territory of the other Contracting Party resulting from</p>
        <p>(a) Requisitioning of their property by its forces or authorities, or</p>
        <p>(b) Destruction of their property by its forces or authorities which was not caused in combat action or was not required by the necessity of the situation,</p>
        <p>Shall be accorded restitution or adequate compensation. Resulting payments shall be freely transferable.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Expropriation">
        <p>(1) Investments of nationals or companies of either Contracting Party shall not be nationalised, expropriated or subjected to measures having effect equivalent to nationalisation or expropriation (hereinafter referred to as &#x2018; expropriation ') in the territory of the other Contracting Party except for a public purpose related to the internal needs of that Party and against prompt, adequate and effective compensation. Such compensation shall amount to the market value of the investment expropriated immediately before the expropriation or impending expropriation became public knowledge, shall include interest at a normal commercial rate until the date of payment, shall be made without delay, be effectively realisable and be freely transferable. The national or company affected shall have a right under the law of the Contracting Party making the expropriation, to prompt review, by a judicial or other independent authority of that Party, of his or its case and of the valuation of his or its investment in accordance with the principles set out in this paragraph.</p>
        <p>(2) Where a Contracting Party expropriates the assets of a company which is incorporated or constituted under the law in force in any part of its own territory, and in which nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party own shares, it shall ensure that the provisions of paragraph (1) of this Article are applied to the extent necessary to guarantee prompt adequate and effective compensation in respect of their investment to such nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party who are owners of those shares.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Repatriation of investment and returns">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall in respect of investments guarantee to nationals or companies of the other Contracting Party the unrestricted transfer to the country where they reside of their investments and returns, subject to the right of each Contracting Party in exceptional balance of payments difficulties and for a limited period to exercise equitably and in good faith powers conferred by its laws. Such powers shall not however be used to impede the transfer of returns, and as regards the proceeds of the sale or the liquidation of the investment the actual transfer may be spread over as few years as possible, but not more than five years. Transfers of currency shall be effected without delay in the convertible currency in which the capital was originally invested or in any other convertible currency agreed by the investor and the Contracting Party concerned. Unless otherwise agreed by the investor transfers shall be made at the rate of exchange applicable on the date of transfer pursuant to the exchange regulations in force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Exceptions">
        <p>The provisions in this Agreement relative to the grant of treatment not less favourable than that accorded to the nationals or companies of either Contracting Party or of any third State shall not be construed so as to oblige one Contracting Party to extend to the nationals or companies of the other the benefit of any treatment, preference or privilege resulting from</p>
        <p>(a) Any existing or future customs union or similar international agreement to which either of the Contracting Parties is or may become a party; or</p>
        <p>(b) Any international agreement or arrangement relating wholly or mainly to taxation or any domestic legislation relating wholly or mainly to taxation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of disputes between an investor and a host state">
        <p>(1) Disputes between a national or company of one Contracting Party and the other Contracting Party concerning an obligation of the latter under this Agreement in relation to an investment of the former which have not been amicably settled shall after a period of three months from written notification of a claim be submitted to international arbitration if either party to the dispute so wishes.</p>
        <p>(2) Where the dispute is referred to international arbitration, the investor and the Contracting Party concerned in the dispute may agree to refer the dispute either to:</p>
        <p>(a) The International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (having regard to the provisions, where applicable, of the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and National of other States, opened for signature at Washington DC on 18 March 1965 ((1))</p>
        <p>And the Additional Facility for the Administration of Conciliation, Arbitration and Fact Finding Proceedings); or</p>
        <p>(b) The Court of Arbitration of the International Chamber of Commerce; or</p>
        <p>(c) An international arbitrator or ad hoc arbitration tribunal to be appointed by a special agreement or established under the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law</p>
        <p>If after a period of three months from written notification of the claim there is no agreement to an alternative procedure, the parties to the dispute shall be bound to submit it to arbitration under the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law as then in force. The parties to the dispute may agree in writing to modify these Rules.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>(1) Disputes between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or application of this Agreement should, if possible, be settled through the diplomatic channel.</p>
        <p>(2) If a dispute between the Contracting Parties cannot thus be settled, it shall upon the request of either Contracting Party be submitted to an arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>(3) Such an arbitral tribunal shall be constituted for each individual case in the following way. Within two months of the receipt of the request for arbitration, each Contracting Party shall appoint one member of the tribunal Those two members shall then select a national of a third State who on approval by the two Contracting Parties shall be appointed Chairman of the tribunal. The Chairman shall be appointed within two months from the date of appointment of the other two members.</p>
        <p>(4) If within the periods specified in paragraph (3) of this Article the necessary appointments have not been made, either Contracting Party may, in the absence of any other agreement, invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make any necessary appointments. If the President is a national of either Contracting Party or if he is otherwise prevented from discharging the said function, the Vice-President shall be invited to make the necessary appointments. If the Vice-President is a national of either Contracting Party or if he too is prevented from discharging the said function the Member of the International Court of Justice next in seniority who is not a national of either Contracting Party shall be invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>(5) The arbitral tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Such decision shall be binding on both Contracting Parties. Each Contracting Party shall bear the cost of its own member of the tribunal and of its representation in the arbitral proceedings; the cost of the Chairman and the remaining costs shall be borne in equal parts by the Contracting Parties. The tribunal may, however, in its decision direct that a higher proportion of costs shall be borne by one of the two Contracting Parties, and this award shall be binding on both Contracting Parties. The tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Subrogation">
        <p>It either Contracting Party makes payment under an indemnity it has given in respect of an investment or any part thereof in the territory of the other Contracting Party, the latter Contracting Party shall recognise</p>
        <p>(a) The assignment, whether under law or pursuant to a legal transaction, of any right or claim from the party indemnified to the former Contracting Party (or its designated Agency), and</p>
        <p>(b) That the former Contracting Party (or its designated Agency) is entitled by virtue of subrogation to exercise the rights and enforce the claims of such a party.</p>
        <p>The former Contracting Party (or its designated Agency) shall accordingly if it so desires be entitled to assert any such right or claim to the same extent as its predecessor in title either before a Court or tribunal in the territory of the latter Contracting Party or in any other circumstances. If the former Contracting Party acquires amounts in the lawful currency of the other Contracting Party or credits thereof by assignment under the terms of an indemnity, the former Contracting Party shall be accorded in respect thereof treatment not less favourable than that accorded to the funds of companies or nationals of the latter Contracting Party or of any third State deriving from investment activities similar to those in which the party indemnified was engaged. Such amounts and credits shall be freely available to the former Contracting Party concerned for the purpose of meeting its expenditure in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Territorial extension">
        <p>At the time of signature of this Agreement, or at any time thereafter, the provisions of this Agreement may be extended to such territories for whose international relations the Government of the United Kingdom are responsible may be agreed between the Contracting Parties in an Exchange of Notes.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Entry into force">
        <p>This Agreement shall enter into force on signature.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Duration and termination">
        <p>This Agreement shall remain in force for a period of ten years. Thereafter it shall continue in force until the expiration of twelve months from the date on which either Contracting Party shall have given written notice of termination to the other. Provided that in respect of investments made whilst the Agreement is in force its provision shall continue in effect with respect to such investments for a period of twenty years after the date of termination and without prejudice to the application thereafter of the rules of general international law.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion/>
    <attachments>
      <p>In witness whereof the undersigned, duly authorised thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done in duplicate at Castries this 8th day of January 1983.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the United kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland:</p>
      <p>DUNROSSIL</p>
      <p>For the Government of Saint Lucia:</p>
      <p>J. COMPTON</p>
      <p>(1)  Treaty Series No. 25 (1967), Cmnd. 3255.</p>
    </attachments>
  </main>
</treaty>
