<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Senegal - Tunisia BIT (1984)</name>
    <code>T1984-18</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">SEN</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">TUN</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1984-05-17</date_signed>
    <date_into_force/>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">fr</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>2887</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>1985-05-07, approved by Senegal, http://www.dri.gouv.sn</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{SEN,TUN}_1984-05-17.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>fr</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T1981-11">OIC Investment Agreement (1981)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT</p>
      <p>Between the Government of the Republic of Tunisia and the Government of the Republic of Senegal on the Reciprocal Promotion and Protection of Investments</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>Between</p>
      <p>On the one hand, the Government of the Republic of Tunisia</p>
      <p>And</p>
      <p>The Government of the Republic of Senegal</p>
      <p>On the other hand,</p>
      <p>Hereinafter referred to as "Contracting Parties"</p>
      <p>-  Desiring to strengthen their economic relations and to intensify cooperation between the two countries with a view to promoting their development;</p>
      <p>-  Convinced that reciprocal protection of investments under a bilateral agreement is likely to stimulate private economic initiative and increase the prosperity of both countries;</p>
      <p>-  Aware of the need to accord fair and equitable treatment to investments of nationals of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>(A)  "Investments" means assets of any kind constituted or recognized in the host country in accordance with its laws and regulations, including but not limited to the following:</p>
        <p>(i)  movable and immovable property and any other proprietary right, and any security interest therein, such as mortgages, liens and pledges;</p>
        <p>(ii)  - the securities, shares, units and obligations</p>
        <p>Companies;</p>
        <p>(iii)  - claims and any interest for a consideration arising out of a contract;</p>
        <p>(iv)  - copyrights, intellectual property rights, technical processes and tangible and intangible assets of goodwill;</p>
        <p>(v)  - commercial concessions conferred by law or contract, including concessions for the research, extraction or exploitation of natural resources, conferring on their beneficiaries a legal position of some duration.</p>
        <p>(B)  - "Income" means income resulting from an investment and, in particular, any profits, profits, interests, dividends or royalties, without limiting the foregoing.</p>
        <p>(C)  - "Nationals" means:</p>
        <p>(i)  - as regards the Republic of Tunisia, natural persons of Tunisian nationality and any legal person having its seat in the territory of the Republic of Tunisia and in which the Tunisian interests are substantial.</p>
        <p>(ii)  in the case of the Republic of Senegal, natural persons of Senegalese nationality and any legal person whose registered office is in Senegal and in which Senegalese interests are substantial.</p>
        <p>(E)  - "Territory" means:</p>
        <p>(i)  - in the case of the Republic of Tunisia, the territory of the Republic of Tunisia;</p>
        <p>(ii)  in the case of the Republic of Senegal, the territory of the Republic of Senegal.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and protection of investments">
        <p>(1)  Each Contracting Party shall encourage nationals of the other Contracting Party to invest capital in its territory, in particular by creating favorable conditions for the realization of investments and the entry of such capital in accordance with its legislation.</p>
        <p>(2)  Investments by one of the Contracting Parties under the conditions laid down by the national legislation of the host country shall be accorded fair and equitable treatment.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="National treatment and most-favored-nation clause">
        <p>(1)  Neither Contracting Party shall impose on its territory investments or income of nationals of the other Contracting Party less favorable treatment than that which it accords to investments or returns of its own nationals or to investments Or income of nationals of any third State.</p>
        <p>(2)  - No Contracting Party shall subject, in its territory, to the nationals of the other Contracting Party, with respect to the management, use, enjoyment or disposal of their investments Less favorable than that which it grants to its own nationals or to third-country nationals.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Compensation">
        <p>For nationals of a Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party suffer damage to the armed forces or other armed conflicts, national emergency revolution, revolt, insurrection, riot or effect In the territory of the other Contracting Party, the treatment accorded by the latter Contracting Party, as regards restitution,</p>
        <p>Compensation, compensation or any other form of settlement shall not be in my favor save that which it grants to its own nationals or to the nationals of any third State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Expropriation">
        <p>-   The nationals of the one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall not be subject to a ratio. - - - - - - - - - -</p>
        <p>No other measures having a similar effect, unless the following conditions are met:</p>
        <p>-  Measures taken in the general interest and in the forms required by law;</p>
        <p>(B)  - the hovels are not discriminatory and</p>
        <p>(C)  the measures shall be accompanied by prompt, adequate and effective payment of an allowance which shall be freely transferable between the territories of the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>(2)  - The provisions of paragraph 1 of this Article shall also apply to income derived from an investment.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Repatriation of investments and incomes">
        <p>(1)  - Subject to its laws and regulations, each</p>
        <p>Of the Contracting Parties shall permit the transfer in any convertible currency without delay:</p>
        <p>(A)  net profits, dividends, royalties, technical assistance and service fees, interest and all other current income arising from investments of nationals of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(B)  the proceeds of the total or partial liquidation of an investment made by nationals of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(C)  repayments of loans contracted by nationals of one Contracting Party to nationals of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(D)  - remuneration of nationals of the other Contracting Party who are authorized to work in its territory in connection with an investment.</p>
        <p>(2)  Each Contracting Party undertakes to accord to transfers referred to in paragraph (1) of this Article treatment no less favorable than that accorded to transfers arising out of investments made by nationals of any third State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Delegation">
        <p>Notwithstanding the provisions of Article 3 of this</p>
        <p>Agreement, a Contracting Party which has entered into a treaty relating to the formation of a customs union or a free trade area or any other treaty establishing economic and / or monetary cooperation with one or more other States shall be free to grant Treatment more favorable to investments by the State or States which are also Parties to the Treaty or by nationals of some of those States. A Contracting Party shall also be free to grant more favorable treatment to investments made by nationals of other States if such treatment is provided for in bilateral agreements concluded with such States prior to the date of signature of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of disputes between a contracting party and a national of the other contracting party">
        <p>(1)  - Where a dispute concerning an investment arises between a Contracting Party and a national of the other Contracting Party in the territory of that Party, the Parties to the dispute shall first of all resolve the dispute by Consultation and negotiation.</p>
        <p>(2)  - If the dispute can not be settled in accordance with paragraph (1) of this Article within three (3) months from the date of submission of the request for consultation and negotiation, Each Contracting Party agrees to submit to the International Center for the Settlement of Investment Disputes with a view to settlement by conciliation or arbitration in accordance with the Convention for</p>
        <p>The Settlement of Disputes Relating to Investments between States and Nationals of other States, opened for signature at Washington on 18 March 1965, any dispute of a legal nature between that Contracting Party and a national of the other Contracting Party relating to an investment Carried out by that national in the territory of the first Contracting Party concerned.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>(1)  Disputes between the Contracting Parties relating to the interpretation or application of this Agreement shall, as far as possible, be settled through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>(2)  - When a dispute between the Contracting Parties can not be settled by this means, it shall be submitted, at the request of one of the Contracting Parties, to an arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>(3)  - The arbitral tribunal shall be constituted, in each individual case, as follows:</p>
        <p>-  Within two months of receipt of a request for arbitration, each Contracting Party shall appoint a member of the tribunal;</p>
        <p>-  These two members shall then choose a national of a third State who, with the agreement of the two Contracting Parties, shall be appointed President of the tribunal;</p>
        <p>-  The President shall be appointed within two months of the date of appointment of the two members.</p>
        <p>(4)  If, within the time limits specified in paragraph (3) of this Article, the necessary appointments have not been made, either Contracting Party may, in the absence of any other agreement, Invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>If the President is a national of one of the Contracting Parties or if he is unable for any reason to perform the said functions, the Vice-President shall be invited to make the necessary appointments. If the Vice-President is a national of one of the Contracting Parties or if he is also prevented from performing the said functions, the member of the International Court of Justice immediately following in the hierarchical order who is not a national of the One of the Contracting Parties is invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>(5)  - The arbitral tribunal shall decide by a majority of votes. Its decision shall be binding on both Contracting Parties. Each Contracting Party shall bear the costs of its own member of the tribunal and of its representation during the arbitral proceedings; The costs of the Chairman and the other costs shall be borne equally by the Contracting Parties. It is, however, permissible for the court to order in its decision that a greater proportion of the costs be borne by one of the two Parties, and this award is binding on both Parties. The court rules its own procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Subrogation">
        <p>If a Contracting Party, by virtue of a guarantee given for an investment in the territory of the other Contracting Party, makes payments to its own nationals, the other Contracting Party, without prejudice to the rights of the first Contracting Party arising out of Article 9 shall recognize the transfer by law or contract of all rights and claims of such nationals to the first Contracting Party and the subrogation in its favor of all such rights and claims Transmitted) that the first Contracting Party shall be permitted to exercise to the same extent as its predecessor. With regard to the transfer of payments to the Contracting Party in question by virtue of the transmission of the rights, the provisions of paragraphs 2 and 3 of Article 3 and of Article 4 shall apply mutatis mutandis.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Coming into force">
        <p>This Agreement shall enter into force on the day on which the two Contracting Parties have notified each other that the constitutional requirements for this purpose have been fulfilled.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Duration, amendment and denunciation">
        <p>(1)  This Agreement shall remain in force for a period of ten years and shall remain in force unless terminated in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 3 of this Article.</p>
        <p>(2)  - Each Contracting Party may submit to the other Contracting Party, in writing and through diplomatic channels, draft amendments to this Agreement. Any amendment agreed upon by the two Parties shall enter into force in accordance with the provisions of article 11 above.</p>
        <p>(3)  Either Contracting Party may, by giving one year's written notice to the other Contracting Party, terminate this Agreement at the end of the initial ten years.</p>
        <p>(4)  - In respect of investments made or acquired before the date of termination of this Agreement and to which this Agreement otherwise applies, the provisions of all other Articles of this Agreement shall continue to apply for a period Ten years after the date of denunciation.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>In witness whereof, the respective Plenipotentiaries have signed the present Agreement.</p>
      <p>DONE in duplicate at TUNIS, on 17 May 1984, in the French language, both texts being equally authentic.</p>
      <p>For the Government Republic of Tunisia</p>
      <p>B&#xE9;ji CAID ESSEBSI, Minister of Foreign Affairs</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of Senegal</p>
      <p>Moustapha NIASSE,</p>
      <p>Minister of State for Foreign Affairs</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
