<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Malaysia - Peru BIT (1995)</name>
    <code>T1995-189</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">MYS</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">PER</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1995-10-13</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1995-12-25</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">es</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>2474</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{MYS,PER}_1995-10-13.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>es</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <relation type="IT_OVERLAP" document-code="T2016-6">Trans-Pacific Partnership (TPP) (2016)</relation>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T2018-4">Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership (CPTPP)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Agreement between the Government of the Republic of Peru and the Government of Malaysia for the Promotion and Protection of Investments&nbsp;</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Republic of Peru and the Government of Malaysia, hereinafter referred to as the "" contracting parties;</p>
      <p>Desiring to expand and deepen economic and industrial cooperation on a long-term basis and, in particular, to create favourable conditions for investments of investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other contracting party;</p>
      <p>Recognizing the need to protect investments made by investors of both parties and to stimulate the flow of capital and individual business initiatives with a view to promoting the economic prosperity of both contracting parties;</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>1. For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>(a) "investment" and active means every kind and in particular, though not exclusively, includes: ownership of movable and immovable property and other property rights such as mortgages, liens or pledges; actions, assets and debentures of companies or interests in the property of such companies; rights to funds used to create a financial value or rights to any provision quetenga a financial value; Intellectual Property Rights rights, including copyrights, patents, trademarks, trade names, industrial designs, trade secrets, processes and knowhow and rights of key; business concessions conferred by law or under contract, including concessions deprospecci&#xF3;n, exploration and exploitation of natural resources; the ownership of movable and immovable property and other property rights such as mortgages, liens or pledges; actions, assets and debentures of companies or interests in the property of such companies; rights to funds used to create a financial value or rights to any provision quetenga a financial value; Intellectual Property Rights rights, including copyrights, patents, trademarks, trade names, industrial designs, trade secrets, processes and knowhow and rights of key; business concessions conferred by law or under contract, including concessions deprospecci&#xF3;n, exploration and exploitation of natural resources;</p>
        <p>b) "returns" means the amounts obtained by an investment and in particular, though not exclusively, include profit, capital gains, interest, dividends, royalties or fees;</p>
        <p>(c) The term "investor "means: any natural person possessing the citizenship of deuna or permanently residing in the territory of the Contracting Party in accordance with its laws; or any company, partnership, trust company, Joint Venture Corporation, oempresa organization duly incorporated or constituted in accordance with the applicable laws of that Contracting Party; any natural person possessing the citizenship of deuna or permanently residing in the territory of the Contracting Party in accordance with its laws; or any company, partnership, trust company, Joint Venture Corporation, oempresa organization duly incorporated or constituted in accordance with the applicable laws of that Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>(d) "territory" means: with respect to the Republic of Peru, in addition to the area within its domain eldominio adjacent territorial sea and the airspace over which the Republic of Peru exercises sovereignty and jurisdiction according to its constitution; with regard to Malaysia, all land territory consisting of the Federation of Malaysia, marterritorial, bed and its subsoil and airspace. with respect to the Republic of Peru, in addition to the area within its domain eldominio adjacent territorial sea and the airspace over which the Republic of Peru exercises sovereignty and jurisdiction according to its constitution; with regard to Malaysia, all land territory consisting of the Federation of Malaysia, marterritorial, bed and its subsoil and airspace.</p>
        <p>(e) "freely usable currency" means the United States dollar, the pound sterling, the German, French franc, the Japanese yen or any other currency that is widely used to make payments for international transactions and widely traded in the principal international exchange markets.</p>
        <p>2. The term "investment" mentioned in paragraph (1) shall apply only to all investments are made in accordance with the laws, regulations and national policies of the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>Any alteration of the form in which assets are invested shall not affect their classification as investment, provided that such alteration is not contrary to the approvals granted, if any, to the originally invested assets.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="The Reciprocal Promotion and Protection of Investments">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall promote and create favourable conditions for investors of the contracting otraparte on capital investment in its territory and, subject to its right to exercise powers conferred by its laws, regulations and national policies, shall admit such investments.</p>
        <p>2. Investments of investors of each Contracting Party shall at all times be tratojusto and equitable and shall enjoy full protection and security in the territory of the other contracting party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="The Most Favoured Nacion Clausula">
        <p>1. Investments made by investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of the contracting otraparte receive treatment Fair and Equitable Treatment and not less favourable than that accorded to investments made by investors of any third State.</p>
        <p>2. Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of the other States suffer losses owing to war or other armed conflict, revolution, state of national emergency, revolt, riot or insurrection in the territory of the latter Contracting Party, shall be accorded such treatment by other contracting party, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or other payment, not less favourable than that which the Contracting Party accords to investors of any third State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Exceptions">
        <p>The provisions of this Agreement relating to the grant of not less favourable treatment than that accorded to investors of any third State shall not be construed so as to oblige one contracting party to extend to investors of the other Contracting Party the benefit of any treatment, preference or privilege resulting from:</p>
        <p>(a) Any existing or future customs union or free trade area or a common market or a monetary unauni&#xF3;n or similar international agreement or other forms of regional cooperation to which either of the contracting parties is or may become a party; or</p>
        <p>(b) The adoption of an agreement designed to lead to the formation or extension of such a union o&#xE1;rea within a reasonable period of time; or</p>
        <p>(c) Any international agreement or arrangement relating wholly or mainly to taxation or domestic cualquierlegislaci&#xF3;n relating wholly or mainly to taxation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Expropriation">
        <p>Neither of the Contracting Parties shall take measures of expropriation or nationalization or any other measures having an effect equivalent to expropriation or nationalization of an investor against the investments of the other contracting party except under the following conditions:</p>
        <p>(a) Where the measures are taken for a public or lawful purpose and under due process of law;</p>
        <p>(b) Where the measures are not discriminatory;</p>
        <p>(c) Where the measures are accompanied by provisions for the payment of prompt, adequate yefectiva compensation. such compensation shall correspond to the market value of the affected investments immediately before the measure of dispossession was publicly known, and shall be freely transferable in freely usable currencies from the contracting party. any unreasonable delay in payment of compensation shall include interest at a normal commercial rate agreed upon by both parties unless such rate is prescribed by law.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Transfers">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall, subject to its laws, regulations and national policies, without reasonable retrasono freely usable currency transfer of:</p>
        <p>(a) The capital of the investment and reinvestment;</p>
        <p>(b) The net profits, dividends, royalties, technical assistance and technical fees, interest and otrosingresos, investment flows accruing from any of the investors of the other contracting party;</p>
        <p>(c) The proceeds from the total or partial liquidation of any investment made porinversionistas of the other contracting party;</p>
        <p>(d) Funds in repayment of loans given by investors of one Contracting Party ainversionistas of the other Contracting Party which both contracting parties have recognized as investments; and</p>
        <p>(e) The net earnings and other compensations of investors of one Contracting Party who sepermite that are used in connection with an investment in the territory of the other contracting party.</p>
        <p>2. The rate of exchange applicable to transfers referred to in paragraph 1 of this article, the exchange rate deber&#xE1;ser flow from the date of shipment.</p>
        <p>3. The Contracting Parties undertake to accord to transfers referred to in paragraph 1, esteart&#xED;culo treatment as favourable as that accorded to transfers originating from investments made by investors of any third State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Settlement of Investment Disputes between a Contracting Party and an Investor of the other Contracting Party">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party consents to submit to the International Centre for Settlement of Investment diferenciasrelativas (hereinafter the "") Centre for settlement by conciliation or arbitration under the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of Other States done at Washington DC on 18 March 1965, any dispute arising between an investor that Contracting Party and of the other contracting party, including:</p>
        <p>(i) An obligation assumed by that Contracting Party of the investor with the other party contratanterespecto to an investment made by that investor; or</p>
        <p>(ii) An alleged breach of any right conferred by this Agreement or created with respectoa an investment made by that investor.</p>
        <p>2. A company which is incorporated or constituted under the laws in force in the territory of a Member States and before which such a dispute arises the majority of shares are owned by investors of the other Contracting Party, shall be treated in accordance with article 25 (2) (b) of the Convention, as a company of the other contracting party.</p>
        <p>3.</p>
        <p>(I) If any dispute referred to in paragraph 1 elinversionista arise and the Contracting Party concerned shall seek to resolve the dispute through consultations and negotiations. if the dispute cannot thus be settled within six months, then if the investor concerned also consents in writing to submit the dispute to the Centre for settlement by conciliation or arbitration under the Convention, either of the Contracting Parties to the dispute may initiate the procedure by sending a request in this regard to the Secretary General of the Centre as provided for in articles 28 and 36 of the Convention, provided that the investor concerned has not submitted the dispute to the courts of justice or administrative tribunals or agencies with competent court of the Contracting Party which is a party to the dispute.</p>
        <p>(II) In case of disagreement as to whether conciliation or arbitration is the more appropriate procedure, the investor concerned shall prevail. the Contracting Party which is party in the dispute shall not raise an objection as defence, or right of appeal at any stage of the arbitration proceedings or of the fact that the investor who is the other party to the dispute has received or will receive, pursuant to a contract of insurance or guarantee, indemnification or other compensation for all or part of its losses or damages.</p>
        <p>4. Neither Contracting Party shall pursue through diplomatic channels cualquiercontroversia referred to the Centre unless:</p>
        <p>(I) The Secretary-General of the Centre or a conciliation commission or an arbitral tribunal constituted por&#xE9;l, decides that the dispute is not within the jurisdiction of the Centre; or</p>
        <p>(II) The other Contracting Party shall not be subjected to comply with any award or not by an arbitral tribunal.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of Disputes between Contracting Party">
        <p>1. Disputes between the contracting parties concerning the interpretation or application of presenteconvenio shall, as far as possible, be settled through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2. If a dispute between the contracting parties cannot be settled in this way within six months, plazode shall, at the request of either party, be submitted to an arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>3. Such an arbitral tribunal shall be constituted for each individual case in the following way: losdos within months of receipt of the request for arbitration, each Contracting Party shall appoint one member of the Tribunal. those two members shall then select a national of a third State who on approval of the two Contracting Parties shall be appointed Chairman of the Tribunal. the Chairman shall be appointed within two months from the date of appointment of the other two members.</p>
        <p>4. If within the periods specified in paragraph 3 of this article the necessary nombramientosno have been made, either Contracting Party may, in the absence of any other agreement, invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointments. if the President is a national of either Contracting Party or if he is said otherwise prevented from exercising the function, the Vice-President shall be invited to make the necessary appointments. if the Vice-President is a national of either Contracting Party or if he too is prevented from exercising the function, the said member of the International Court of Justice next in seniority who is not a national of either party shall be invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>5. The arbitral tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. such decision ser&#xE1;obligatoria for both contracting parties. each Contracting Party shall bear the cost of its own member of the Tribunal and of its representation in the arbitral proceedings; the cost of the Chairman and the remaining costs shall be borne in equal parts by the contracting parties. the Tribunal may, however, decide that a higher proportion of costs shall be borne by one of the two contracting parties, and this decision shall be binding on both contracting parties. the tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Subrogacion">
        <p>If a Contracting Party makes a payment to any of its investors under a guarantee it has accorded in respect of an investment, the other Contracting Party shall, without prejudice to the rights of the latter Contracting Party under Article 7, recognize the transfer of any right or title to the investors of such latter Contracting Party and the latter subrogation of the contracting party to any right or title.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Application to Investments">
        <p>1. This Agreement shall apply to investments made in the territory of either partescontratantes in accordance with its laws, regulations or national policies, by investors of the other contracting party before and after the entry into force of this Agreement.</p>
        <p>2. This Agreement shall also apply to disputes arising after its entry into force, queest&#xE9;n related to investments made by investors of one Contracting Party in accordance with the laws, regulations and national policies of the host State of investment before the entry into force of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Entry Into Force , Duration and Termination of the Agreement">
        <p>1. This Agreement shall enter into force thirty (30) days later after the date on which the Governments of the Contracting Parties have notified each other that their constitutional requirements for the Entry into Force of this Agreement have been fulfilled. the later date shall refer to the date on which the last notification has been sent.</p>
        <p>2. This Agreement shall remain in force for a period of ten (10) years and shall continue in force unless seadenunciado in accordance with paragraph (3) of this article.</p>
        <p>3. Any Contracting Party may by written notification to the other party contratantecon one year in advance, terminate this Agreement at the end of the initial (10) years or at any time thereafter.</p>
        <p>4. With respect to investments made or acquired prior to the date of termination of esteconvenio, all of the provisions of the other articles of this Agreement shall continue to be effective for a period of ten (10) years from such date of termination.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>In WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done in duplicate at Lima on 13 October 1995, Bahasa Malaysia, Spanish and English languages, all texts being equally authentic. in case of divergence of interpretation, the English text shall prevail.</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
