<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>BLEU - Brazil BIT (1999)</name>
    <code>T1999-23</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">BLEU</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">BRA</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1999-01-06</date_signed>
    <date_into_force/>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en,pt</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>465</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad; JusMundi</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{BLEU,BRA}_1999-01-06.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en,pt</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE BELGO-LUXEMBURG ECONOMIC UNION AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE FEDERATIVE REPUBLIC OF BRAZIL&nbsp;ON THE RECIPROCAL PROMOTION&nbsp;AND&nbsp;PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>THE GOVERNMENT OF THE KINGDOM OF BELGIUM, acting both in its own name and in the name of&nbsp;the Government of the Grand-Duchy of Luxembourg, by virtue of existing agreements,&nbsp;the Walloon Government,&nbsp;the Flemish Government,&nbsp;and the Government of the Region of Brussels-Capital,&nbsp;on the one hand,</p>
      <p>and</p>
      <p>THE GOVERNMENT OF THE FEDERATIVE REPUBLIC OF BRAZIL,&nbsp;on the other hand,</p>
      <p>(hereinafter referred to as &#x201C;the Contracting Parties&#x201D;),</p>
      <p>DESIRING to strengthen their economic cooperation by creating favourable conditions for&nbsp;investments by nationals of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party,</p>
      <p>HAVE agreed as follows</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement,</p>
        <p>The term &#x201C;investors&#x201D; shall mean :</p>
        <p>a) the &#x201C;nationals&#x201D;, i.e. any natural person who, according to the legislation of the Kingdom&nbsp;of Belgium, of the Grand-Duchy of Luxemburg or of the Federative Republic of Brazil,&nbsp;is considered as a citizen of the Kingdom of Belgium, of the Grand-Duchy of&nbsp;Luxemburg or of the Federative Republic of Brazil respectively ;</p>
        <p>b) the &#x201C;companies&#x201D;, i.e. any legal person constituted in accordance with the legislation of&nbsp;the Kingdom of Belgium, of the Grand-Duchy of Luxemburg or of the Federative&nbsp;Republic of Brazil and having its registered office in the territory of the Kingdom of&nbsp;Belgium, of the Grand-Duchy of Luxemburg or of the Federative Republic of Brazil&nbsp;respectively.</p>
        <p>2. The term &#x201C;investments&#x201D; shall mean any kind of assets and any direct or indirect contribution&nbsp;in cash, in kind or in services, invested or reinvested in any sector of economic activity.</p>
        <p>The following shall more particularly, though not exclusively, be considered as investments&nbsp;for the purpose of this Agreement :</p>
        <p>a) movable and immovable property as well as any other rights in rem, such as mortgages,&nbsp;liens, pledges, usufruct and similar rights ;</p>
        <p>b) shares, corporate rights and any other kind of shareholdings, including minority or&nbsp;indirect ones, in companies constituted in the territory of one Contracting Party ;</p>
        <p>c) bonds, claims to money and to any performance having an economic value ;</p>
        <p>d) copyrights, industrial property rights, technical processes, trade names and good will ;</p>
        <p>e) concessions granted under public law or under contract, including concessions to&nbsp;explore, develop, extract or exploit natural resources.</p>
        <p>Changes in the legal form in which assets and capital have been invested or reinvested shall&nbsp;not affect their designation as &#x201C;investments&#x201D; for the purpose of this Agreement.</p>
        <p>3. The term &#x201C;incomes&#x201D; shall mean the proceeds of an investment and shall include in particular,&nbsp;though not exclusively, profits, interests, capital increases, dividends, royalties and payments.</p>
        <p>4. The term &#x201C;territory&#x201D; shall apply to the territory of the Kingdom of Belgium, to the territory of&nbsp;the Grand-Duchy of Luxemburg and to the territory of the Federative Republic of Brazil, as&nbsp;well as to the maritime areas, i.e. the marine and underwater areas which extend beyond the&nbsp;territorial waters, of the States concerned and upon which the latter exercise, in accordance&nbsp;with international law, their sovereign rights and their jurisdiction for the purpose of&nbsp;exploring, exploiting and preserving natural resources.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion of investments">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall promote investments in its territory by investors of the other Contracting Party and shall accept such investments in accordance with its legislation.</p>
        <p>2. In particular, each Contracting Party shall authorize the conclusion and the fulfilment of&nbsp;licence contracts and commercial, administrative or technical assistance agreements, as far as&nbsp;these activities are in connection with such investments.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Protection of investments">
        <p>1. All investments, whether direct or indirect, made by investors of one Contracting Party shall&nbsp;enjoy a fair and equitable treatment in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>2. Except for measures required to maintain public order, such investments shall enjoy&nbsp;continuous protection and security, i.e. excluding any unjustified or discriminatory measure&nbsp;which could hinder, either in law or in practice, the management, maintenance, use,&nbsp;possession or liquidation thereof.</p>
        <p>3. The treatment and protection referred to in paragraphs 1 and 2 shall at least be equal to those&nbsp;accorded by the latter Contracting Party to investments made by its own investors or investors&nbsp;of a third State, whichever is the most favourable to the investor concerned, and shall in no&nbsp;case be less favourable than those recognized under international law.</p>
        <p>4. However, the provisions of paragraphs 1 to 3 of this Article shall not cover any treatment,&nbsp;preference or privilege granted by one Contracting Party to investments made by the investors&nbsp;of a third State pursuant to its participation in or association with a free trade zone, a customs&nbsp;union, a common market or any other form of regional economic organization.</p>
        <p>5. The provisions of paragraphs 1 to 3 of this Article shall not be construed so as to oblige one&nbsp;Contracting Party to extend to investors of the other Contracting Party any treatment, preference or privilege resulting, from any international agreement or arrangement relating wholly or mainly to taxation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Deprivation and limitation of ownership">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party undertakes not to adopt any measure of expropriation or&nbsp;nationalization or any other measure having, the effect of directly or indirectly dispossessing&nbsp;the investors of the other Contracting Party of their investments in its territory.</p>
        <p>2. If reasons of public purpose, security or national interest require a derogation from the&nbsp;provisions of paragraph 1, the following conditions shall be complied with :</p>
        <p>a) the measures shall be taken under due process of law ;</p>
        <p>b) the measures shall be neither discriminatory, nor contrary to any specific commitments ;</p>
        <p>c) the measures shall be accompanied by provisions for the payment of an adequate and&nbsp;effective compensation.</p>
        <p>3. Such compensation shall amount to the actual value of the investments on the day before the&nbsp;measures were taken or became public.</p>
        <p>Such compensation shall be paid in the currency of the State of which the investor is a&nbsp;national or in any other convertible currency. It shall be paid without delay and shall be freely&nbsp;transferable. It shall bear interest at LIBOR from the date of the determination of its amount&nbsp;until the date of its payment.</p>
        <p>4. Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments suffer losses owing to war or other&nbsp;armed conflict, revolution, a state of national emergency or revolt in the territory of the other&nbsp;Contracting Party shall be granted by the latter Contracting Party a treatment, as regards&nbsp;restitution, indemnification, compensation or other settlement, at least equal to that which the&nbsp;latter Contracting Party grants to the investors of the most favoured nation.</p>
        <p>5. In respect of matters dealt with in this Article, each Contracting Party shall grant to the&nbsp;investors of the other Contracting Party a treatment which shall at least be equal to that&nbsp;granted in its territory to the investors of the most favoured nation. This treatment shall in no&nbsp;case be less favourable than that recognized under international law.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Transfers">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall grant to investors of the other Contracting Party the free transfer&nbsp;of all payments relating to an investment, including more particularly :</p>
        <p>a) amounts necessary for establishing, maintaining or expanding the investment ;</p>
        <p>b) amounts necessary for payments under a contract, including amounts necessary for&nbsp;repayment of loans, royalties and other payments resulting from licences, franchises,&nbsp;concessions and other similar rights, as well as salaries of expatriate personnel ;</p>
        <p>c) proceeds from investments ;</p>
        <p>d) proceeds from the total or partial liquidation of investments, including capital gains or&nbsp;increases in the invested capital ;</p>
        <p>e) compensation paid pursuant to Article 4.</p>
        <p>2. The nationals of each Contracting Party who have been authorized to work in the territory of&nbsp;the other Contracting Party in connection with an investment shall also be permitted to&nbsp;transfer an appropriate portion of their earnings to their country of origin.</p>
        <p>3. Transfers shall be made in a freely convertible currency at the rate applicable on the day&nbsp;transfers are made to cash transactions in the currency used.</p>
        <p>4. Each Contracting Party shall issue the authorizations required to ensure that the transfers can&nbsp;be made without undue delay, with no other expenses than the usual taxes and costs.</p>
        <p>5. The guarantees referred to in this Article shall at least be equal to those granted to the&nbsp;investors of the most favoured nation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Subrogation">
        <p>1. If one Contracting Party or any public institution or a designated agency of this Party pays&nbsp;compensation to its own investors pursuant to a guarantee providing coverage for an&nbsp;investment, the other Contracting Party shall recognize that the former Contracting Party or&nbsp;the public institution or agency concerned is subrogated into the rights of the investors.</p>
        <p>2. As far as the transferred rights are concerned, the other Contracting Party shall be entitled to&nbsp;invoke against the insurer who is subrogated into the rights of the indemnified investors the&nbsp;obligations of the latter under law or contract.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Applicable regulations">
        <p>If an issue relating to investments is covered both by this Agreement and by the national legislation&nbsp;of one Contracting Party or by international conventions, existing or to be subscribed to by the&nbsp;Parties in the future, the investors of the other Contracting Party shall be entitled to avail themselves&nbsp;of the provisions that are the most favourable to them.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Specific agreements">
        <p>1. Investments made pursuant to a specific agreement concluded between one Contracting Party&nbsp;and investors of the other Party shall be covered by the provisions of this Agreement and by&nbsp;those of the specific agreement.</p>
        <p>2. Each Contracting Party undertakes to ensure at all times that the commitments it has entered&nbsp;into vis-a-vis investors of the other Contracting Party shall be observed.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Settlement of investment disputes">
        <p>1. Any investment dispute between an investor of one Contracting Party and the other&nbsp;Contracting Party shall be notified in writing by the first party to take action. The notification&nbsp;shall be accompanied by a sufficiently detailed memorandum.</p>
        <p>As far as possible, the Parties shall endeavour to settle the dispute through negotiations, if&nbsp;necessary by seeking expert advice from a third party, or by conciliation between the&nbsp;Contracting Parties through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2. In the absence of an amicable settlement by direct agreement between the parties to the&nbsp;dispute or by conciliation through diplomatic channels within six months from the&nbsp;notification, the dispute shall be submitted, at the option of the investor, either to the&nbsp;competent jurisdiction of the State where the investment was made, or to international&nbsp;arbitration The choice between the two channels is in principle irreversible with the exception&nbsp;mentionned in paragraph 3.</p>
        <p>To this end, each Contracting Party agrees in advance and irrevocably to the settlement of any&nbsp;dispute by this type of arbitration.</p>
        <p>3. An investor who has submitted the dispute to national jurisdiction may nevertheless have&nbsp;recourse to international arbitration if, before judgement has been delivered on the subject&nbsp;matter by a national court or judge, the investor declares not to pursue his case any longer&nbsp;through national proceedings.</p>
        <p>4. In case of international arbitration, the dispute shall be submitted for settlement by arbitration&nbsp;to one of the hereinafter mentioned organizations, at the option of the investor :</p>
        <p>an ad hoc arbitral tribunal set up according to the arbitration rules laid down by the&nbsp;United Nations Commission on International Trade Law (U.N.C.I.T.R.A.L.) ;</p>
        <p>the International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (I.C.S.I.D.), set up by&nbsp;the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals&nbsp;of other States, opened for signature at Washington on March 18, 1965, when each State&nbsp;party to this Agreement has become a party to the said Convention. As long as this&nbsp;requirement is not met, each Contracting Party agrees that the dispute shall be submitted&nbsp;to arbitration pursuant to the Rules of the Additional Facility of the I.C.S.I.D.</p>
        <p>the Arbitral Court of the International Chamber of Commerce in Paris ;</p>
        <p>the Arbitration Institute of the Chamber of Commerce in Stockholm</p>
        <p>If the arbitration procedure has been introduced upon the initiative of a Contracting Party, this&nbsp;Party shall request the investor involved in writing to designate the arbitration organization to&nbsp;which the dispute shall be referred.</p>
        <p>5. At any stage of the arbitration proceedings or of the execution of an arbitral award, none of&nbsp;the Contracting Parties involved in a dispute shall be entitled to raise as an objection the fact&nbsp;that the investor who is the opposing party in the dispute has received compensation totally or&nbsp;partly covering his losses pursuant to an insurance policy or to the guarantee provided for in&nbsp;Article 6 of this Agreement.</p>
        <p>6. The arbitral tribunal shall decide on the basis of the national law, including the rules relating&nbsp;to conflicts of law, of the Contracting Party involved in the dispute in whose territory the&nbsp;investment has been made, as well as on the basis of the provisions of this Agreement, of the&nbsp;terms of the-specific agreement which may have been entered into regarding the investment,&nbsp;and of the principles of international law.</p>
        <p>7. The arbitral awards shall be final and binding on the parties to the dispute. Each Contracting&nbsp;Party undertakes to execute the awards in accordance with its national legislation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Most favoured nation">
        <p>In all matters relating to the treatment of investments the investors of each Contracting Party shall enjoy most-favoured-nation treatment in the territory of the other Party</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Disputes between the contracting parties relating to the interpretation or application of this agreement">
        <p>1. Any dispute relating to the interpretation or application of this Agreement shall be settled as&nbsp;far as possible through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2. In the absence of a settlement through diplomatic channels, the dispute shall be submitted to a&nbsp;joint commission consisting of representatives of the two Parties ; this commission shall&nbsp;convene without undue delay at the request of the first party to take action.</p>
        <p>3. If the joint commission cannot settle the dispute, the latter shall be submitted, at the request of&nbsp;either Contracting Party, to an arbitration court set up as follows for each individual case :</p>
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall appoint one arbitrator within a period of two months from the&nbsp;date on which either Contracting Party has informed the other Party of its intention to submit&nbsp;the dispute to arbitration. Within a period of two months following their appointment, these&nbsp;two arbitrators shall appoint by mutual agreement a national of a third State as chairman of&nbsp;the arbitration court.</p>
        <p>If these time limits have not been complied with, either Contracting Party shall request the&nbsp;President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointment(s).&nbsp;</p>
        <p>If the President of the International Court of Justice is a national of either Contracting Party or&nbsp;of a State with which one of the Contracting Parties has no diplomatic relations or if, for any&nbsp;other reason, he cannot exercise this function, the Vice-President of the International Court of&nbsp;Justice shall be requested to make the appointment(s).</p>
        <p>4. The court thus constituted shall determine its own rules of procedure. Its decisions shall be&nbsp;taken by a majority of the votes ; they shall be final and binding on the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>5. Each Contracting Party shall bear the costs resulting from the appointment of its arbitrator. The expenses in connection with the appointment of the third arbitrator and the administrative&nbsp;costs of the court shall be borne equally by the Contracting Parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Previous investments">
        <p>This Agreement shall also apply to investments made before its entry into force by investors of one&nbsp;Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party in accordance with the latter&#x2019;s laws&nbsp;and regulations. It shall however not apply to any dispute concerning an investment which arose&nbsp;before its entry into force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Entry into force and duration">
        <p>1. This Agreement shall enter into force one month after the date of exchange of the instruments&nbsp;of ratification by the Contracting Parties. The Agreement shall remain in force for a period of&nbsp;ten years.</p>
        <p>Unless notice of termination is given by either Contracting Party at least six months before the&nbsp;expiry of its period of validity, this Agreement shall be tacitly extended each time for a further&nbsp;period of ten years, it being understood that each Contracting Party reserves the right to&nbsp;terminate the Agreement by notification given at least six months before the date of expiry of&nbsp;the current period of validity.</p>
        <p>2. Investments made prior to the date of termination of this Agreement shall be covered by this&nbsp;Agreement for a period of ten years from the date of termination.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned representatives, duly authorized thereto by their&nbsp;respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</p>
      <p>DONE at Brasilia, on January 06, 1999, in two original copies,&nbsp;each in the English, French, Dutch and Portuguese languages, all texts being equally authentic. The&nbsp;text in the English language shall prevail in case of difference of interpretation.</p>
      <p>FOR THE BELGO-LUXEMBURG&nbsp;ECONOMIC UNION :</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Kingdom of Belgium,&nbsp;acting both in its own name and in the name of&nbsp;the Government of the Grand-Duchy of Luxembourg,&nbsp;for the Walloon Government,&nbsp;for the Flemish Government,&nbsp;and for the Government of the Region of Brussels Capital,</p>
      <p>(signature)</p>
      <p>FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE&nbsp;FEDERATIVE REPUBLIC OF BRAZIL :</p>
      <p>(signature)</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
