<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Chile - Ukraine BIT (1995)</name>
    <code>T1995-68</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">CHL</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">UKR</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1995-10-30</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1997-08-29</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">es</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>874</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{CHL,UKR}_1995-10-30.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>es</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT&nbsp;BETWEEN THE REPUBLIC OF CHILE AND&nbsp;UKRAINE&nbsp;ON THE RECIPROCAL PROMOTION AND PROTECTION&nbsp;OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Republic of Chile and Ukraine, hereinafter the&nbsp;"Contracting Parties";</p>
      <p>Desiring to intensify economic cooperation to the mutual&nbsp;benefit of both countries;</p>
      <p>With the intention to create and maintain favorable&nbsp;conditions for investments by investors of one Contracting&nbsp;Party which implies the transfer of capital to the&nbsp;territory of the other Contracting Party;</p>
      <p>Recognizing that the reciprocal promotion and protection&nbsp;of such foreign investments favour the economic prosperity&nbsp;of both countries;</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows: </p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purpose of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>(1) "investor" means the following subjects of one&nbsp;Contracting Party which have made an investment in&nbsp;the territory of the other Contracting Party in&nbsp;accordance with the present Agreement: </p>
        <p>(a) natural persons&nbsp;who, according to the law of&nbsp;that Contracting&nbsp;Party, are considered to be its nationals;</p>
        <p>(b)&nbsp;legal persons, including companies, corporations, business associations and other legally recognized entities, which are constituted or otherwise duly organised under&nbsp;the law of that Contracting Party and have their&nbsp;seat together with effective economic activities&nbsp;in the territory of that same Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(2) " investment" means any kind of asset, provided that&nbsp;the investment has been admitted in accordance with&nbsp;the laws and regulations of the other contracting&nbsp;Party, and shall include in particular, though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>(a) movable and immovable&nbsp;property and any other property rights such&nbsp; as servitudes, mortgages, enjoyment or pledges;</p>
        <p>(b) shares, debentures or any other kinds of participation in companies;</p>
        <p>(c) claims to money or to any performance having an economic value;</p>
        <p>(d) intellectual&nbsp;and industrial property rights, including&nbsp;copyright, patents, trademarks,&nbsp;trade names,&nbsp;technical processes, know-how and goodwill;</p>
        <p>(e)&nbsp;concessions conferred by law or under contract, including concessions to search for, cultivate, extract or exploit natural resources.</p>
        <p>(3) "territory" means in respect of each Contracting&nbsp;Party the land, maritime and airspace under its&nbsp;sovereignity, including the exclusive economic zone&nbsp;and the continental shelf where that contracting&nbsp;Party exercises, in conformity with international&nbsp;law, sovereign rights or jurisdiction.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Scope of Application">
        <p>This Agreement shall apply to investments in the territory&nbsp;of one Contracting Party made in accordance with its&nbsp;legislation, prior to or after the entry into force of the&nbsp;Agreement, by investors of the other Contracting Party.&nbsp;It shall however not be applicable to disputes which arose&nbsp;prior to its entry into force or to disputes directly related to events which occurred prior to its entry into force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Promotion and Protection of Investments">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party shall, subject to its general&nbsp;policy in the field of foreign investments, promote&nbsp;investments by investors of the other Contracting&nbsp;Party .</p>
        <p>(2) Each Contracting Party shall protect within its&nbsp;territory investments made in accordance with its&nbsp;laws and regulations by investors of the other&nbsp;Contracting Party and shall not impair by&nbsp;unreasonable or discriminatory measures the&nbsp;management, maintenance, use, enjoyment, extension,&nbsp;sale and liquidation of such investments.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Treatment of Investments">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party shall guarantee a fair and&nbsp;equitable treatment to investments made by investors&nbsp;of the other Contracting Party on its territory and shall ensure that the excercise of the right thus&nbsp;recognized shall not be hindered in practice.</p>
        <p>(2) Each Contracting Party shall accord investments of&nbsp;the investors of one Contracting Party in its&nbsp;territory a treatment which is no less favourable&nbsp;than that accorded to investments made by its own&nbsp;investors or by investor of any third country,&nbsp;whichever is the most favourable.</p>
        <p>(3) If a Contracting Party accords special advantages to&nbsp;investors of any third country by virtue of an&nbsp;agreement establishing a free trade area, a customs&nbsp;union, a common market, an economic union or any&nbsp;other form of regional economic organization to which&nbsp;the Party belongs or through the provisions of an&nbsp;agreement relating wholly or mainly to taxation, it&nbsp;shall not be obliged to accord such advantages to&nbsp;investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Free Transfer">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party shall allow without delay the investors of the other Contracting Party the transfer&nbsp;of funds in connection with an investment in a freely&nbsp;convertible currency, particularly of: </p>
        <p>(a) interests, dividends, profits and other returns;</p>
        <p>(b) repayments of a loan agreement related to the&nbsp;investment;</p>
        <p>(c) any capital or proceeds from the sale or partial&nbsp;sale or liquidation of the investment; and</p>
        <p>(d) compensation for expropriation or loss described&nbsp;in Article 6 of this Agreement.</p>
        <p>(2) Transfers shall be made at the exchange&nbsp;rate applying on the date of transfer in accordance&nbsp;with the law of the Contracting Party which has admitted the investment.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Expropriation and Compensation">
        <p>(1) Neither Contracting Party shall take any measures&nbsp;depriving, directly or indirectly, an investor of the&nbsp;other contracting Party of an investment unless the&nbsp;following three conditions are complied with :</p>
        <p>(a) the measures are taken in the public or national&nbsp;interest and in accordance with the law;</p>
        <p>(b) the measures are not discriminatory;</p>
        <p>(c) the measures are accompanied by provisions for the payment of prompt, adequate and effective compensation.</p>
        <p>(2) The compensation shall be based on the market value&nbsp;of the investments affected immediately before the&nbsp;measure became public knowledge. Where that value&nbsp;cannot be readily ascertained, the compensation may&nbsp;be determined in accordance with generally recognised&nbsp;equitable principles of valuation taking into account&nbsp;the capital invested, depreciation, capital already&nbsp;repatriated, replacement value and other relevant&nbsp;factors. In case of delay of the compensation&nbsp;payment, it shall carry interest at the appropriate&nbsp;market rate of interest from the date of&nbsp;expropriation or loss until the dale of payment.</p>
        <p>(3) The investor affected shall have a right to access,&nbsp;under the law of the Contracting Party making the&nbsp;expropriation, to the judicial authority of that&nbsp;Party, in order to review the amount of compensation&nbsp;and the legality of any such expropriation or&nbsp;comparable measure.</p>
        <p>(4) The investors of one Contracting Party whose&nbsp;investments have suffered losses due to a war or any&nbsp;other armed conflict, revolution, state of emergency or rebellion, which took place in the territory of&nbsp;the other Contracting Party shall be accorded by the&nbsp;latter Contracting Party treatment as regard&nbsp;restitution, indemnification, compensation or other&nbsp;consideration, no less favourable than that which&nbsp;that Contracting Party accords to its domestic&nbsp;investors or to investors of any third country,&nbsp;whichever is more favourable to the investors&nbsp;concerned.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Subrogation">
        <p>(1) Where one Contracting Party or an agency authorized&nbsp;by the Contracting Party has granted a contract of&nbsp;insurance or any form of financial guarantee against&nbsp;non-commercial risks with regard to an investment by&nbsp;one of its investors in the territory of the other&nbsp;Contracting Party , the latter shall recognize the&nbsp;rights of the first Contracting Party by virtue of&nbsp;the principle of subrogation to the right s o f the&nbsp;investor when payment has been made under this&nbsp;contract or financial guarantee by the first&nbsp;Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(2) Where a Contracting Party has made a payment to its&nbsp;investor and has taken over rights and claims of the&nbsp;investor, that investor shall not, unless authorized&nbsp;to act on behalf of the Contracting Party making the&nbsp;payment, pursue those rights and claims against the&nbsp;other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of Disputes between a Contracting Party and an Investor of the other Contracting Party">
        <p>(1) With a view to an amicable solution of disputes,&nbsp;which arise within the terms of this Agreement,&nbsp;between a Contracting Party and an investor of the other Contracting Party consultations will take place&nbsp;between the parties concerned.</p>
        <p>(2) If these consultations do not result in a solution&nbsp;within three months from the date of request for&nbsp;settlement, the investor may submit the dispute either:</p>
        <p>(a) to the competent tribunalof the Contracting Party in whose territorythe investment was made; or&nbsp;</p>
        <p>(b) to international arbitration of theInternational Centre for Settlement ofInvestment Disputes ( ICSID ), created by theConvention on the Settlement of InvestmentDisputes between states and Nationals of otherStates opened for signature at Washington on March 18, 1965.</p>
        <p>(3) Once the investor has submitted the dispute to thecompetent tribunal of the Contracting Party in whoseterritory the investment was made or to internationalarbitration, that election shall be final.</p>
        <p>(4) For the purpose of this Article, any legal personwhich is constituted in accordance with thelegislation of one Contracting Party, and in which,before a dispute arises, the majority of shares areowned by investors of the other Contracting Party,shall be treated, in accordance with Article 25 (2)(b) of the said Washington Convention, as a legalperson of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(5) The arbitration decisions shall be final and bindingon both parties and shall be enforced in accordancewith the laws of the Contracting Party in whoseterritory the investment was made.</p>
        <p>(6) Once a dispute has been submitted to the competenttribunal or international arbitration in accordancewith this Article, neither Contracting Party shallpursue the dispute through diplomatic channels unlessthe other Contracting Party has failed to abide orcomply&nbsp; with any judgment, award, order or otherdetermination made by the competent international orlocal tribunal in question.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Settlement of Disputes between the Contracting Parties">
        <p>(1) The Contracting Parties shall endeavour to resolve&nbsp;any difference between them regarding the&nbsp;interpretation or application of the provisions of&nbsp;this Agreement by friendly negotiations.</p>
        <p>(2) If the difference cannot thus be settled within six&nbsp;months following the date of notification of the&nbsp;difference, either Contracting Party may submit it to&nbsp;an Ad-hoc Arbitral Tribunal in accordance with this Article.</p>
        <p>(3) The Arbitral Tribunal shall be formed by three&nbsp;members and shall be constituted as follows: within&nbsp;two months of the notification by a Contracting Party&nbsp;of its wish to settle the dispute by arbitration,&nbsp;each contracting Party shall appoint one arbitrator.&nbsp;These two members shall then, within thirty days of&nbsp;the appointment of the last one, agree upon a third&nbsp;member who shall be a national of a third country and&nbsp;who shall act as the Chairman. The appointment of&nbsp;the Chairman shall be approved by the Contracting&nbsp;Parties within thirty days of that persons&nbsp;nomination.</p>
        <p>(4) If, within the time limits provided for in paragraph&nbsp;(2) and (3) of this Article the required appointment&nbsp;has not been made or the required approval has not been "given, either Contracting Party may request the&nbsp;President of the International Court of Justice to&nbsp;make the necessary appointments. If the President of&nbsp;the International Court of Justice is prevented from&nbsp;carrying out the said function or if that person is a&nbsp;national of either contracting Party, the&nbsp;appointments shall be made by the Vice-President, and&nbsp;if the latter is prevented or if that person is a&nbsp;national of either Contracting Party, the&nbsp;appointments shall be made by the most senior Judge&nbsp;of the Court who is not a national of either&nbsp;Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(5) The Chairman of the Tribunal shall be a national of a&nbsp;third country which has diplomatic relations with&nbsp;both Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>(6) The Arbitral Tribunal shall reach its decisions&nbsp;taking into account the provisions of this Agreement,&nbsp;the principles of international law on this subject&nbsp;and the general principles of Law as recognized by&nbsp;the contracting Parties. The Tribunal shall reach&nbsp;its decisions by a majority vote and shall determine&nbsp;its procedure.</p>
        <p>(7) Each Contracting Party shall bear the cost of the&nbsp;arbitrator it has appointed and of its representation&nbsp;in the arbitral proceedings. The cost of the&nbsp;Chairman and the remaining costs shall be borne in&nbsp;equal parts by the Contracting Parties unless agreed&nbsp;otherwise.</p>
        <p>(8) The decisions of the Arbitral Tribunal shall be final&nbsp;and binding on both Parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Consultations between Contracting Parties">
        <p>The Contracting Parties shall consult at the request of&nbsp;either of them on matters concerning the interpretation or&nbsp;application of this Agreement</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Final Provisions">
        <p>(1) The Contracting Parties shall notify each other when the constitutional requirements for the entry into&nbsp;force of this Agreement have been fulfilled. The Agreement shall enter into force thirty days after the date of the latter notification.</p>
        <p>(2) This Agreement shall remain in force for a period of&nbsp;fifteen years. Therafter it shall remain in force&nbsp;indefinitely unless one of the Contracting Parties gives one year's written notice of termination&nbsp;through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>(3) In respect of investments made prior to the date when&nbsp;the notice of termination of this Agreement becomes&nbsp;effective, the provisions of this Agreement shall&nbsp;remain in force a further period of fifteen years&nbsp;from that date.</p>
        <p>(4) This Agreement shall be applicable irrespective of whether diplomatic or consular relations exist&nbsp;between the Contracting Parties.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>Done at Santiago, on this 30th day of October of One&nbsp;Thousand Nine Hundred and Ninety Five in duplicate in&nbsp;Spanish, Ukrainian and English languages, all texts being&nbsp;equally authentic. In case of any divergence of&nbsp;interpretation, the English text shall prevail.</p>
      <p>FOR THE REPUBLIC OF CHILE</p>
      <p>FOR UKRAINE</p>
    </conclusion>
    <attachments>
      <div type="annex" title="Protocol">
        <p>On signing the Agreement on the Reciprocal Promotion and&nbsp;Protection of Investments between the Republic of Chile&nbsp;and Ukraine have, in addition, agreed on the following&nbsp;provisions, which shall be regarded as an integral part of the said Agreement.</p>
        <div type="article" title="Ad Article 5">
          <p>(1) Capital can only be transferred one year after it has&nbsp;entered the territory of the Contracting Party unless&nbsp;its legislation provides for a more favourable&nbsp;treatment.</p>
          <p>(2) A transfer shall be deemed to have been made without&nbsp;delay if carried out within such period as is&nbsp;normally required for the completion of transfer&nbsp;formalities. The said period shall start on the day&nbsp;on which the relevant request has been submitted in&nbsp;due form and may in no case exceed thirty days.</p>
          <p>Done at Santiago, on this 30th day of October of One&nbsp;Thousand Nine Hundred and Ninety Five, in duplicate in the&nbsp;Spanish, Ukrainian and English languages, all texts being&nbsp;equally authentic. In case of any divergence of&nbsp;interpretation, the English text shall prevail.</p>
          <p>FOR THE REPUBLIC OF CHILE</p>
          <p>FOR UKRAINE</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </attachments>
  </main>
</treaty>
