<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Canada - Philippines BIT (1995)</name>
    <code>T1995-53</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">CAN</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">PHL</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1995-11-10</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1996-11-01</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en, fr</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>794</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{CAN,PHL}_1995-11-10.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en, fr</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENTBETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF THEPHILIPPINES FOR THE PROMOTION AND RECIPROCAL PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>TheGovernment of Canada and the Republic of the Philippines hereinafter referredto as the "Contracting Parties";</p>
      <p>DESIRING to intensify economiccooperation between the Contracting Parties;</p>
      <p>INTENDING to create favourableconditions for investments by investors of one Contracting Party in the territoryof the other Contracting Party, and to increase prosperity in their respectiveterritories;</p>
      <p>RECOGNIZING that encouragement and protection of such investmentswill benefit the economic prosperity of the Contracting Parties;</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>Forthe purpose of this Agreement:   </p>
        <p>(a) "enterprise" means  </p>
        <p>(i)any entity constituted or organized under applicable  law, whether or notfor profit, whether privately-owned  or governmentally-owned, includingany corporation,  trust, partnership, sole proprietorship, joint ventureor  other association; and</p>
        <p> (ii) a branch of any such entity;  </p>
        <p>(b)"fair market value" means the value of an investment or  return,immediately prior to its expropriation or immediately  before the.expropriation became public knowledge,  whichever is the earlier.Valuation criteria shall include  going concerned value, asset valueincluding declared tax  value of tangible property, and other criteria, as appropriate, to determine fair market value.  </p>
        <p>(c) "financialservice" means a service of a financial nature,  such as, but notlimited to, insurance, and services  incidental or auxiliary to a serviceof a financial nature;</p>
        <p> (d) "financial institution"includes any financial intermediary or  other enterprise that isauthorized to do business and  regulated or supervised as a financial institutionunder the  law of the Contracting Party in whose territory it is located;  </p>
        <p>(e)"intellectual property rights" includes copyright and related  rights,trademark rights, patent rights, and the other rights  referred to in theAgreement on Aspects of Trade-Related  Intellectual Property Rightsforming part of the Agreement  establishing the World Trade Organization,done at  Marrakesh, April 1994.</p>
        <p>(f)"investment" means any kind of asset owned or controlled  eitherdirectly, or indirectly through an investor of a third  State, by aninvestor of one Contracting Party in the  territory of the otherContracting Party in accordance with  the latter's laws and, inparticular, though not exclusively  includes:</p>
        <p>(i) movable andimmovable property and any related  property rights, such as mortgages,liens usufructs  or pledges;</p>
        <p>(ii) shares, stock, bonds anddebentures or any other  form of equity participation in a company,business  enterprise or joint venture;</p>
        <p>(iii) money, claims tomoney, and claims to performance  . under contract having an economicvalue;   </p>
        <p>(iv) goodwill; </p>
        <p>(v) intellectual property rights;  </p>
        <p>(vi)rights, conferred by law or under contract, to undertake  any economic andcommercial activity, including any  rights to search for, cultivate,extract or exploit natural  resources.  Any change in the form of aninvestment does not affect its  character as an investment.</p>
        <p>(g)"investor" means:  </p>
        <p>in the case of Canada:   </p>
        <p>(i) Anynatural person possessing the citizenship of or  permanently residing inCanada in accordance with  its laws; or</p>
        <p>(ii) Any enterpriseincorporated or duly constituted In  accordance with the applicable lawsof Canada,  </p>
        <p>who makes investment in the territory of the Republic of the  Philippines;and</p>
        <p>in the case of the Republic of the Philippines,   </p>
        <p>(i)Individuals who are citizens of the Philippines within  the meaning of itsConstitution; or</p>
        <p>(ii) enterprises that are incorporated or, in any event,are  properly organized and actually doing business  under the lawsof the Republic of the Philippines and  have their headquarters in theterritory of the Philippines where effective management is carried  out.  </p>
        <p>whomakes the investment in the territory of Canada and who  does not possessthe citizenship of Canada;</p>
        <p>(h) "measure" includes anylaw, rule, regulation, requirement,  or established governmental procedureor practice;  "existing measure" means a measure existing at thetime  this Agreement enters into force;</p>
        <p>(i) "returns"means all amounts yielded by an investment and  in particular, though notexclusively, includes profits,  interest, capital gains, dividends,royalties, fees or other  current income;</p>
        <p>(j) "stateenterprise" means an enterprise that is  governmentally-owned orcontrolled through ownership  interests by a government;</p>
        <p>(k)"territory" means:</p>
        <p>(i) In respect of Canada, the territory ofCanada as well  as those maritime areas, including the seabed and  subsoiladjacent to the outer limit of the territorial  sea, over which Canadaexercises, in accordance  with international law, sovereign rights for the purpose of exploration and exploitation of the natural  resources ofsuch areas.</p>
        <p>(ii) In respect of the Republic of the Philippines, the  nationalterritory as defined in Article 1 of its Constitution.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="II" title="Establishment, acquisition and protection of investment">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Partyshall promote investments in its  territory by nationals and companies ofthe other  Contracting Party.  </p>
        <p>(2) Each Contracting Party shallaccord investments or returns  of investors of the other ContractingParty.  (a) fair and equitable treatment in accordance with  principlesof international law, and  (b) full protection and security.</p>
        <p>(3)Each Contracting Party shall, subject to the terms of this  Agreement andthe Annex, including inter-alia paragraphs 4 and 5 of this Article andparagraph 2 of Article 4, permit  establishment of a new businessenterprise or acquisition  of an existing business enterprise or a shareof such  enterprise by investors or prospective investors of the  otherContracting Party on a basis no less favourable than  that which, in likecircumstances, it permits such  acquisition or establishment by:</p>
        <p>(a)its own investors or prospective investors; or</p>
        <p>(b) investors orprospective investors of any third state.</p>
        <p>(4) Decisions by eitherContracting party, pursuant to  measures not inconsistent with thisAgreement, as to  whether or not to permit an acquisition shall not be  subjectto the provisions of Articles XIII or XV of this  Agreement.</p>
        <p>(5)Decisions by either Contracting Party not to permit establishment of anew business enterprise or acquisition  of an existing business enterpriseor a share or such  enterprise by investors or prospective investors shallnot  be subject to the provisions of Article XIII of this  Agreement. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="III" title="Most favoured nation (mfn) treatment after establishment and exceptions to mfn">
        <p>(1) EachContracting Party shall grant to investments, or  returns of investors ofthe other Contracting Party,  treatment no less favourable than thatwhich, in like  circumstances, it grants to investments or returns of  investorsof any third State. </p>
        <p>(2) Each Contracting Party shallgrant investors of the other  Contracting party, as regards theirmanagement, use,  enjoyment or disposal of their investments or returns,  treatmentno less favourable than that which, in like  circumstances, it grants toinvestors of any third State.</p>
        <p>(3) Subparagraph (3)(b) of Article II andparagraphs (1) and  (2) of this Article do not apply to treatment by a  ContractingParty pursuant to any existing or future  bilateral or multilateralagreement:  </p>
        <p>(a) establishing, strengthening or expanding a free trade  areaor customs union or an interim agreement  leading to the formation of afree trade area or  customs&#xB7; union of which either Contracting Party is or may become a member;  </p>
        <p>(b) negotiated within the framework of the GAITor its  successor organization and liberalizing trade in  services;or  </p>
        <p>(c) relating to:  </p>
        <p>(i) aviation;  </p>
        <p>(ii) telecommunicationstransport networks and  telecommunications transport services;</p>
        <p>(iii)fisheries;  </p>
        <p>(iv) maritime matters, including salvage; or  </p>
        <p>(v)financial services.  </p>
        <p>(d) relating wholly or mainly to taxation, inaccordance  with, and subject to the provisions of Article XII.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="IV" title="National treatment after establishment and exceptions to national treatment">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party shall grant toinvestments or  returns of investors of the other Contracting Party  treatmentno less favourable than that which, in like  circumstances, it grants toinvestments or returns of its  own investors with respect to theexpansion, management, conduct, operation and sale or disposition of investments. </p>
        <p>(2) Subparagraph (3)(a) of Article II, paragraph (1) of this  Article,and paragraphs (1) and (2) of Article IV do not  apply to:  </p>
        <p>(a)   </p>
        <p>(i)any existing non-conforming measures  maintained within the territory ofa  Contracting Party; and  </p>
        <p>(ii) any measure maintained or adoptedafter the  date of entry into force of this Agreement,  that, at thetime of sale or other disposition of a  government's equity interests in,or the assets of , an existing state enterprise or an existing  governmentalentity, prohibits or imposes  limitations on the ownership of equityinterests  or assets or imposes nationality  requirements relating tosenior management or  members of the board of directors;  </p>
        <p>(b) thecontinuation or prompt renewal of any non-conforming  measure referred toin subparagraph (a);  </p>
        <p>(c) an amendment to any non-conforming measurereferred to  in subparagraph (a), to the extent that the amendment  doesnot decrease the conformity of the measure, as it  existed immediatelybefore the amendment, with those  obligations;   </p>
        <p>(d) the rightof each Contracting Party is to make or maintain  exceptions within thesectors or matters listed in Section 1 of the Annex to this Agreement.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="V" title="Other measures">
        <p>(1)</p>
        <p>(a) A Contracting Party may not require that anenterprise  of that Contracting Party, that is an investment under  thisAgreement, appoint to senior management  positions individuals of any .particular nationality.  </p>
        <p>(b) A Contracting Party may require that amajority of the  board of directors, or any committee thereof, of an  enterpriseconstituted or organized under the laws of  that Contracting Party that isan investment under this  Agreement be of a particular nationality, orresident in  the territory of the Contracting Party, provided that the  requirementdoes not materially impair the ability of the  investor to exercisecontrol over its investment.  </p>
        <p>(2) Neither Contracting Party may impose anyof the following  requirements in connection with permitting the  establishmentor acquisition of an investment or enforce  any of the followingrequirements in connection with the  subsequent regulation of thatinvestment:  </p>
        <p>(a) to export a given level or percentage of goods;  </p>
        <p>(b)to achieve a given level or percentage of domestic  content; </p>
        <p>(c) topurchase, use or accord a preference to goods  produced or servicesprovided in its territory, or to  purchase goods or services from personsIn its  territory;   </p>
        <p>(d) to relate in any way the volume orvalue of imports to  the volume or value of exports or to the amount of  foreignexchange inflows associated with such  investment; or  </p>
        <p>(e) totransfer technology, a production process or other  proprietary knowledgeto a person in its territory  unaffiliated with the transferor, except whenthe requirement is imposed or the commitment or  undertaking isenforced by a court, administrative  tribunal or competition authority,either to remedy an alleged violation of competition laws or acting in a  mannernot inconsistent with other provisions of this  Agreement.  </p>
        <p>(3)Subject to its laws, regulations and policies relating to the  entry .ofaliens. each Contracting Party shall grant  temporary entry to citizens ofthe other Contracting Party  employed by an enterprise who seeks to renderservices  to that enterprise or a subsidiary or affiliate thereof, in a capacitythat is managerial or executive.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="VI" title="Miscellaneous exceptions">
        <p>(1)   </p>
        <p>(a) In respect of intellectualproperty rights, a  Contracting Party may derogate from Articles III andIV in a manner that is consistent with the  agreement establishing theWorld Trade  Organisation done at Marrakesh. April 1994.  </p>
        <p>(b) The provisionsof Article VIII do not apply to the  issuance of compulsory licensesgranted in relation to  intellectual property rights, or to therevocation,  limitation or creation of intellectual property rights, to  theextent that such issuance, revocation, limitation  or creation isconsistent with the agreement  establishing the World Trade Organisationdone at  Marrakesh, April 1994.  </p>
        <p>(2) The provisions of Articles II,III, IV and V of this Agreement  do not apply to:  </p>
        <p>(a) procurement bya government or state enterprise;  </p>
        <p>(b) subsidies or grants provided by agovernment or a  state enterprise, including government-supported  loans,guarantees and insurance;  </p>
        <p>(c) any current or future foreign aid programto promote  economic development, whether under a bilateral  agreement,or pursuant to a multilateral arrangement  or agreement, such as the OECDAgreement on Export Credits.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="VII" title="Compensation for losses">
        <p>Investors of one ContractingParty who suffer losses  because their investments or returns on theterritory of the  other Contracting Party are affected by an armedconflict, or a  national emergency on that territory, shall be accorded bysuch  latter Contracting Party, in respect of restitution, indemnification,compensation or other settlement, treatment no less favourable than thatwhich it accords to its own  investors or to investors of any third State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="VIII" title="Expropriation">
        <p>(1) Investments or returns of investors ofeither Contracting  Party shall not be nationalized, expropriated orsubjected  to measures having an effect equivalent to nationalization  orexpropriation, (hereinafter referred to as "expropriation") inthe territory of the other Contracting Party, except for a  publicpurpose, under due process of law, in a nondiscriminatory  manner andagainst prompt, adequate and  effective compensation. Such compensationshall be  based on the fair market value of the investment or returns  expropriatedimmediately before the expropriation or at the  time the proposedexpropriation became public knowledge,  whichever is the earlier, shall bepaid without delay and  shall be effectively realizable and freelytransferable.</p>
        <p>(2) The investor affectedshall have a right, under the law of  the Contracting Party making theexpropriation, to prompt  review, by a judicial or other independentauthority of that  party, of its case and of the valuation of itsinvestment or  returns in accordance with the principles set out in this Article.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="IX" title="Transfers">
        <p>(a) Each Contracting Party shall guarantee to an investorof  the other Contracting Party the unrestricted investments  andreturns. Without limiting the generality of the  foregoing, eachContracting Party shall also guarantee to  the investor the unrestrictedtransfer of:   </p>
        <p>(a) funds in repayment of loans related to aninvestment;  </p>
        <p>(b) the proceeds of the total or partial liquidation ofany investment;  </p>
        <p>(c) wages and other remuneration accruing to a  citizenof the other Contracting Party who was  permitted to work in connectionwith an Investment  in the territory of the other Contracting Party.  </p>
        <p>(d)any compensation owed to an investor by virtue of  Articles VII or VIIIthis Agreement.  </p>
        <p>(b) Transfers shall be effected without delay in theconvertible currency in which the capital was originally invested or in  anyother convertible currency agreed by the investor, and  the ContractingParty concerned. Unless otherwise agreed by the investor, transfer shallbe made at the rate  of exchange applicable on the date of transfer.  </p>
        <p>(c)Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 and 2, a Contracting Party  may prevent atransfer through the equitable, nondiscriminatory  and good faithapplication of its laws relating  to:  </p>
        <p>(a) bankruptcy, insolvency orthe protection of the rights of creditors;  </p>
        <p>(b) issuing, trading ordealing in securities;  </p>
        <p>(c) criminal or penal offenses;  </p>
        <p>(d) reportsof transfers of currency or other monetary  instruments; or  </p>
        <p>(e)ensuring the satisfaction of judgments in adjudicatory  proceedings.  </p>
        <p>(d)Neither Contracting Party may require its investors to transfer orpenalize its investors that fail to transfer the  returns attributable toinvestments in the territory of the  other Contracting Party.  </p>
        <p>(e)Paragraph 4 shall not be construed to prevent a  Contracting Party fromimposing any measure through the  equitable, non-discriminatory and goodfaith application of  its laws relating to the matters set out insubparagraphs (a)  through (e) of paragraph 3.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="X" title="Subrogation">
        <p>(1) If a Contracting Party or any agency thereofmakes a  payment to any of its investors under a guarantee or a  contractof insurance it has entered into in respect of an  investment, the otherContracting Party shall recognize the  validity of the subrogation infavour of such Contracting  Party or agency thereof to any right or titleheld by the  investor. This does not necessarily imply, however, a  recognitionon the part of the other Contracting Party of the  merits of any case orthe amount of any claim arising  therefrom.  </p>
        <p>(2) A Contracting Partyor any agency thereof which is  subrogated to the rights of an investor inaccordance with  paragraph (1) of this Article, shall be entitled in all  circumstancesto the same rights as those of the investor  in respect of the investmentconcerned and its related  returns. Such rights may be exercised by theContracting  Party or any agency thereof or by the investor if the  ContractingParty or any agency thereof so authorizes.If a Contracting Party or any of its agencies makes payment &#xE8; one of its investors under a guarantee or a contract of insurance given by it in connection with an investment, the other Contracting Party shall recognize the validity of the subrogation in favour of such Contracting Party or agency to any right or title held by the investor. by such recognition, it cannot be presumed, however, that the Contracting Party shall recognize the validity of any dispute or the value of any request for such subrogation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XI" title="Prudential and financial measures">
        <p>(1) Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed to prevent a  Contracting Party from adopting or maintaining reasonable  measures for prudential reasons, such as:</p>
        <p>(a) the protection of investors, depositors, financial  market participants, policy holders, policy claimants,  or persons to whom a fiduciary duty is owed by a  financial institution;</p>
        <p>(b) the maintenance of the safety, soundness, integrity or  financial responsibility of financial institutions; and</p>
        <p>(c) ensuring the integrity and stability of a Contracting  Party's financial system. </p>
        <p>(2) Notwithstanding paragraphs (1), (2) and (4) of Article IX,  and without limiting the applicability of paragraph (3) of  Article IX, a Contracting Party may prevent or limit  transfers by a financial institution to, or for the benefit of,  an affiliate of or person related to such institution or  provider, through the equitable, non-discriminatory and  good faith application of measures relating to maintenance  or the safety, soundness, integrity or financial  responsibility of financial institutions.</p>
        <p>(3) Sub-paragraph 3(b) of Article II does not apply in respect  of financial services.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XII" title="Taxation measures">
        <p>(1) Except as set out in this Article, nothingin this Agreement  shall apply to taxation measures.  </p>
        <p>(2) Nothing inthis Agreement shall affect the rights and  obligations of the ContractingParties under any tax  convention. In the event of any inconsistencybetween the  provisions of this Agreement and any such convention, the  provisionsof that convention apply to the extent of the  inconsistency.  </p>
        <p>(3)Subject to paragraph (2), a claim by an investor that a tax  measure of aContracting Party is in breach of an  agreement between the centralgovernment authorities of  a Contracting Party and the investor concerningan  investment shall be considered a claim for breach of this  Agreementunless the taxation authorities of the  Contracting Parties, no laterthan. six months after being  notified of the claim by the investor,jointly determine that  the measure does not contravene such agreement.  </p>
        <p>(4)Article VIII may be applied to a taxation measure unless  the taxationauthorities of the Contracting Parties, no later  than six months afterbeing notified by an investor that he  disputes a taxation measure,jointly determine that the  measure is not an expropriation.  </p>
        <p>(5) Ifthe taxation authorities of the Contracting Parties fail to  reach thejoint determinations specified in paragraphs (3)  and (4) within sixmonths after being notified, the investor  may submit its claim forresolution under Article XIII.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XIII" title="Settlement of disputes between an investor and the host contracting party">
        <p>(1) Any dispute between one ContractingParty and an  investor of the other Contracting Party, relating to a claim by the investor that a measure taken or not taken by the  formerContracting Party is in breach of this Agreement,  and that the investorhas incurred loss or damage by  reason of, or arising out of, that breach,shall, to the extent  possible, be settled amicably between them.  </p>
        <p>(2)If a dispute has not been settled amicably within a period  of six monthsfrom the date on which it was initiated, it may  be submitted by theinvestor to arbitration in accordance  with paragraph (4). For thepurposes of this paragraph, a  dispute is considered to be initiated whenthe investor of  one Contracting Party has delivered notice in writing tothe  other Contracting Party alleging that a measure taken or  nottaken by the latter Contracting Party is in breach of this  Agreement, andthat the investor has incurred loss or  damage by reason of, or arisingout of, that breach.  </p>
        <p>(3) An investor may submit a dispute as referred toin  paragraph (1) to arbitration in accordance with paragraph (4)only if:  </p>
        <p>(a) the investor has consented in writing thereto;  </p>
        <p>(b) theinvestor has waived its right to initiate or continue  any otherproceedings in relation to the measure that  is alleged to be in breach ofthis Agreement before  the courts or tribunals of the Contracting Party  concernedor in a dispute settlement procedure of  any kind;  </p>
        <p>(c) if the matterinvolves taxation, the conditions  specified in paragraph 5 of Article XIIhave been  fulfilled; and  </p>
        <p>(d) not more than three years have elapsedfrom the  date on which the investor first acquired, or should  havefirst acquired, knowledge of the alleged breach  and knowledge that theinvestor has incurred loss or  damage.  </p>
        <p>(4) The dispute may, at theelection of the investor concerned,  be submitted to arbitration under:  </p>
        <p>(a)The International Centre for the Settlement of  Investment Disputes(ICSID), established pursuant to  the Convention on the Settlement ofInvestment  Disputes between States and Nationals of other  States,opened for signature at Washington 18 March, 1965 (ICSID Convention),provided that both  the disputing Contracting Party and the Contracting  Partyof the investor are parties to the ICSID  convention; or  </p>
        <p>(b) theAdditional Facility Rules of ICSID, provided that  either the disputingContracting Party or the  Contracting Party of the investor, but not both,is a  party to the ICSID Convention; or  </p>
        <p>(c) an internationalarbitrator or ad hoc arbitration  tribunal established under theArbitration Rules of the  United Nations Commission on International Trade Law (UNCITRAL).  </p>
        <p>(5) Each Contracting Party hereby gives itsunconditional  consent to the submission of a dispute to international  arbitrationin accordance with the provisions of this  Article. </p>
        <p>(6)   </p>
        <p>(a)The consent given under paragraph (5), together with  either the consent givenunder paragraph (3), or the  consents given under paragraph (12), shallsatisfy the  requirements for:  </p>
        <p>(i) written consent of the parties toa dispute for  purposes of Chapter 11 (Jurisdiction of the  Centre)of the ICSID Convention and for  purposes of the Additional FacilityRules; and  </p>
        <p>(ii) an "agreement in writing" for purposes ofArticle II  of the United Nations Convention for the  Recognition andEnforcement of Foreign Arbitral  Awards, done at New York, June 10, 1958("New  York Convention").  </p>
        <p>(b) Any arbitration under thisArticle shall be held in a  State that is a party to the New YorkConvention, and  claims submitted to arbitration shall be considered to  ariseout of a commercial relationship or transaction  for the purposes ofArticle 1 of that Convention.  </p>
        <p>(7) A tribunal established under thisArticle shall decide the  issues in dispute in accordance with thisAgreement and  applicable rules of international law.</p>
        <p>(8) A tribunalmay order an interim measure of protection to  preserve the rights of adisputing party, or to ensure that  the tribunal's jurisdiction is madefully effective, including  an order to preserve evidence in thepossession or control  of a disputing party or to protect the tribunal'sjurisdiction.  A tribunal may not order attachment or enjoin the  applicationof the measure alleged to constitute a breach  of this Agreement. Forpurposes of this paragraph, an  order includes a recommendation.  </p>
        <p>(9)A tribunal may award, separately or in combination, only:  </p>
        <p>(a) monetarydamages and any applicable interest;  </p>
        <p>(b) restitution of property, inwhich case the award shall  provide that the disputing Contracting Partymay pay  monetary damages and any applicable interest in lieu  ofrestitution.  A tribunal may also award costs in accordance with the  applicablearbitration rules.   </p>
        <p>(10) An award of arbitration shall be final andbinding and  shall be enforceable in the territory of each of the  ContractingParties.  </p>
        <p>(11) Any proceedings under this Article are without prejudice tothe rights of the Contracting Parties under Articles XIV and XV. </p>
        <p>(a) A claim that a Contracting Party is in breach of this Agreement,and that an enterprise that is a juridical  person incorporated or dulyconstituted in  accordance with applicable laws of that Contracting  Partyhas incurred loss or damage by reason of, or  arising out of, that breach,may be brought by an  investor of the other Contracting Party acting on  behalfof an enterprise which the investor owns or  controls directly orindirectly. In such a case</p>
        <p>(i) any award shall be made to the affected  enterprise; </p>
        <p>(ii) the consent to arbitration of both the investor and  theenterprise shall be required;  </p>
        <p>(iii) both the investor and enterprise mustwaive any  right to initiate or continue any other proceedings  inrelation to the measure that is alleged to be in  breach of this Agreementbefore the courts or  tribunals of the Contracting Party concerned or in  adispute settlement procedure of any kind; and  </p>
        <p>(iv) the investor may notmake a claim if more than  three years have elapsed from the date on which the enterprise first acquired, or should have first  acquired,knowledge of the alleged breach and  knowledge that it has incurred lossor damage.  </p>
        <p>(b) Notwithstanding subparagraph 12(a), where a  disputingContracting Party has deprived a disputing  investor of control of anenterprise, the following shall  not be required:  </p>
        <p>(i) a consent toarbitration by the enterprise under  12(a)ii); and  </p>
        <p>(ii) a waiverfrom the enterprise under 12(a)iii).  </p>
        <p>(11) The procedures referred to in this article shall be without prejudice to the rights of the Contracting Parties under Articles XIV and xv.articles XIV and XV.</p>
        <p>(12)</p>
        <p>a) A claim that a Contracting Party is in breach of this Agreement and that the enterprise has legal personality and duly constituted in accordance with the relevant laws of that Contracting Party has incurred loss or damage by reason of that breach may be submitted by an investor of the other contracting party acting on behalf of an enterprise that the investor owns or controls directly or indirectly. in such a case,</p>
        <p>i) The award is intended for the undertaking concerned;</p>
        <p>ii) The investor and the enterprise must both consent to arbitration;</p>
        <p>iii) The investor and the enterprise both to waive the right to initiate or continue any proceedings with respect to the alleged measure to be inconsistent with this Agreement, civil or administrative courts of the Contracting Party concerned or to any body for the resolution of disputes; and</p>
        <p>iv) An investor may not make a claim if more than three years have elapsed since the date on which the undertaking became aware or should have had knowledge of the alleged breach and that it has caused him injury.</p>
        <p>b) Notwithstanding subparagraph (a), if the contracting party in the dispute has deprived the investor of control of the enterprise, the following conditions shall not apply to: subparagraph 12 (a), if the contracting party in the dispute has deprived the investor of control of the enterprise, the following conditions shall not apply to:</p>
        <p>i) The enterprise consent to arbitration in accordance with subparagraph 12 (a) (ii); et12 (a) (ii); and</p>
        <p>ii) A waiver from the enterprise under subparagraph 12 (a) (iii). (a) (iii).</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XIV" title="Consultations and exchange of information">
        <p>Either Contracting Party may request consultations on the  interpretation or application of this Agreement. The other  Contracting Party shall give sympathetic consideration to the  request. Upon request by either Contracting Party, information  shall be exchanged on the measures of the other Contracting  Party that may have an impact on new investments,  investments or returns covered by this Agreement.    </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XV" title="Disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>(1)Disputes between the Contracting Parties concerning the  interpretationand application of this Agreement shall be  settled, as far as possible,through friendly consultations  by both parties through diplomaticchannels.  </p>
        <p>(2) If such disputes cannot be settled through consultations,  theyshall, at the request of either Contracting Party, be  submitted forsettlement to an ad hoc international arbitral  panel (hereinafter called"the Panel").  </p>
        <p>(3) The Panel mentioned above shall beestablished as  follows: The Panel is composed of three arbitrators.Within  two months after receipt through diplomatic channels of  therequest for arbitration, each Contracting Party shall  appoint onearbitrator; the two arbitrators shall propose by  mutual agreement thethird arbitrator who is a national of a  third State which has diplomaticrelations with both  Contracting Parties, and the third arbitrator shall,upon  approval by the two Contracting Parties, be appointed as  Chairmanof the Panel. The Chairman shall be appointed  within two months from thedate of appointment of the  other two members of the Panel.  </p>
        <p>(4) Ifthe appointments of the members of the Panel are not  made within theperiods specified in paragraph (3) of this  Article, either ContractingParty may, in the absence of any  other arrangement, invite the Presidentof the International  Court of Justice to make necessary appointmentswithin  three months. Should the President be a national of one  ContractingParty or should he not be able to perform this  designation because ofother reasons, this task shall be  entrusted to the Vice-President of theCourt, or to the next  senior Judge of the Court who is not a national ofeither  Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(5) The Panel shall determine its ownprocedure. The Panel  shall decide its award by majority of votes. Suchaward is  final and binding upon the Contracting Parties. Unless  otherwiseagreed, the decision of the Panel shall be  rendered within six months ofthe appointment of the  Chairman in accordance with paragraphs (3) and (4)of  this Article.  </p>
        <p>(6) Each Contracting Party shall bear the cost ofits own  member of the panel and of its representation in the  arbitralproceedings. The costs of the Chairman and the  remaining costs shall beborne in equal parts by the  Contracting Parties. The Panel may, however,in its  decision direct that a higher proportion of costs shall be  borneby one of the two Contracting Parties, and this  award shall be binding onboth Contracting Parties.  </p>
        <p>(7) Within 60 days after a decision is made bythe Panel, the  Contracting Parties shall agree on the manner in which to  giveeffect to the decision which shall normally consist of  implementation ofsuch decision. If the Contracting Parties  fail to reach an agreement, theContracting Party bringing  the dispute shall be entitled to compensationor to suspend  benefits of equivalent value to those awarded by the panel. Any dispute between the contracting parties relating to the interpretation or application of this Agreement shall as far as possible be settled amicably through consultations through diplomatic channels.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XVI" title="Transparency">
        <p>(1) The Contracting Parties shall, withina two year period  after the entry into force of this Agreement, exchange  letterslisting, to the extent possible, any existing measures  that do notconform to the obligations in subparagraph  (3)(a) of Article II, ArticleIV or paragraphs (1) and (2) of  Article V.</p>
        <p>(2) Each Contracting Party shall, to the extent practicable,  ensurethat its laws, regulations, procedures, and  administrative rulings ofgeneral application respecting any  matter covered by this Agreement arepromptly published  or otherwise made available in such a manner as to  enableinterested persons and the other Contracting Party  to become acquaintedwith them.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XVII" title="Application and general exceptions">
        <p>(1) ThisAgreement shall apply to any investment made by an  investor of oneContracting Party in the territory of the  other Contracting Party beforeor after the entry into force  of this Agreement.  </p>
        <p>(2) Nothing inthis Agreement shall be construed to prevent a  Contracting Party fromadopting, maintaining or enforcing  any measure otherwise consistent withthis Agreement  that it considers appropriate to ensure that investment  activityin its territory is undertaken in a manner sensitive  to environmentalconcerns.  </p>
        <p>(3) Provided that such measures are not applied in an  arbitraryor unjustifiable manner, or do not constitute a  disguised restriction oninternational trade or investment,  nothing in this Agreement shall beconstrued to prevent a  Contracting Party from adopting or maintainingmeasures,  including environmental measures:  </p>
        <p>(a) necessary to ensurecompliance with laws and regulations that are not inconsistent with the provisionsof this Agreement;   </p>
        <p>(b) necessary to protect human, animal or plantlife or  health; or  </p>
        <p>(c) relating to the conservation of living ornon-living  exhaustible natural resources.  </p>
        <p>(4) The Annex shall forman integral part of this Agreement.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XVIII" title="Entry into force">
        <p>(1) This Agreement shall enterinto force three months after  the notification between the ContractingParties of the  accomplishment of their respective internal procedures for the entry into force of this Agreement.  </p>
        <p>(2) This Agreement shallremain in force unless either  Contracting Party notifies the other ContractingParty in  writing of its intention to terminate it. The termination of  thisAgreement shall become effective one year after  notice of termination hasbeen received by the other  Contracting Party. In respect of investmentsor  commitments to invest made prior to the date when the  terminationof this Agreement becomes effective, the  provisions of Articles I to XVIIinclusive of this Agreement  shall remain in force for a period of fifteenyears.  </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, duly authorized  thereto bytheir respective Governments, have signed this  Agreement.   </p>
      <p>Donein duplicate at Manila on November 9, 1995 in French and EnglishLanguages, both texts being equally authentic.   </p>
      <p>ROY MACLAREN  </p>
      <p>TradeMinister</p>
      <p>FOR THE GOVERNMENT OFCANADA</p>
      <p>RIZALINO S.NAVARRO  </p>
      <p>Secretary </p>
      <p>Department of Trade and Industry   </p>
      <p>FORTHE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF THE PHILIPPINES   </p>
    </conclusion>
    <attachments>
      <p>
        <b>ANNEX</b>
      </p>
      <div type="section" num="1" title="Reservations and exceptions">
        <p>(a)In accordance with Article IV, subparagraph 2(d), Canada reserves theright to make and maintain  exceptions in the sectors or matters listedbelow:  </p>
        <p>&#x2022; social services (i.e. public law enforcement; correctional  services;income security or insurance; social security  or insurance; socialwelfare; public education; public  training; health and child care); </p>
        <p>&#x2022;services in any other sector;  </p>
        <p>&#x2022; government securities -as described inSIC 8152;  </p>
        <p>&#x2022; residency requirements for ownership of oceanfront  land; </p>
        <p>&#x2022; measures implementing the Northwest Territories and  the Yukon Oiland Gas Accords.  </p>
        <p>(b) In accordance with Article IV, subparagraph 2(d),the Republic of the Philippines reserves the right to make  andmaintain exceptions in the sectors or matters listed  below:  </p>
        <p>&#x2022; massmedia as described in Article XVI, Section 11 of the Constitution;  </p>
        <p>&#x2022;services involving the practice of licensed profession;  </p>
        <p>&#x2022; small-scaleretail trade as described in Republic Act No. 1180;  </p>
        <p>&#x2022; cooperativeenterprises as described in Republic Act  No. 6938;  </p>
        <p>&#x2022; privatesecurity agencies as described in Republic Act  No. 5487;  </p>
        <p>&#x2022;small-scale mining as described in Republic Act No. 7076;  </p>
        <p>&#x2022;utilization of marine resources except deep sea fishing  as described inArticle XII, Section 2 of the Constitution;  </p>
        <p>&#x2022; trading in rice and corn asdescribed in Republic Act No.  3018; Presidential Decree No. 194.  Forthe purpose of this Annex, "SIC" means, with respect to  Canada,Standard Industrial Classification numbers as set out  in StatisticsCanada, Standard Industrial Classification, fourth  edition, 1980.   </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section" num="2" title="Canada specific interpretation and exceptions">
        <p>(a) For the purposesof this Agreement an "investment" shall  not include real estateor other property, tangible or  intangible, located in the territory ofCanada, not acquired  in the expectation or used for the purpose ofeconomic  benefit or other business purposes.  </p>
        <p>(b) The provisions ofArticles II, III, IV and V of this  Agreement do not apply to any measuredenying  investors of the Philippines and their investments any  rightsor preferences provided to the aboriginal peoples of Canada. </p>
        <p>(c)Investments in cultural industries in Canada are exempt  from the'provisions of this Agreement. "Cultural  Industries" meansnatural persons or enterprises  engaged in any of the followingactivities:  </p>
        <p>(i) the publication, distribution, or sale of books,  magazines,periodicals or newspapers in print or  machine readable form but notincluding the sole  activity of printing or typesetting any of the  foregoing; </p>
        <p>(ii) the production, distribution, sale or exhibition of film  orvideo recordings;</p>
        <p>(iii) the production, distribution, sale or exhibitionof  audio or video music recordings;  </p>
        <p>(iv) the publication,distribution, sale or exhibition of  music in print or machine readableform; or  </p>
        <p>(v) radiocommunications in which the transmissions are  intendedfor direct reception by the general public,  and all radio, television orcable broadcasting  undertakings and all satellite programming and  broadcastnetwork services.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="section" num="3" title="Philippines-specific interpretation and exceptions&#xA0; &#xA0;">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement,"investment" in the  territory of the Philippines shall onlyinclude assets which,  where registration is required by the Philippinelaws, rules or regulations, have been so registered.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="section" num="4" title="Interest">
        <p>The compensation for expropriation described in ArticleVIII  (Expropriation) shall include interest payable from the date of  expropriationto the date of payment at a normal commercial rate.   </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section" num="5" title="Procedure for disputes on prudential and financial&#xA0; measures">
        <p>(a)Where an investor submits a claim to arbitration under  Article XIII, andthe disputing Contracting Party invokes  paragraphs (1) or (2) of ArticleXI, the tribunal  established pursuant to Article XIII, shall at therequest of  that Contracting Party, seek a report in writing from the  ContractingParties on the issue of whether and to what  extent the said paragraphsare a valid defence to the claim of the investor. The tribunal may not proceed  pending receiptof a report under this Article.   </p>
        <p>(b) Pursuant to a request receivedin accordance with  subparagraph (a), the Contracting Parties shallproceed  in accordance with Article XV, to prepare a written report,  eitheron the basis of agreement following consultations,  or by means of anarbitral panel. The consultations shall  be between the financial servicesauthorities of the  Contracting Parties. The report shall be transmittedto the  tribunal, and shall be binding on the tribunal.  </p>
        <p>(c) Where,within 70 days of the referral by the tribunal, no  request for theestablishment of a panel pursuant to  subparagraph (b) has been made andno report has been  received by the tribunal, the tribunal may proceed to  decidethe matter.  </p>
        <p>(d) Panels for disputes on prudential issues and other financialmatters shall have the necessary expertise  relevant to the specificfinancial service in dispute. </p>
      </div>
    </attachments>
  </main>
</treaty>
