<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Belarus - China BIT (1993)</name>
    <code>T1993-32</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">BLR</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">CHN</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1993-01-11</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1995-01-14</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>407</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>tfs.mofcom.gov.cn</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{BLR,CHN}_1993-01-11.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN GOVERNMENT OF THEREPUBLIC OF BELARUS AND GOVERNMENT OF THE CHINESE PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC ONPROMOTION AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Republic of Belarus and theGovernment of the Chinese People's Republic, hereinafter referred to as "theParties",</p>
      <p>Desiring to promote, protect and create a favorableenvironment for investors of the other Party to make investments in itsterritory,</p>
      <p>Basing on the principles of mutual respect forsovereignty, equality and mutual benefits,</p>
      <p>To expand economic cooperation of the two States,</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1">
        <p>For the purpose of this agreement</p>
        <p>1.   The term "investments" meansany kind of asset defined in accordance with the laws and regulations of theContracting Parties in whose territory the investment is made, by an investorof one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party, inaccordance with the latter's laws. It includes in particular, though notexclusively:</p>
        <p> a) Movable andimmovable property and any related property rights;</p>
        <p>b) Shares or any other form of participation in acompany, business enterprise;</p>
        <p>c) Claims to performance under financial value,related to a specific investment;</p>
        <p>d) Intellectual property rights, industrial propertyrights, Know-how and industrial designs;</p>
        <p>e) Rights conferred by law or under contracts, toundertake any economic and commercial activity, including any rights to searchfor, cultivate, extract or exploit natural resources.</p>
        <p>2.    The term "investors" for the Contracting Parties means</p>
        <p>-- Any natural person possessing the citizenship in aContracting Party in accordance with its laws;</p>
        <p>-- Organizations and companies incorporatedin accordance with applicable laws of a Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>-- Under the condition that a naturalperson, organization or company are authorized in accordance with the laws of aContracting Party to make investments in the territory of the secondContracting Party.</p>
        <p>3.    The Term "returns" all amounts yielded by aninvestment and in, though not exclusively, includes profits, dividends,interest, and royalties.</p>
        <p>4.    The term "territory" means the territory ofthe Republic of Belarus and the Territory of the Chinese People's Republiccorrespondingly.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2">
        <p>1.   Each Contracting Party shallpossibly encourage investors of the other Contracting Party to make investmentsin its territory and shall admit investments of investors of the othercontracting Party.</p>
        <p>2.    Each Contracting Party in accordance with its lawsshall assist citizens of the other Contracting Party in granting visas and workpermit related to investments made in its territory.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall grant to investments investors ofthe other Contracting Party in its own territory, treatment no less favorablethan that which it grants to investments or returns of investors of any thirdState.</p>
        <p>2.   The regulations of paragraph 1of this Article shall be no less favorable than that granted to investments ofany third State and investment activities.</p>
        <p>3.   The provisions of paragraph 1and 2 do not cover any future privileges and benefits to be granted toinvestors or their investments of any third State by a Contracting Party on thebasis of:</p>
        <p>- Concluded or to be concluded agreements on economic zones, economicand customs unions and free trade zones;</p>
        <p>-  International agreement or any other agreements on taxation;</p>
        <p>-  Any agreements on pre-border trade.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4">
        <p>1.   Investments or returns ofinvestors of either Contracting Party shall not be nationalized, expropriatedor subjected to measures having an effect to nationalization or expropriationin the territory of the other Contracting Party, except for a public purpose,under due process of law, in a non-discriminatory manner and against prompt,adequate and effective compensation.</p>
        <p>2.    The compensation stated in paragraph 1 of this Articleshall be based on the genuine value of the investment expropriated immediatelybefore the expropriation or at the time the proposed expropriation becamepublic knowledge.</p>
        <p> Thecompensation shall be payable from the date of the expropriation at a normalcommercial rate of interest, shall be paid without delay and shall beeffectively realizable and freely transferable into the territory of the otherContracting Party.</p>
        <p>3.   Investors of one ContractingParty who suffer losses because their investments or returns on the territoryor the other Contracting Party are affected by armed conflict, nationalemergency or a natural disaster, civil strife or any other similar actions onthat territory, if subject to compensation or other settlement, shall providetreatment no less favorable than that it accords to investors of any thirdState.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5">
        <p> Each Contracting Party inaccordance with its laws shall guarantee to an investor of the otherContracting Party after having fulfilled its tax obligations, the transfer orinvestments and returns including</p>
        <p>a)    Returns as defined in paragraph 3 of Article 1 of thisAgreement;</p>
        <p>b)   The proceeds of the total or partial liquidation ofany investment;</p>
        <p>c)    Payments made in accordance with credit agreement inconnection with an investment;</p>
        <p>d)   Payments for technical assistance, technical servicesand managerial experience;</p>
        <p>e)    Wages and other remuneration accruing to a citizen ofthe other Contracting Party who was permitted to work in connection with aninvestment in the territory of the other Contracting Party.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6">
        <p>Transfers in accordance with Articles 4 and 5 of thisAgreement shall be made be made at the rate of exchange of the ContractingParty hosting the investment applicable on the date of transfer.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7">
        <p>The Agreement, having entered into force, shall affectthe investments made by investors of the other Contracting Party in accordancewith the laws of the other Contracting Party in its territory before the dateof the Agreement entering into force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8">
        <p>1. Disputes, which arise with the interpretation or implementationof this Agreement, shall if possible be settled via diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2.   If the dispute has not beensettled this way for six months since it was incited by one of the ContractingParties, it shall be submitted, at the request of one of the Parties involved,to the decision of the ad hoc arbitration tribunal.</p>
        <p>1.    The arbitration tribunal is made up of threearbitrators and is established the following way: during two months uponreceipt by one of the Contracting Parties of a written notification of theother Contracting Party on submitting the dispute to the arbitration tribunal;each Contracting Parties appoints an arbitrator. The two appointed arbitratorsshall select the third arbitrator to be a citizen of a third State havingdiplomatic relations with both Contracting Parties, who on approval of theContracting Parties shall be appointed chairman of the arbitration tribunal.</p>
        <p>2.    If the arbitration tribunal has not been establishedwithin four months upon the receipt of a written notification on disputesubmission to the arbitration tribunal, any of the Contracting Parties if thereis no agreement to one of the above alternative procedures apply to Chairman ofthe International Tribunal to perform necessary appointments. If Chairman is acitizen of any of the Contracting Parties or for any other reason is not ableto perform the task, the authority to perform the appointments shall betransferred to the next senior member of the International Tribunal who iscitizen of neither of the Contracting Parties and is free to perform theappointments.</p>
        <p>3.    The arbitration tribunal shall determine its procedurerules. The Arbitration Tribunal takes a decision in accordance with theprovisions of this Agreement and universally recognized principles ofinternational law.</p>
        <p>4.    The Arbitration tribunal takes a decision by majorityvotes. The decision is final and obligatory for the Contracting Parties. Onrequest of any Contracting Party arbitration tribunal shall reason its decision. </p>
        <p>5.    Each Contracting Party shall bear costs related toarbitrator's activities and his/her participation in the arbitrary proceedings.Expenses related to Chairman activities and other costs shall be covered by theContracting Parties equally.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9">
        <p>Article 9</p>
        <p>1.    Disputes between a Contracting Party and an investor ofthe other Contracting Party about compensation amount in case of expropriationcan be submitted to the arbitration tribunal.</p>
        <p>2.    An arbitration tribunal shall be established for everyparticular case as follows: each Party appoints an arbitrator; the arbitratorsappointed select a citizen of a third State, having diplomatic relations withboth Contracting Parties who shall preside over the arbitration tribunal. Thetwo arbitrators are appointed within two months, Chairman is to be selectedwithin four months upon the receipt of a written notification on submitting thedispute to the arbitration tribunal. If within the period stated thearbitration tribunal has not been established, any of the Contracting Partiescan apply to Chairman of the Arbitration Institute of the Stockholm Chamber ofCommerce to perform all necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>3.    The arbitration tribunal shall determine its procedurerules. The arbitration tribunal can take the Rules of the Arbitration Instituteof the Stockholm Chamber of Commerce as guidance.</p>
        <p>4.    The Arbitration tribunal takes a decision by majorityvotes. The decision is final and obligatory for the Contracting Parties. EachParty is obliged to fulfill the decision in accordance with its State laws.</p>
        <p>5.    The Arbitration tribunal takes a decision inaccordance with in accordance with the provisions of this Agreement and thelaws of the State in whose territory investments were made, including collisionnorms and universally recognized principles of international law.</p>
        <p>6.    Each Contracting Party shall bear costs related toarbitrator's activities and his/her participation in the arbitrary proceedings.Expenses related to Chairman activities and other costs shall be covered by theContracting Parties equally.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10">
        <p>If any of the Contracting Parties in accordance withits laws or an international agreement to which both Contracting Parties arebound, creates more favorable investment regime for the other Contracting Partythan that established by this Agreement, a more favorable regime shall bebenefited from.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11">
        <p>1. If necessary, representatives of the Contracting Parties shallhold consultations aimed at:</p>
        <p>a)   Studying issues of theAgreement application;</p>
        <p>b)  Information exchange on legalinvestment issues;</p>
        <p>c)   Studying investment relatedissues;</p>
        <p>d)  Considering possiblealterations and amendments to the Agreement.</p>
        <p>2. Upon request by either Contracting Party, the other Contracting Partyshall agree promptly to consultation on any issue stated in paragraph 1 of thisArticle of this Agreement. The consultations shall be held by turns in Pekingand Minsk.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12">
        <p>1.     This Agreement shall enter into force in thirty dayson the date of the receipt of a written notification of the completion by theContracting Parties of domestic legal procedures for its entry into force andshall remain in force for five years.</p>
        <p>2. This Agreement shall remain in force unless eitherContracting Party   by means of a writtennotification advises the other Party of its intention to terminate theAgreement not less than a year in advance the term, defined in paragraph 1 ofthis Article.</p>
        <p>2.    On the expiry of the initial five-year term eachContracting Party can terminate the Agreement any time via a writtennotification of the other Contracting Party. The notification enters into forcein twelve months upon its receipt by the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>3.    In respect of investments or commitments to investmade prior to the date when the notice of termination of this Agreement becomeseffective, the provisions of Articles 1 to 11 inclusive of this Agreement shallremain in force for a period of fifteen years.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>In witness thereof, the undersigned, being dulyauthorized by their respective governments, have signed this Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done at Beijing on 11 January 1993 in duplicate, eachin the Belarusian, Chinese languages, all texts being equally authentic.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of Belarus</p>
      <p>For the Government of the People's Republic of China</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
