<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Egypt - Syrian Arab Republic BIT (1997)</name>
    <code>T1997-96</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">EGY</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">SYR</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1997-04-28</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1998-10-05</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">ar</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>1408</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source/>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{EGY,SYR}_1997-04-28.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>ar</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T1970-2">Agreement on Investment and Free Movement of Arab Capital among Arab Countries (1970)</relation>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T1981-11">OIC Investment Agreement (1981)</relation>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T1980-14">Unified Agreement for the Investment of Arab Capital in the Arab States (1980)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE ARAB REPUBLIC OF EGYPT AND THEGOVERNMENT OF THE SYRIAN ARAB REPUBLICFOR THE PROMOTION AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Arab Republic of Egypt and the Government of the Syrian Arab Republic, hereinafter referred to as the "Contracting Parties", </p>
      <p>Desiring to expand and deepen their economic cooperation for thebenefit of both countries and in particular in creating favorable conditionsfor investments of investors of either Contracting Party in the territory ofthe other Contracting Party,</p>
      <p>Recognizing the need for the protection of investments of investorsof both Contracting Parties, and for the stimulation of investment flows and individualinitiatives in business for the purpose of fostering the prosperity of bothContracting Parties.</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purpose of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>1. The term "investments"means all kinds of assets owned by an investor of a Contracting Party investedin the territory of the other Contracting Party following the entrance intoforce of this agreement, provided that the host party accepts it as an&#x2018;investment' in accordance with its laws and regulations.</p>
        <p>2. The term "investment"shall include in particular though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>a. Movable andimmovable funds and any of its related guarantees such as mortgages, liens, andother mortgages.</p>
        <p>b. Industrial andintellectual property rights, including copyrights, patents, trademarks, trade names,industrial designs, trade secrets, technical manufacturing processes, craftknowledge, and goodwill used in a licensed investment project.</p>
        <p>c. Company shares,bonds, securities, and ownership stock allowed to be traded in accordance withthe laws and regulations observed in both countries.</p>
        <p>3. The term "investor" means:</p>
        <p>a.     Natural persons possessing the nationality of one of the Contracting Parties in accordance with its laws, and who engage in investment activities in the territory of the other Contracting Party in accordance with its applicable laws and regulations.</p>
        <p>b.    Legal persons(entities and units recognized as such) in accordance with the laws of theContracting Party, such as companies and public, private and joint institutionswho engage in investment activities in the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>4.     The term "returns" means the net amounts yielded by an investment in accordance with the laws of the host country, including particularly though not exclusively profits and dividends.</p>
        <p>5. The term"territory" means:</p>
        <p>a. For the ArabRepublic of Egypt: land locatedwithin its international borders, internal waters, regional sea, continentalshelf and the special economic zone subject to its sovereignty or regionaljurisdiction in accordance with the provisions of international law.</p>
        <p>b.  For the Syrian ArabRepublic: its land, including the regionalsea, mainland, underground and below, the airspace above and all other areasoutside the territorial waters on which it exercises the right of sovereigntyin accordance with international rights, for the purpose of extraction andinvestment of natural, biological and mineral resources, and all other rightsthat exist in the water and under the seabed.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and protection of investments">
        <p>1. EachContracting Party shall encourage and create favorable conditions for investorsof the other Contracting Party to investment capital in its territory, and shalladmit such investments in accordance with its laws, regulations and nationalpolicies.</p>
        <p>2. Each ContractingParty shall grant the necessary facilities and permits for the entrance, exit,residence and work of the investor and persons whose work is permanently ortemporarily connected to the investment such as experts, administrative andtechnical staff and workers in accordance with the applicable laws andregulations of the host country.</p>
        <p>3. EachContracting Party commits to providing fair and equitable treatment toinvestments of investors of the other Contracting Party. They also commit thatthe management, maintenance, use, transfer, enjoyment or assignment of theinvestment made by investors of the other Contracting Party in its territory,in addition to companies and projects in which the investments were made, shallnot in any way be subject to discriminatory or legally unreasonable measures.</p>
        <p>4. Investments andreturns employed by natural or legal persons of the other Contracting Partyshall enjoy facilities, incentives and other forms of encouragement, includingexemptions from tax and other fees stipulated by the investment laws andregulations observed in the host country of the investment.</p>
        <p>5. EachContracting Party shall guarantee fair and equitable treatment to investments, establishedin accordance with its investment promotion laws and regulations, of investorsof the other Contracting Party. Such treatment shall not be less favorable thantreatment granted and applied to its own investors.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Nationalization and expropriation">
        <p>1. Investments ofinvestors of either Contracting Party shall not be subject, directly orindirectly, to expropriation, nationalization or any other measures having asimilar effect in the territory of the other Contracting Party, except for apublic interest, on a non-discriminatory basis and against the payment of faircompensation based on legal regulations and without unreasonable delay.</p>
        <p>2. Fair compensationshall be based on the real market value immediately before the nationalizationor expropriation measure was announced.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Compensation">
        <p>Investors of either Contracting Party who suffer losses to theirinvestments in the territory of the other Contracting Party due to war, armedconflict, revolt, a state of national emergency or insurrection shall beaccorded, with respect to restitution, compensation for losses or other formsof compensation, treatment which is no less favorable than that accorded to itsown investors.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Repatriation of capital and returns">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall permit the repatriation of capital andreturns invested in its territory abroad, in the same currency it was investedin or in any freely convertible currency, without delay, in accordance with theapplicable investment laws and regulations, which includes for example:</p>
        <p>1. Investedcapital, including reinvested returns for the purpose of the maintenance orincrease of the investment.</p>
        <p>2. Profits,dividends, interest, or other due returns from any investment made by aninvestor of the other Contracting Party in accordance with its applicableinvestment laws.</p>
        <p>3. Proceeds fromthe full or partial sale or liquidation of aninvestment made by investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>4. Repayment ofloan installments and its interest obtained with the knowledge of the hostcountry of the investment in foreign currencies from abroad, for the purpose offinancing or expanding the investment.</p>
        <p>5. Compensationprovided for in Articles (3 &amp; 4) of this agreement and payments obtainedfrom disputes related to the project.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Settlement of disputes between the investor and the host country">
        <p>Disputes related to various aspects of the investment, its relatedactivities and returns of a Contracting Party or its nationals shall be settledthrough conciliation, arbitration, the competent court in the host country ofthe investment, the Arab Investment Court established in accordance withSection 6 of the Unified Agreement for the Investment of Arab Capital in theArab States and its annex approved by the Arab Economic and Social Council inits Resolution no. 841 dated 10/09/1980, or the Cairo Centre for InternationalCommercial Arbitration.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Committee to pursue implementation of the agreement">
        <p>Inan effort to achieve the goals of this agreement, a joint committee shall beestablished at the ministerial level between both countries to promote andprotect investments. The committee's responsibilities shall include:</p>
        <p>1. Pursue theimplementation of this agreement.</p>
        <p>2. Examine waysand methods for the promotion of investment between the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>3. Work oneliminating obstacles hindering the implementation of investments.</p>
        <p>4. Examine waysand methods for the development and financing of joint projects in bothcountries.</p>
        <p>5. Examine theproposed suggestions referred to it by the relevant bodies in both countries.</p>
        <p>6. Adopt aconciliatory role in disputes related to investment activities and work towardssettling them amicably.</p>
        <p>The committee shall meet periodically on a yearly basis, andwhenever necessary, in each country alternately.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Dispute settlement between the contracting parties">
        <p>Any dispute between the Contracting Parties concerning theinterpretation of the provisions of this agreement shall be settled through discussionsbetween representatives of the Contracting Parties. If the dispute concerns theimplementation of this agreement - and if it cannot be settled within twelvemonths from the beginning of the dispute- it may be referred to an arbitrationtribunal of three members, based on the request of either Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall appoint an arbitrator, and thesearbitrators shall appoint a chairman to the tribunal who shall be a national ofa third country.</p>
        <p>If either Contracting Party does not appoint an arbitrator and doesnot give consideration to the other Contracting Party's invitation to make theappointment within two months, the appointment shall be made based on a requestsubmitted by that Contracting Party to the Secretary-General of the League ofArab States.</p>
        <p>If both arbitrators fail to agree on a chairman to the tribunalwithin two months after they were appointed, the appointment shall be madebased on a request submitted by either Contracting Party to theSecretary-General of the League of Arab States.</p>
        <p>Subject to other provisions agreed upon between the ContractingParties, the tribunal shall determine its legal procedures.</p>
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall bear the cost of its appointed arbitratorand the representation costs in the arbitral hearings. The cost of the chairmanand the remaining costs shall be borne in equal parts by the ContractingParties.</p>
        <p>Thetribunal's decisions shall be final and binding on each Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Entry into force">
        <p>This Agreement shall enter into force (30) days from the date ofthe last notification of completion of the ratification procedures by theContracting Parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Duration and termination">
        <p>This Agreement shall remain in force for a period of ten years, andshall be automatically renewed for similar periods, unless either ContractingParty notifies the other Contracting Party in writing of its intention to terminateit a year before its expiration. Investments made before the end of thisagreement shall remain subject to it for a period of ten years from the date ofits termination.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>In witness whereof the undersigned, duly authorized thereto bytheir respective Governments, have signed this Agreement</p>
      <p>Done on Wednesday 21 Muharam 1417 H, corresponding to 28 May 1997in two originals in Arabic, all texts being equally authentic.</p>
      <p>FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE ARAB REPUBLIC OF EGYPT</p>
      <p>Dr. Nawal Abdulmonim Al Tatawi</p>
      <p>Minister of Economy and InternationalCooperation</p>
      <p>FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE SYRIAN ARAB REPUBLIC</p>
      <p>Dr. Mohamed Al Omadi</p>
      <p>Minister of Economy and Foreign Trade</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
