<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Malaysia - Uruguay BIT (1995)</name>
    <code>T1995-190</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">MYS</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">URY</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1995-08-09</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2002-04-13</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">es</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>2492</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>es</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{MYS,URY}_1995-08-09.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT FOR THE PROMOTION AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS WITH THE GOVERNMENT OF MALAYSIA</p>
    </title>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>1. For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>a) "investments means every kind of asset and in particular, though not exclusively, includes: <br/>movable and immovable property and any other property rights such as mortgages, liens or pledges; <br/>shares, stocks and bonds of companies or interests in the property of such companies; <br/>claims dinerarios any benefit or having financial value; <br/>Intellectual Property Rights, including copyrights, patents, trademarks, registered names, industrial designs, trade secrets and know-how, technical processes, key value; <br/>business concessions conferred by law or under contract, including concessions for research, crops, extract or exploit natural resources;<br/></p>
        <p>b) Income "" refers to the amount by yielded an investment and in particular, though not exclusively, includes interests, capital gains, profits, dividends, royalties or gratuities;</p>
        <p>c) "investor" refers to: any person possessing the citizenship of one of the contracting parties and who is not a citizen of the other contracting party, in accordance with its laws; or <br/>any corporation, partnership, firm, joint-ventures, association or enterprise duly incorporated or constituted under the laws of that Contracting Party;<br/></p>
        <p>d) "territory means: <br/>with regard to Malaysia, covering the entire territory of the Federation of Malaysia; the territorial sea and its seabed, subsoil and airspace; <br/>with regard to the Eastern Republic of Uruguay, its territory as well as those maritime areas including the seabed and subsoil adjacent to the outer limit of the territorial sea over which Uruguay exercises, in accordance with international law, sovereign rights for the purpose of the exploration and exploitation of natural resources of such areas;<br/></p>
        <p>e) "currency free course" refers to the United States dollar, pound sterling framework, German, French franc, the Japanese yen or any currency widely used in international transactions and free convertibility in the principal international exchange markets.</p>
        <p>2.</p>
        <p>i) The term "investment" referred to in paragraph 1 (a), only refers to all investments made in accordance with the laws, regulations and national policies of the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>ii) Any change in the form of a good investment of shall not affect their character as an investment, provided that such change is not contrary to the Act of approval of the originally invested assets, if the same propagated.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and Protection of Investments">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall promote and create favourable conditions for investors of the other contracting party to invest capital in its territory and in accordance with its laws, regulations and national policies, shall admit such investments.</p>
        <p>2. At any time shall be accorded fair and equitable treatment to the investments made by investors of each Contracting Party who shall enjoy full and adequate protection and security in the territory of the other contracting party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="The Most-favoured-nation Clause">
        <p>1. Investments made by investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall receive a fair and equitable and not less favourable than that accorded to investments made by investors of any third State.</p>
        <p>2. The provisions of this Agreement relating to the grant of not less favourable treatment than that accorded to investors of any third State shall not be interpreted as an obligation of one contracting party to extend to the investors of the other party the benefit of any treatment, preference or privilege resulting from:</p>
        <p>a) Any existing or future customs union or free trade area or a common market or a customs union or similar international agreement or other forms of regional cooperation to which either Contracting Party is or may become a party; or the conclusion of an agreement to lead to the formation or extension of such a union or area within a reasonable period of time; or</p>
        <p>b) Any international agreement or arrangement relating wholly or mainly to taxation or any domestic legislation relating wholly or mainly to taxation matters.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Compensation for Losses">
        <p>Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of the other contracting party suffer losses owing to war or other armed conflict, revolution, state of national emergency, revolt, riot or insurrection in the territory of the latter, from Contracting Party shall receive this treatment as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or other compensation not less favourable than that which the latter Contracting Party agrees to investors of a third State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Expropriation">
        <p>Neither of the Contracting Parties shall take measures of expropriation, nationalization or other measures effectively remove possession with equivalent effect to the investment against expropriation or nationalization of an investor of the other contracting party except under the following conditions:</p>
        <p>a) Where the measures are taken for a lawful purpose and under due process;</p>
        <p>b) Where the measures are not discriminatory;</p>
        <p>c) Where the measures are accompanied by provisions for the payment of prompt, effective and adequate compensation. such compensation shall amount to the market value of the affected investments immediately before the measure of dispossession became public knowledge, and shall be freely transferable in a free flow of currency from the contracting party. any unjustified delay in payment of compensation shall interests according to the commercial rate for use as agreed by both parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Transfers">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall allow without unjustified delay the transfer of currency in a free flow of:</p>
        <p>a) Net income, dividends, royalties, technical assistance and technical fees, interest and other current accrued investment income, from any of the investors of the other contracting party;</p>
        <p>b) Results from the total or partial liquidation of any investment made by investors of the other contracting party;</p>
        <p>c) Funds for the repago loans or requested by investors of one Contracting Party to investors of the other Contracting Party which both contracting parties have recognized as investments; and</p>
        <p>d) The net earnings and other compensations of investors of one Contracting Party who are employed and allowed to work in connection with investments in the territory of the other contracting party.</p>
        <p>2. The exchange rates applicable to such transfer referred to in paragraph 1 of this article shall be those used at the date of transfer.</p>
        <p>3. The Contracting Parties undertake to accord to transfers referred to in paragraph 1 of this article a treatment as favourable as that accorded to transfers originating from investments made by investors of any third State.</p>
        <p>4. Transfers are subject to the right of each Contracting Party to exercise and equitable in good faith its powers conferred by laws and regulations in force at the date of the investment, as well as any new laws and regulations, provided that no investor may be placed in a less favourable position as at the date of initiation of the investment.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Settlement of Investment Dispute between a Contracting Party and an Investor of the other Contracting Party">
        <p>1. Disputes arising within the framework of this Agreement between the investor of one Contracting Party and the other Contracting Party shall be settled as far as possible by consultations and negotiations.</p>
        <p>2. For the purposes of this article, a dispute by investments are defined as the dispute concerning the interpretation or application of the provisions of this Agreement with respect to any investment made by an investor of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other contracting party.</p>
        <p>3. If the dispute as defined in paragraph 2 of this article cannot be settled in this way within six months of notification of a claim, be submitted, a decision by the claimant to one or the other of the following bodies:</p>
        <p>a) The competent judicial or administrative tribunals of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investment has been made;</p>
        <p>b) An arbitral tribunal of three members. the arbitrators shall be appointed in accordance with the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law (UNCITRAL); or the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes when both parties are contracting parties to the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of Other States, opened for signature at Washington, DC., on 18 March 1965, for settlement by conciliation or arbitration to an arbitral tribunal of three members. the arbitrators shall be appointed in accordance with the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law (UNCITRAL); or the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes when both parties are contracting parties to the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of Other States, opened for signature at Washington, DC., on 18 March 1965, for settlement by conciliation or arbitration.</p>
        <p>In the event that an investor chooses to submit the dispute to the competent court of the Contracting Party where the investment has been made or to international arbitration, that election shall be definitive.</p>
        <p>4. The arbitral tribunal shall decide the dispute in accordance with the terms of this Agreement, the legislation of the Contracting Party involved in the dispute, the terms of any specific agreement concluded in relation to the investment and the relevant principles of International Law.</p>
        <p>5. The judgment or arbitral decision taken shall be final and binding on both parties to the dispute.</p>
        <p>6. Neither Contracting Party shall submit an international claim in respect of a dispute which one of its investors and the other contracting party have submitted to international arbitration or a decision of the competent court of the Party in whose territory the investment has been made, unless the other Contracting Party has not implemented or the decision or award rendered in such dispute.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of Disputes between the Contracting Parties">
        <p>1. Disputes between the contracting parties concerning the interpretation or application of this agreement should, if possible, be settled through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2. In the event that a dispute between the contracting parties cannot be settled in this way, at the request of either contracting party be submitted to an arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>3. Such an arbitral tribunal shall be constituted for each individual case in the following way: within two months of receipt of the request for arbitration, each Contracting Party shall appoint one member of the Tribunal. these two members shall then select a national of a third State who on approval by the two Contracting Parties shall be appointed Chairman of the Tribunal. the Chairman shall be appointed within two (2) months from the date of appointment of the other two members.</p>
        <p>4. If within the periods specified in paragraph 3 of this article have not been completed the necessary appointments, either Contracting Party may, in the absence of any other agreement, invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointments. if the President is a national of either Contracting Party or if he is otherwise prevented from discharging that function, the Vice-President shall be invited to make the necessary appointments. if the Vice-President is a national of either Contracting Party or if he is also prevented from fulfilling the said function, the member of the International Court of Justice next in seniority who is not a national of either Contracting Party shall be invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>5. The arbitral tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. such decision shall be binding on both contracting parties. each Contracting Party shall bear the costs of its representative in the Tribunal and of its representation in the arbitral proceedings; the cost of the Chairman and the remaining charges shall be borne in equal parts by the contracting parties. however, the Tribunal shall decide that a higher proportion of costs shall be borne by one of the two contracting parties and this decision shall be binding on both contracting parties. the tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Subrogation">
        <p>1. If a Contracting Party or an agency of a Party conducting a payment to any of its investors under a guarantee or a contract of insurance it has entered into with respect to an investment, the other Contracting Party shall recognize the validity of the subrogation in favour of such Contracting Party or agency to any right of the investor.</p>
        <p>2. The Contracting Party or its contractual subrogation agency, to the rights of the investor in accordance with paragraph 1 of this article is entitled in all circumstances to the same rights as those of the investor in respect of the concerned and its investment returns. those rights may be exercised by the party or its agency or by the investor if authorised by the said Contracting Party or an agency.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Implementation of Investments">
        <p>1. This Agreement shall apply to investments made in the territory of either Contracting Party in accordance with its laws, regulations or national policy by investors of the other contracting party prior to and after the Entry into Force of this Agreement.</p>
        <p>2. The Agreement shall not apply in any case to differences or disputes which arose before its Entry into Force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Amendments">
        <p>This Agreement may be amended by mutual consent of the contracting parties at any time after its Entry into Force. the agreed amendments shall enter into force thirty (30) days after the parties have notified each other of the completion of the constitutional requirements for Entry into Force. any alteration or modification of this Agreement shall be without prejudice to the rights and obligations arising from this agreement prior to the date of such amendment or modification and so that those rights and obligations are implemented in its entirety.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Entry Into Force , Duration and Termination">
        <p>1. This Agreement shall enter into force thirty days after the date on which the Governments of the Contracting Parties have notified each other of the completion of the constitutional requirements for the Entry into Force of the Agreement. the later date shall refer to the date of referral of the last notification letter.</p>
        <p>2. This Agreement shall remain in force for a period of ten years and shall continue in force unless terminated in accordance with paragraph 3 of this article.</p>
        <p>3. Unless one of the Contracting Parties notifies the other contracting party of its intention to terminate this Agreement one year before the end of the period of ten years, including the Agreement this article shall be automatically extended for another period of ten years.</p>
        <p>4. With respect to investments made or acquired prior to the date of termination of this Agreement, the provisions of all of the other articles of this Agreement shall remain in force for a period of ten years from such date of termination.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>In WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, being duly authorised by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done in duplicate at Montevideo, nine days of the month of August 1995, Malay, Spanish and English languages, all texts being equally authentic. in case of divergence of interpretation, the English text shall prevail.</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
