<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Croatia - Netherlands BIT (1998)</name>
    <code>T1998-131</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">HRV</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">NLD</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1998-04-28</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1999-06-01</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated>2021-03-31</date_terminated>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type>Terminated by consent</termination_type>
    <docreference>1093</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>Terminated by consent</IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{HRV,NLD}_1998-04-28.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T1994-84">The Energy Charter Treaty (1994)</relation>
    <relation type="TERMINATED_BY_THIRD_TREATY" document-code="T1994-84">The Energy Charter Treaty (1994)</relation>
    <relation type="IT_OVERLAP" document-code="T2020-2">Agreement for the Termination of Bilateral Investment Treaties Between the Member States of the European Union (2020)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Agreement on Encouragement and Reciprocal Protection of Investments between the Republic of Croatia and the Kingdom of the Netherlands</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Republic of Croatia, hereinafter referred to as the Contracting Parties,</p>
      <p>Desiring to strengthen their traditional ties of friendship and to extend and intensify the economic relations between them particularly with respect to investments by the nationals of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party,</p>
      <p>Recognizing that agreement upon the treatment to be accorded to such investments will stimulate the flow of capital and technology and the economic development of the Contracting Parties and that fair and equitable treatment of investment is desirable, Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>a) The term "investments" means every kind of asset, more particularly, though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>(i) Movable and immovable property as well as any other rights in rem in respect of every kind of asset;</p>
        <p>(ii) Rights derived from shares, bonds and other kinds of interests in companies and joint ventures;</p>
        <p>(iii) Claims to money, to other assets or to any performance having an economic value;</p>
        <p>(iv) Rights in the field of intellectual property, technical processes, goodwill and knowhow;</p>
        <p>(v) Rights granted under public law or under contract, including rights to prospect, explore, extract and win natural resources.</p>
        <p>b) The term "nationals" shall comprise with regard to either Contracting Party:</p>
        <p>(i) Natural persons having the nationality of that Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>(ii) Legal persons constituted under the law of that Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>(iii) Legal persons not constituted under the law of that Contracting Party but controlled, directly or indirectly, by natural persons as defined in (i) or by legal persons as defined in (ii).</p>
        <p>c) The term "territory" means:</p>
        <p>(i) With respect to the Kingdom of the Netherlands the term "territory" includes any area adjacent to the territorial sea which, under the laws of the Kingdom, and in accordance with international law, is the exclusive economic zone or continental shelf of the Kingdom, in which it exercises jurisdiction or sovereign rights.</p>
        <p>(ii) With respect to the Republic of Croatia the territory of the Republic of Croatia as well as those maritime areas adjacent to the outer limit of the territorial sea including the seabed and subsoil over which the Republic of Croatia exercises sovereign rights and jurisdiction in accordance with international law.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2">
        <p>Either Contracting Party shall, within the framework of its laws and regulations, promote economic cooperation through the protection in its territory of investments of nationals of the other Contracting Party. Subject to its right to exercise powers conferred by its laws or regulations, each Contracting Party shall admit such investments.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall ensure fair and equitable treatment of the investments of nationals of the other Contracting Party and shall not impair, by unreasonable or discriminatory measures, the operation, management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal thereof by those nationals. Each Contracting Party shall accord to such investments full physical security and protection.</p>
        <p>2. More particularly, each Contracting Party shall accord to such investments treatment which in any case shall not be less favourable than that accorded either to investments of its own nationals or to investments of nationals of any third State, whichever is more favourable to the national concerned.</p>
        <p>3. If a Contracting Party has accorded special advantages to nationals of any third State by virtue of agreements establishing customs unions, economic unions, monetary unions or similar institutions, or on the basis of interim agreements leading to such unions or institutions, that Contracting Party shall not be obliged to accord such advantages to nationals of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>4. Each Contracting Party shall observe any obligation it may have entered into with regard to investments of nationals of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>5. If the provisions of law of either Contracting Party or obligations under international law existing at present or established hereafter between the Contracting Parties in addition to the present Agreement contain a regulation, whether general or specific, entitling investments by nationals of the other Contracting Party to a treatment more favourable than is provided for by the present Agreement, such regulation shall to the extent that it is more favourable prevail over the present Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4">
        <p>With respect to taxes, fees, charges and to fiscal deductions and exemptions, each Contracting Party shall accord to nationals of the other Contracting Party who are engaged in any economic activity in its territory, treatment not less favourable than that accorded to its own nationals or to those of any third State that are in the same circumstances, whichever is more favourable to the nationals concerned. For this purpose, however, there shall not be taken into account any special fiscal advantages accorded by that Party:</p>
        <p>a) Under an agreement for the avoidance of double taxation; or</p>
        <p>b) By virtue of its participation in a customs union, economic union or similar institution; or</p>
        <p>c) On the basis of reciprocity with a third State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5">
        <p>The Contracting Parties shall guarantee that payments relating to an investment may be transferred. The transfers shall be made in a freely convertible currency, without restriction or delay. Such transfers include in particular though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>a) Profits, interest, dividends and other current income;</p>
        <p>b) Funds necessary</p>
        <p>(i) For the acquisition of raw or auxiliary materials, semi-fabricated or finished products, or</p>
        <p>(ii) To replace capital assets in order to safeguard the continuity of an investment;</p>
        <p>c) Additional funds necessary for the development of an investment;</p>
        <p>d) Funds in repayment of loans;</p>
        <p>e) Royalties or fees;</p>
        <p>f) Earnings of natural persons;</p>
        <p>g) The proceeds of sale or liquidation of the investment;</p>
        <p>h) Payments arising under Article 7.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6">
        <p>Neither Contracting Party shall take any measures depriving, directly or indirectly, nationals of the other Contracting Party of their investments unless the following conditions are complied with:</p>
        <p>a) The measures are taken in the public interest and under due process of law;</p>
        <p>b) The measures are not discriminatory or contrary to any undertaking which the Contracting Party which takes such measures may have given;</p>
        <p>c) The measures are taken against just compensation. Such compensation shall represent the genuine value of the investments affected, shall not include interest at a normal commercial rate until the date of payment and shall, in order to be effective for the claimants, be paid and made transferable, without delay, to the country designated by the claimants concerned and in the currency of the country of which the claimants are nationals or in any freely convertible currency accepted by the claimants.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7">
        <p>Nationals of the one Contracting Party who suffer losses in respect of their investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party owing to war or other armed conflict, revolution, a state of national emergency, revolt, insurrection or riot shall be accorded by the other Contracting Party treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or other settlement, no less favourable than that which that Contracting Party accords to its own nationals or to nationals of any third State, whichever is more favourable to the nationals concerned.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8">
        <p>If the investments of a national of the one Contracting Party are insured against noncommercial risks or otherwise give rise to payment of indemnification in respect of such investments under a system established by law, regulation or government contract any subrogation of the insurer or re-insurer or Agency designated by the one Contracting Party to the rights of the said national pursuant to the terms of such insurance or under any other indemnity given shall be recognized by the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9">
        <p>1. Disputes between one Contracting Party and a national of the other Contracting Party concerning an obligation of the former under this agreement in relation to an investment of the latter, shall at the request of the national concerned be submitted to the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes, for settlement by arbitration or conciliation under the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of other States, opened for signature at Washington on 18 March 1965.</p>
        <p>2. As long as the Republic of Croatia has not become a Contracting State of the Convention as mentioned in paragraph 1 of this Article, disputes as referred to in that paragraph shall be submitted to the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes under the Rules Governing the Additional Facility for the Administration of Proceedings by the Secretariat of the Centre (Additional Facility of Rules).</p>
        <p>3. Each Contracting Party hereby gives its unconditional consent to the submission of disputes as referred to in Paragraph 1 of this Article to international arbitration in accordance with the provisions of this Article.</p>
        <p>4. A legal person which is a national of one Contracting Party and which before such a dispute arises is controlled by nationals of the other Contracting Party shall in accordance with Article 25 (2) b) of the Convention for the purpose of the Convention be treated as a national of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10">
        <p>The present Agreement shall apply to investments, made in the territory of one of the Contracting Parties, in accordance with its legislation, by investors of the other Contracting Party prior to as well as after the entry into force of the present Agreement. The present Agreement shall however not be applicable to disputes concerning investments which are subject of a dispute settlement procedure under the Agreement on the Protection of Investments between the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia and the Kingdom of the Netherlands of 16 February 1976. In that case the latter Agreement shall continue to apply to these investments, as far as it concerns the disputes referred to, until a final settlement for these disputes has been reached.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11">
        <p>Either Contracting Party may propose the other Party that consultations be held on any matter concerning the interpretation or application of the Agreement. The other Party shall accord sympathetic consideration to the proposal and shall afford adequate opportunity for such consultations.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12">
        <p>1. Any dispute between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or application of the present Agreement, which cannot be settled within a reasonable lapse of time by means of diplomatic negotiations, shall, unless the Contracting Parties have otherwise agreed, be submitted, at the request of either Contracting Party, to an arbitral tribunal, composed of three members. Each Contracting Party shall appoint one arbitrator and the two arbitrators thus appointed shall together appoint a third arbitrator as their chairman who is not a national of either Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>2. If one of the Contracting Parties fails to appoint its arbitrator and has not proceeded to do so within two months after an invitation from the other Party to make such appointment, the latter Contracting Party may invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointment.</p>
        <p>3. If the two arbitrators are unable to reach agreement, in the two months following their appointment, on the choice of the third arbitrator, either Contracting Party may invite the President of the International Court of Justice, to make the necessary appointment.</p>
        <p>4. If, in the cases provided for in the paragraphs (2) and (3) of this Article, the President of the International Court of Justice is prevented from discharging the said function or is a national of either Contracting Party, the Vice-President shall be invited to make the necessary appointments. If the Vice-President is prevented from discharging the said function or is a national of either Contracting Party the most senior member of the Court available who is not a national of either Party shall be invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>5. The tribunal shall decide on the basis of respect for the law. Before the tribunal decides, it may at any stage of the proceedings propose to the Contracting Parties that the dispute be settled amicably. The foregoing provisions shall not prejudice settlement of the dispute ex aequo et bono if the Parties so agree.</p>
        <p>6. Unless the Contracting Parties decide otherwise, the tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
        <p>7. The tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Such decision shall be final and binding on the Contracting Parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13">
        <p>As regards the Kingdom of the Netherlands, the present Agreement shall apply to the part of the Kingdom in Europe, to the Netherlands Antilles and to Aruba, unless the notification provided for in Article 14, paragraph (1) provides otherwise.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="14">
        <p>1. The present Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the second month following the date on which the Contracting Parties have notified each other in writing that their constitutionally required procedures have been complied with, and shall remain in force for a period of fifteen years.</p>
        <p>2. Unless notice of termination has been given by either Contracting Party at least six months before the date of the expiry of its validity, the present Agreement shall be extended tacitly for periods of ten years, whereby each Contracting Party reserves the right to terminate the Agreement upon notice of at least six months before the date of expiry of the current period of validity.</p>
        <p>3. In respect of investments made before the date of the termination of the present Agreement the foregoing Articles shall continue to be effective for a further period of fifteen years from that date.</p>
        <p>4. Subject to the period mentioned in paragraph (2) of this Article, the Kingdom of the Netherlands shall be entitled to terminate the application of the present Agreement separately in respect of any of the parts of the Kingdom.</p>
        <p>5. On the day of entry into force of the present Agreement, the Agreement on the Protection of Investments between the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia and the Kingdom of the Netherlands of 16 February 1976 shall be terminated, except for the purpose of settlement of existing disputes as referred to in Article 10 of the present Agreement.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>Done in duplicate at Zagreb on April 28th 1998, in the Netherlands, and Croatian and English languages, the three texts being equally authentic.</p>
      <p>In case of difference of interpretation the English text will prevail.</p>
      <p>For the Republic of Croatia</p>
      <p>For the Kingdom of the Netherlands</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
