<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Guatemala - Taiwan Province of China BIT (1999)</name>
    <code>T1999-93</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">GTM</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">TWN</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1999-11-02</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2001-12-01</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en,es,zh</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>1834</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>https://investtaiwan.nat.gov.tw/showBusinessPagechtG_Agreement01?lang=cht&amp;search=G_Agreement01&amp;menuNum=92</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{GTM,TWN}_1999-11-02.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en,es,zh</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T2005-62">Guatemala - Taiwan Province of China FTA (2005)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENTBETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THEREPUBLIC OF GUATEMALA FOR THE PROMOTION AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>TheGovernment of the Republic of China and the Governmentof the Republic of Guatemala, hereinafter referred toas the "Contracting Parties",</p>
      <p>Desiring topromote greater economic cooperation for the reciprocalbenefits of both Contacting Parties,</p>
      <p>Intendingto create favorable conditions for investments, that willstimulate economic and technological development in theterritories of the Contracting Parties, and increase the productionof investors of each Contracting Party in the of theother, and </p>
      <p>Recognizingthat the promotion and protection of investments, through thepresent Agreement, will be conducive to the stimulationof business initiative and to the development of economiccooperation between them,</p>
      <p>Have agreedas follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For thepurposes of the present Agreement:</p>
        <p>1."Investment" means: any kind of asset, in goods or rights, owned byan investor of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other ContractingParty in accordance with thelatter's laws and, in particular, though not exclusively, includes:</p>
        <p>a) Movableand immovable property and any other related rights;</p>
        <p>b) Sharesof stock, documents of title and debentures of companies or any other forms ofparticipation in a company;</p>
        <p>c) Creditsor claims that have an economic value and that are directly related to an investment;</p>
        <p>d) Intellectualproperty rights according to the legislation of the Contracting Parties;</p>
        <p>e) Rightsconferred by law or under contract, to undertake any economic and commercialactivities, including any rights to search for, cultivate, extract or exploitnatural resources,</p>
        <p>Any changein the form of an investment shall not affect its character as an investment.</p>
        <p>Investmentsin areas restricted by the Constitution, laws and regulations of theContracting Party receiving the investment are excluded, among them, thoseactivities reserved for nationals of each Contracting Party. The aboverestriction or reservation shall not be discriminatory between investors fromthe other Contracting Party and investorsfrom any third States.</p>
        <p>It will beconsidered that the Government of the receiving Contracting Party has given itsapproval, when that Government grants to an Investor from the other ContactingParty commercial licenses, patents, or any other related documents required toinitiate operations.</p>
        <p>2."Returns" means: all amounts yielded by an investment, as referred toin paragraph 1 of this article and in particular, though not exclusively,includes profits, interests, capital gains, dividends, royalties, and fees.</p>
        <p>3."Investor" means:</p>
        <p>a) Anynatural persons possessing the nationality of one of the Contracting Partiesaccording to its legislation, and that make investments, as referred to inparagraph 1 of thisarticle;</p>
        <p>b) Anylegal persons, duly incorporated or constituted in accordance with the laws ofone of the Contracting Parties, and that make investments, as referred to in paragraph1 of this article;</p>
        <p>4."Territory" means:</p>
        <p>a) For theRepublic of China: The territory, including the territorial sea and any maritimearea situated beyond the territorial sea, over which the Republic of China may exercisesovereignty rights or jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>b) For theRepublic of Guatemala: The land and waters and air space and the marine andsubmarine zones over which the State exercises sovereignty in accordance with theConstitution of the Republic of Guatemala and international law.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and protection">
        <p>1. EachContracting Party shall encourage and create favorable conditions in itsterritory for investments of investors of the other Contracting Party,according to its Constitution, laws and regulations.</p>
        <p>2. EachContracting Party shall promote, to the extent possible, the investmentsreferred to in paragraph 1, and shall at all times be accorded fair andequitable treatment; and, it shall provide, in accordance with its laws andregulations, all necessary permits related to such investments as well as allauthorizations required to perform the license and technical, commercial or administrativeassistance contracts.</p>
        <p>3. EachContracting Party shall protect the investments of investors of the otherContracting Party in its territory, and shall eliminate all obstacles andprejudices, arbitrary or discriminatory measures suffered by these investments,and will abstain itself from incorporating any administrative measures thatmight affect these investments.</p>
        <p>Bothreturns of the investments, and the reinvestments shall enjoy the sameprotection established for the investments.</p>
        <p>4. Allinvestments approved by either Contracting Party shall be covered under thisAgreement.</p>
        <p>5. Theinvestments made in the territory of any of the Contracting Parties, before theentry into force of this Agreement, shall be covered by the protectionestablished in it, at the request of the interested investor.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless,this Agreement shall not apply to disputes which arose prior to its entry intoforce.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="National and most-favoured-nation treatment">
        <p>1. Inaccordance with its laws and regulations, each Contracting Party shall grantinvestments made by investors of the other Contracting Party in the former's territory treatment no less favorable than that granted to investments of its owninvestors, or from any third State.</p>
        <p>2. Nothingin this article shall be construed so as to oblige a Contracting Party toextend to investments of investors of the other Contracting Party advantagesresulting from any existing or future Association or participation in a free tradearea, customs union, common market, economic and monetary union or any othersimilar institutions of economic integration.</p>
        <p>3. Nothingin this article shall be construed so as to oblige a Contracting Party toextend to investments of investors of the other Contracting Party deductions, fiscalexemptions or any other similar advantages resulting from double taxationagreements or any other agreement regarding tax matters concluded between oneContracting Party and any third State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Expropriation and compensation">
        <p>1.Investments of investors of either Contracting Party shall enjoy fullprotection and security in accordance with the legislation of the ContractingParty in which the investmentis made.</p>
        <p>2.Investments of investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of theother Contracting Party shall not be nationalized, expropriated, or subjectedto measures having anequivalent effect, except in cases when any such measures have been adopted for'public purpose, in accordance with the Constitution and due process of law, ona non discriminatory basis.</p>
        <p>TheContracting Party that adopts any such measures, shall be obliged to pay,according to its laws and regulations, a prompt, adequate and effectivecompensation. The compensation shall amount to the fair market price of the investmentexpropriated immediately before expropriation or impending expropriation becamepublic knowledge, whichever was earlier. It shall include interest from the dateof dispossession of the expropriated property until the date of payment.</p>
        <p>Before theexpropriation, nationalization or measures having an equivalent effect takesplace, the Contracting Party making the expropriation shall take into, considerationmeasures to make a satisfactory compensation to investors of the other ContractingParty.</p>
        <p>Theinvestor affected shall have a right, under the law of the Contracting Partymaking the expropriation, to prompt review, by a judicial or other independentauthority of that Contacting Party, of his or its case and of the valuation ofhis or its investment in accordance with the principles set out in thisparagraph.</p>
        <p>3.Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of theother Contracting Party suffer damages or losses owing to war or other armedconflicts, a state of national emergency, revolt, insurrection or riot in the territoryof the latter Contracting Party shall be accorded by the latter ContactingParty treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or othersettlement, no less favorable than that which the latter Contracting Partyaccords to its own nationals or investors of any third State.</p>
        <p>The Contracting Party which may take any such measures shall be liable to pay, in accordance with its laws and regulations, a prompt, effective and adequate compensation. The compensation shall be the fair market value of the expropriated investment immediately before the expropriation or impending expropriation became public knowledge, what happens first. It shall include interest from the date on which the original owner be deprived of the expropriated property until the date of payment. before the expropriation and nationalization measures or having an equivalent effect, the contracting party making the expropriation shall take account of measures to offset satisfactorily to investors of the other contracting party. the Investor affected shall have a right under the law of the contracting party making the expropriation, to promote the review by a judicial or other independent authority of the contracting party of its case and of the valuation of its investment in accordance with the principles set out in this paragraph.</p>
        <p>3. Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of the other contracting party suffer loss or damage owing to war or other armed conflict, a national state of emergency, revolt, riot or insurrection in the territory of the contracting party recently referred to receive the contracting party recently referred to as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or other settlement, a treatment no less favourable than that which the contracting party recently referred to it provides to its own nationals or to investors of third States.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Transfers">
        <p>1. EachContracting Party shall guarantee investors of the other Contracting Party, inaccordance with its laws and regulations, the unrestricted transfer of paymentsrelated to their investments. Such transfers shall include, in particular,though not exclusively, the following:</p>
        <p>a)Additional amounts needed to maintain, expand and develop the Investment;</p>
        <p>b) Returns;</p>
        <p>c) Paymentsmade according to the terms of a contract, among them mortgages, repayments ofloans related to an investment;</p>
        <p>d) Cashderived from the partial or total sale or liquidation of the investment;</p>
        <p>e) Thecompensations referred to in article 4;</p>
        <p>f) Thepayments resulting from a dispute settlement procedure</p>
        <p>2. Subject tothe exchange regime in effect, transfers shall be effected at the market rateof exchange applicable on the date of transfer and shall be made without delayin any freelyconvertible currency.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Subrogation">
        <p>If aContracting Party or its designated agency makes a payment under an indemnityagainst non-commercial risks given in respect of an investment in the territoryof the other Contracting Party, the latter Contracting Party shall recognize theassignment, under the law of that country, of any light or claim from theinvestor to the former Contracting Party, or its designated agency, as well asthe entitlement by virtue of subrogation that will entitle the formerContracting Party, or its designated agency, to assert any such right or claimto the same extent as its predecessor. The Contracting Party that recognizesthe subrogation of the other Contracting Party or its designated agency shallpermit the correspondent transfers to the latter.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Settlement of disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>1. Anydispute between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation orapplication of this Agreement shall, to the extent possible, be settled throughdiplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2. If thedispute cannot thus be settled within a period of three months from thecommencement of consultations, it shall be submitted, upon written request ofeither Contracting Party, to an arbitration tribunal.</p>
        <p>3 Thearbitration tribunal shall be constituted in the following way: eachContracting Party shall appoint one member of the tribunal, and those twomembers shall then select anational of a third State as chairman of the tribunal. The members shall beappointed within two months, and the chairman within a month, from the date the lastmember was appointed.</p>
        <p>4. If oneof the Contracting Parties fails to appoint its member of the tribunal withinthe period specified in paragraph 3, the other Contacting Party may invite the Chairmanof the court of arbitration of the International Chamber of Commerce (the ICC)to make the necessary appointments, according to the rules of the ICC then in effect.</p>
        <p>5. In casethat the appointed members of both Contracting Parties could not reach anagreement upon the appointment of the chairman of the tribunal, within the periodof time established on paragraph 3 of this article, any Contracting Party couldrequest to follow the procedure established on paragraph 4.</p>
        <p>6. Theproceedings of the arbitration tribunal shall be conducted in accordance withthe Rules of Conciliation and Arbitration of the ICC. The Contracting Partiesshall establish the venue in which the arbitral procedure will take place. Incase that the tribunal cannot reach agreement, within 7 days, on the venuewhere the arbitral procedureshould take place, either Contracting Party can invite the Secretary General ofthe ICC to make, within 7 days, a selection of the venue for the procedure. Incase that theSecretary General of the ICC cannot make a decision, the City of London,capital city of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, willbe immediatelyestablished as the place for the procedure.</p>
        <p>7. Thearbitration tribunal shall reach its award by a majority of votes. Such awardshall be final and binding for both Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>8. EachContracting Party shall bear the cost of its own member of the tribunal and ofits representation in the arbitration proceeding. The cost of the chairman andthe remainingcosts shall be borne in equal parts by both Contracting Parties. The arbitrationtribunal may in its decision direct that a higher proportion of costs shall be borne byone of the two Contracting Parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of investment disputes between one contracting party and investors of the other contracting party">
        <p>1. For thesettlement of any investment dispute which may arise between one ContractingParty and an investor of the other Contracting Party with respect to mattersregulated by this Agreement, an amicable settlement shall be conducted betweensuch parties to the dispute.</p>
        <p>2. If adispute cannot be settled in compliance with paragraph 1 of this article, within3 months from the date the above amicable settlement is initiated, it shall besubmitted to arbitration, upon written request of either party to the dispute,in accordance with the Rules of Conciliation and Arbitration of the InternationalChamber of Commerce then ineffect.</p>
        <p>3. Theprocedures established in paragraphs 3 to 8 of article 7 hereof shall beapplicable to the arbitration conducted under this article.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Entry into force, duration, amendment and termination">
        <p>1. ThisAgreement shall enter into force one month after the date when both ContractingParties have notified each other, through the diplomatic channels, of thecompletion of their applicable legal formalities required for the entry intoforce of international agreements.</p>
        <p>2. ThisAgreement shall remain in force for an initial period of ten years, and shallcontinue thereafter unless one of the Contracting Parties notifies the otherContracting Party, with a written notification one year in advance, of its intentionto terminate it. In such case, the termination shall become effective one yearafter the notification has been received by the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>3. Inrespect of investments made prior to the termination of this Agreement, theprovisions contained in this Agreement shall remain in force for an additionalperiod of ten yearsfrom the date of termination.</p>
        <p>4. TheContracting Parties shall periodically consult with each other, to improve themeasures, application and interpretation of this Agreement, and to make any amendmentby exchange of letters</p>
        <p>5. ThisAgreement shall remain in force, independent of the diplomatic and consularrelations between the Contacting Parties</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, duly authorized, have signed this Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done intriplicate at Guatemala City the twelve day of November, 1999 in the Spanish,Chinese and English languages, all three texts being equally authoritative. Incase of anydivergence of interpretation, the English text shall prevail.</p>
      <p>For theGovernment of the Republic of China</p>
      <p>Andrew J.S.Wu</p>
      <p>AmbassadorExtraordinary and Plenipotentiary</p>
      <p>For theGovernment of the Republic of Guatemala</p>
      <p>Jos&#xE9; Guillermo Castillo V.</p>
      <p>Interim Minister of Economy</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
