<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Slovakia - United Kingdom BIT (1990)</name>
    <code>T1990-47</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">GBR</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">SVK</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1990-07-10</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1992-10-26</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en, cs</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>2925</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{GBR,SVK}_1990-07-10.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en, cs</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T1994-84">The Energy Charter Treaty (1994)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN ANDNORTHERN IRELAND AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE CZECH AND SLOVAK FEDERAL REPUBLIC FORTHE PROMOTION AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Czech and Slovak Federal Republic and the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland</p>
      <p>Desiring to create favorable conditions for the development of investments by investors of one State in the territory of another State;</p>
      <p>Recognizing that the promotion and reciprocal protection of such investments provided by the international agreement will contribute to stimulate entrepreneurial initiative and encourage the development of economic relations between the two countries;</p>
      <p>Acting in the spirit of the principles of the Final Act of the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe, signed in Helsinki on 1 August 1975;</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>Definitions For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>a)  "investment" means every kind of asset belonging to an investor of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party under the law in force of the latter Contracting Party in any sector of economic activity and in particular, though not exclusively, includes:</p>
        <p>(I)  movable and immovable property and any other related property rights, including mortgages, liens or pledges;</p>
        <p>(ii) shares in and stock and debenturesof a company and any other form of participation in a company;</p>
        <p> (iii) claims to money or to any performanceunder contract having a financial value;</p>
        <p>(iv) intellectual property rights,goodwill, know-how and technical processes;</p>
        <p>(v) business concessions conferred by lawor, where appropriate under the law of the Contracting Party concerned, undercontract, including concessions to search for, cultivate, extract or exploitnatural resources.</p>
        <p>A change in the form in which assets areinvested does not affect their character as investments within the meaning ofthis Agreement. The term "investment" includes all investments,whether made before or after the date of entry into force of this Agreement;</p>
        <p>(b) the term" returns" meansthe amounts yielded by an investment and in particular, though not exclusively,includes profit, interest, capital gains, dividends, royalties and thetern" investors" means:</p>
        <p>c)  the term "investor" means:</p>
        <p>(I)  as regards the Czech and Slovak Federal Republic:</p>
        <p>(aa) alllegal entities established under Czechoslovak law; </p>
        <p>(bb) allnatural persons who, according to Czechoslovak law, are Czechoslovak citizensand have the right to act as investors;</p>
        <p>(ii)  as regards the United Kingdom:</p>
        <p>(aa)physical persons deriving their status as United Kingdom nationals from the lawin force in the United Kingdom;</p>
        <p>(bb)corporations, firms and associations incorporated or constituted under the lawin force in any part of the United Kingdom or in any territory to which thisAgreement is extended in accordance with the provisions of Article 12;</p>
        <p>d)  the term "territory" means:</p>
        <p>(i) inrespect of the Czech and Slovak Federal Republic: the territory of the Czechand Slovak Federal Republic;</p>
        <p>(ii) inrespect of the United Kingdom: Great Britain and Northern Ireland, including theterritorial sea and any maritime area situated beyond the territorial sea ofthe United Kingdom which has been or might in the future be designated underthe national law of the United Kingdom in accordance with international law asan area within which the United Kingdom may exercise rights with regard to the seabedand subsoil and the natural resources and any territory to which this Agreementis extended in accordance with the provisions of Article 12.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and protection of investment">
        <p>(1) EachContracting Party shall encourage and create favourable conditions for investorsof the other Contracting Party to invest capital in its territory, and, subjectto its right to exercise powers conferred by its laws, shall admit such capital.</p>
        <p>(2)Investments of investors of each Contracting Party shall at all times beaccorded fair and equitable treatment and shall enjoy full protection andsecurity in the territory of the other Contracting Party. Neither ContractingParty shall in any way impair by unreasonable or discriminatory measures themanagement, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal of investments in itsterritory of investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(3)Investors of one Contracting Party may conclude with the other ContractingParty specific agreements, the provisions and effect of which, unless morebeneficial to the investor, shall not be at variance with this Agreement. EachContracting Party shall, with regard to investments of investors of the otherContracting Party, observe the provisions of these specific agreements, as wellas the provisions of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="National treatment and most favoured nation provisions">
        <p>(1) Each ContractingParty shall ensure that under its law investments or returns of investors ofthe other Contracting Party are granted treatment not less favourable than thatwhich it accords to investments or returns of its own investors or toinvestments or returns of investors of any third State.</p>
        <p>(2) EachContracting Party shall ensure that under its law investors of the other ContractingParty, as regards their management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal oftheir investments, are granted treatment not less favourable than that which itaccords to its own investors or to investors of any third State.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Compensation for losses">
        <p>Investorsof one Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of the other ContractingParty suffer losses owing to any armed conflict, a state of national emergency,or civil disturbances in the territory of the latter Contracting Party shall beaccorded by the latter Contracting Party treatment, as regards restitution,indemnification, compensation or other settlement, no less favourable than thatwhich the latter Contracting Party accords to its own investors or to investorsof any third State. Resulting payments shall be freely transferable.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Expropriation">
        <p>(1)Investments of investors of either Contracting Party shall not be nationalised,expropriated or subjected to measures having effect equivalent tonationalisation or expropriation (hereinafter referred to as"expropriation") in the territory of the other Contracting Partyexcept for a public purpose related to the internal needs of that Party on anon-discriminatory basis and against prompt, adequate and effectivecompensation.</p>
        <p>Suchcompensation shall amount to the genuine value of the investment expropriated immediatelybefore the expropriation or before the impending expropriation became publicknowledge, 'whichever is the earlier, shall include interest at a normal commercialrate until the date of payment, shall be made without delay, be effectivelyrealisable and be freely transferable. The investor affected shall have aright, under the law of the Contracting Party making the expropriation, toprompt review, by a judicial or other independent authority of that Party, ofhis or its case and of the valuation of his or its investment in accordancewith the principles set out in this paragraph.</p>
        <p>(2) Theprovisions of paragraph (1) shall also apply where a Contracting Party expropriatesthe assets of a company which is incorporated or constituted under the law in forcein any part of its own territory, and in which investors of the otherContracting Party own shares.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Repatriation of investment and returns">
        <p>EachContracting Party shall in respect of investments guarantee to investors of theother Contracting Party the unrestricted transfer of their investments andreturns. Transfers shall be effected without delay in the convertible currencyin which the capital was originally invested or in any other convertiblecurrency agreed by the investor and the Contracting Party concerned. Unlessotherwise agreed by the investor transfers shall be made at the rate ofexchange applicable on the date of transfer pursuant to the exchange regulationsin force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Exceptions">
        <p>Theprovisions of this Agreement relative to the grant of treatment not lessfavourable than that accorded to the investors of either Contracting Party orof any third State shall not be construed so as to oblige one Contracting Partyto extend to the investors of the other the benefit of any treatment,preference or privilege resulting from:</p>
        <p>(a) anyexisiting or future customs or economic union or similar internationalagreement to which either of the Contracting Parties is or may become a Party,or</p>
        <p>(b) any international agreement or arrangement, or any domestic legislation,relating wholly or mainly to taxation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of disputes between an investor and a host state">
        <p>(1)Disputes between an investor of one Contracting Party and the other ContractingParty concerning an obligation of the latter under Articles 2(3), 4, 5 and 6 ofthis Agreement in relation to an investment of the former which have not beenamicably settled shall, after a period of four months from written notificationof a claim, be submitted to arbitration under paragraph (2) below if eitherparty to the dispute so wishes.</p>
        <p>(2) Wherethe dispute is referred to arbitration, the investor concerned in the disputeshall have the right to refer the dispute either to:</p>
        <p>(a) anarbitrator or ad hoc arbitral tribunal to be appointed by a special agreementor established and conducted under the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commissionon International Trade Law; the parties to the dispute may agree in writing tomodify these Rules, or</p>
        <p>(b) theInstitute of Arbitration of the Chamber of Commerce of Stockholm, or</p>
        <p>(c) theCourt of Arbitration of the Federal Chamber of Commerce and Industry in Vienna.</p>
        <p>(3) Thearbitrator or arbitral tribunal to which the dispute is referred underparagraph (2) shall, in particular, base its decision on the provisions of thisAgreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>(1)Disputes between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or applicationof this Agreement should, if possible, be settled amicably.</p>
        <p>(2) If adispute between the Contracting Parties cannot thus be settled, it shall uponthe request of either Contracting Party be submitted to an arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>(3) Such anarbitral tribunal shall be constituted for each individual case in the followingway. Within two months of the receipt of the request for arbitration, eachContracting Party shall appoint one member of the tribunal. Those two membersshall then select a national of a third State who on approval by the twoContracting Parties shall be appointed Chairman of the tribunal. The Chairmanshall be appointed within two months from the date of appointment of the othertwo members.</p>
        <p>(4) Ifwithin the periods specified in paragraph (3) of this Article the necessary appointmentshave not been made, either Contracting Party may, in the absence of any otheragreement, invite the President of the International Court of Justice to makeany necessary appointments. If the President is a national of eitherContracting Party or if he is otherwise prevented from discharging the saidfunction, the Vice-President shall be invited to make the necessaryappointments. If the Vice-President is a national of either Contracting Partyor if he too is prevented from discharging the said function, the Member of theInternational Court of Justice next in seniority who is not a national ofeither Contracting Party shall be invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>(5) Thetribunal shall determine its own procedure. The arbitral tribunal shal1 reachits decision by a majority of votes. Such decision shall be binding on bothContracting Parties.</p>
        <p>(6) EachContracting Party shall bear the cost of its own member of the tribunal and of itsrepresentation in the arbitral proceedings; the cost of the Chairman and theremaining costs shall be borne in equal parts by the Contracting Parties. Thetribunal may, however, in its decision direct that a higher proportion of costsshall be borne by one of the two Contracting Parties, and this award shall bebinding on both Contracting Parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Subrogation">
        <p>(1) If oneContracting Party or its designated Agency (" the first ContractingParty") makes a payment under an indemnity given in respect of aninvestment in the territory of the other Contracting Party ("the secondContracting Party"), the second Contracting Party shall recognise: </p>
        <p>(a) theassignment to the first Contracting Party by law or by legal transaction of allthe rights and claims of the party indemnified, and</p>
        <p>(b) thatthe first Contracting Party is entitled to exercise such rights and enforcesuch claims by virtue of subrogation, to the same extent as the partyindemnified.</p>
        <p>(2) Thefirst Contracting Party shall be entitled in all circumstances to:</p>
        <p>(a) thesame treatment in respect of the rights and claims acquired by it by virtue ofthe assignment, and</p>
        <p>(b) anypayments received in pursuance of those rights and claims, as the partyindemnified was entitled to receive by virtue of this Agreement in respect of theinvestment concerned and its related returns.</p>
        <p>(3) Anypayments received in non-convertible currency by the first Contracting Party inpursuance of the rights and claims acquired shall be freely available to thefirst Contracting Party for the purpose of meeting any expenditure incurred inthe territory of the second Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Application of other rules">
        <p>If theprovision of law of either Contracting Party or obligations under internationallaw existing at present or established hereafter between the ContractingParties in addition to the present Agreement contain rules, whether general orspecific, entitling investments by investors of the other Contracting Party toa treatment more favourable than is provided for by the present Agreement, suchrules shall to the extent that they are more favourable prevail over thepresent Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Territorial extension">
        <p>At the time of entry into force of this Agreement, or at any time thereafter, the provisions of this Agreement may be extended to such territories for whose international relations the Government of the United Kingdom are responsible as may be agreed between the Contracting Parties in an Exchange of Notes.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Entry into force">
        <p>EachContracting Party shall notify the other in writing of the completion of the constitutionalformalities required in its territory for the entry into force of thisAgreement.</p>
        <p>This Agreement shall enter into force on the date of the later of the two notifications.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="14" title="Duration and determination">
        <p>This Agreement shall remain in force for a period of ten years. Thereafter it shall continue in force until the expiration of twelve months from the date on which either Contracting Party shall have given written notice of termination to the other. Provided that in respect of investments made whilst the Agreement is in force, its provisions shall continue in effect with respect to such investments for a period of fifteen years after the date of termination and without prejudice to the application thereafter of the rules of general international law.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, duly authorised by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</p>
      <p>DONE at Prague, this Tenth day of July 1990 in duplicate, in the English and Czech and languages, both texts being equally authoritative.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland:</p>
      <p>Nicholas Ridley</p>
      <p>State Secretary for Trade and Industry of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Czech and Slovak Federal Republic:</p>
      <p>Vaclav Klaus</p>
      <p>Finance Minister of Czechoslovakia</p>
    </conclusion>
    <attachments>
      <p>
        <b>PROTOCOL RELATINGTO THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN ANDNORTHERN IRELAND AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE CZECH AND SLOVAK FEDERAL REPUBLIC FORTHE PROMOTION AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS </b>
      </p>
      <p>On thesignature of the Agreement between the Government of the United Kingdom of GreatBritain and Northern Ireland and the Government of the Czech and Slovak FederalRepublic for the Promotion and Protection of Investments the signatories belowbeing duly authorised thereto by their respective Governments, have agreed asfollows:</p>
      <p>"Theprovisions of Article 6 of the Agreement shall be applied, in respect of theCzech and Slovak Federal Republic, so that unrestricted transfer of paymentsrelating to returns and loan repayments, shall only be permitted in anyone yearup to a maximum of 20% of the value of the investment of the investor of theUnited Kingdom, that value being the value of the investment at the date of theadmission of the investment to the Czech and Slovak Federal Republic.</p>
      <p>Alltransfers effected from the convertible currency account of a company in whichan investor owns shares are excluded from the above mentionedrestriction."</p>
      <p>ThisProtocol shall form an integral part of the above mentioned Agreement. Unless theContracting Parties agree in writing on an earlier term, the validity of thisProtocol will be terminated on 31 December 1994.</p>
      <p>Done atPrague this Tenth day of July in duplicate in the English and the Czech languages,both texts being equally authoritative.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland:</p>
      <p>Nicholas Ridley</p>
      <p>State Secretary for Trade and Industry of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Czech and Slovak Federal Republic:</p>
      <p>Vaclav Klaus</p>
      <p>Finance Minister of Czechoslovakia</p>
    </attachments>
  </main>
</treaty>
