<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Switzerland - Viet Nam BIT (1992)</name>
    <code>T1992-30</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">CHE</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">VNM</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1992-07-03</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1992-12-03</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">fr</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>3007</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>fr</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{CHE,VNM}_1992-07-03.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Agreement between the Swiss Confederation and the Socialist Republic of Vietnam on the Promotion and Reciprocal Protection of Investments</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Swiss Federal Council</p>
      <p>and</p>
      <p>the Government of the Socialist Republic of Vietnam,</p>
      <p>Desiring to intensify economic cooperation in the mutual interest of both States,</p>
      <p>Intending to create and maintain favourable conditions for investments by investors of one contracting party in the territory of the other contracting party,</p>
      <p>Recognizing the need to encourage and protect foreign investment in order to promote the economic prosperity of both States,</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>(1) The term means investor in respect of either Contracting Party,</p>
        <p>(a) Natural persons who, according to the law of that Contracting Party, are considered to be its nationals;</p>
        <p>(b) Legal entities, including companies registered partnerships, corporations or other organizations, which are constituted or otherwise organised under the law of that Contracting Party and having their seat together with real economic activities, in the territory of that same Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>(c) Legal entities established in accordance with the law of any country, which are directly or indirectly controlled by nationals of that Contracting Party or by legal entities having their seat together with real economic activities, in the territory of that Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(2) The term "investment" includes all categories of assets and in particular:</p>
        <p>(a) Ownership of movable and immovable property as well as any other rights in rem servitudes, charges, such as movable and immovable property, pledges;</p>
        <p>(b) The actions, and other forms of participation shares in companies;</p>
        <p>(c) Monetary claims and rights to any performance having an economic value;</p>
        <p>(d) Copyrights, industrial property rights, such as patents, utility models, industrial designs or models, trade marks, trademarks, trade names, indication of origin), know-how and goodwill;</p>
        <p>(e) The concessions, including extract concessions to search for or exploit natural resources, as well as any other rights conferred by law, by contract or by decision of the Authority in accordance with the law.</p>
        <p>(3) The term territory means the territory and airspace of Switzerland and Vietnam and the islands and maritime areas, over which the State concerned exercises its sovereign rights or jurisdiction in accordance with international law.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Admission and Protection">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party shall promote as far as possible investments by investors of the other contracting party in its territory and admit such investments in accordance with its laws and regulations.</p>
        <p>(2) Once it has admitted an investment in its territory, each Contracting Party shall issue the required authorisations in connection with such investments and with the carrying out of licensing agreements, technical, commercial or administrative assistance. each contracting is gambling, whenever necessary, will grant the necessary authorizations concerning the activities of consultants and other qualified persons of foreign nationality.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Protection , Treatment">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party shall protect within its territory investments made in accordance with its laws and regulations by investors of the other Contracting Party and shall ensure fair and equitable treatment to such investments.</p>
        <p>(2) Any Contracting Party may submit in its territory not investments by investors of the other Contracting Party to treatment less favourable than that which it accords to investments of investors of any third State. the joint ventures involving investors of the two Contracting Parties shall enjoy conditions no less favourable than the joint ventures involving of investors of any third State.</p>
        <p>(3) The most-favoured-nation treatment shall not apply to privileges which either Contracting Party accords to investors of a third State by virtue of its association or participation in a free trade area, customs union or common market.</p>
        <p>(4) Without prejudice to its Law on Foreign Investment in force when the investment was made and investment conditions resulting therefrom, each Contracting Party shall refrain from taking discriminatory measures with respect to the investments of investors of the other Contracting Party and joint ventures involving investors of the two contracting parties. such measures shall include in particular undue restrictions or limitations on access to the means of production or the purchase, transport, marketing and sale of goods and services.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Free Transfer">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party in whose territory of investors of the other Contracting Party has made investments, to grant those investors the free transfer of payments related to these investments, including:</p>
        <p>(a) Profits, dividends, interests and other current income;</p>
        <p>(b) Such as loans;</p>
        <p>(c) The amounts to be used to cover expenses relating to the management of the investment;</p>
        <p>(d) Royalties and other payments deriving from rights enumerated in article 1 (2), letter (c), (d) and (e) of this Agreement;</p>
        <p>(e) Additional contributions of capital necessary for the maintenance or development of the investments;</p>
        <p>(f) The earnings of natural persons;</p>
        <p>(g) The proceeds of the sale of or the partial or total liquidation of an investment including capital gains.</p>
        <p>(2) Unless the investor and the Contracting Party concerned, decide otherwise transfers shall be made at the rate of exchange applicable on the date of transfer in accordance with the legislation in force in the currency of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investment has been made.</p>
        <p>(3) The provisions of this article shall not preclude the Contracting Parties shall apply their respective legislations on tax matters.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Dispossession , Compensation">
        <p>(1) Neither Contracting Party shall take, directly or indirectly, measures of expropriation, nationalization or any other measures having the same nature or the same effect against investments of investors of the other contracting party except for reasons of public interest and provided that such measures are not discriminatory, that they comply with the legal requirements and provide for payment of adequate and effective compensation. the amount of compensation shall include interest, shall be paid in the currency of the country of origin of the investment and shall be paid without delay to the person entitled thereto without regard to its residence or its headquarters.</p>
        <p>(2) Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments have suffered losses due to a war or any other armed conflict, revolution, rebellion or state of emergency, which took place in the territory of the other contracting party benefit, on the part of this latter, from a treatment in accordance with Article 3, paragraph (2) of this Agreement. in any event, they shall be compensated.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Investments Made Prior to the Agreement">
        <p>This Agreement shall also apply to investments in the territory of a Contracting Party in accordance with its laws and regulations by investors of the other contracting party prior to the entry into force of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="More Favourable Terms">
        <p>Notwithstanding the conditions laid down in this Agreement, the more favourable conditions which have been or will be agreed by one of the Contracting Parties with investors of the other Contracting Party shall apply.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Subrogation">
        <p>Where a Contracting Party has provided any financial guarantee against non-commercial risks with regard to an investment by one of its investors in the territory of the other contracting party, the latter shall recognize the rights of the first Contracting Party on the basis of the principle of subrogation to the rights of the investor if payment has been made under this first guaranteed by the contracting party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Disputes between a Contracting Party and an Investor of the other Contracting Party">
        <p>(1) Any investment dispute between a Contracting Party and an investor of the other Contracting Party shall to the extent possible and without prejudice to the provisions of article 10 of this Agreement (disputes between contracting parties), resolved amicably between the parties to the dispute. to this end, consultations will take place between the parties concerned.</p>
        <p>(2) If these consultations do not solution within six months from the date on which the dispute has been raised, the dispute shall, at the request of the investor, be submitted:</p>
        <p>(a) Either to an arbitration body of the economy of the host country;</p>
        <p>(b) Or to an ad hoc tribunal. such an arbitral tribunal shall be constituted ad hoc as follows:</p>
        <p>(i) The arbitral tribunal shall be constituted for each individual case. unless the parties to the dispute decide otherwise, each party shall appoint one arbitrator and these two arbitrators shall nominate a Chairman who shall be a national of a third State. the arbitrators shall be appointed within two months from the receipt of the request to submit the diff&#xE9;-rend to arbitration and the Chairman shall be appointed within two months.</p>
        <p>(ii) If the time limits referred to in subparagraph (i) of this article have not been observed, each Party to the dispute may, in the absence of any other agreement, invite the President of the International Court of Arbitration of the Stockholm Chamber of Commerce to make the necessary appointments. if the President is unable to perform this function or if he is a national of one of the Contracting Parties, the provisions of paragraph (5) of article 10 of this Agreement shall apply mutatis mutandis.</p>
        <p>(iii) Unless the Parties decide otherwise, the tribunal shall determine its procedure luim&#xEA;me while drawing on the arbitration rules of procedure of the United Nations Commission on United Nations Commission on International Trade Law (c.n.u.d.c.i.). the tribunal shall reach its decisions by a majority of votes. the decisions of the Tribunal are final and binding. each Contracting Party shall ensure the recognition and enforcement of the arbitral award.</p>
        <p>(iv) The Tribunal in its award determine the apportionment of the expenses of the arbitration between the parties. unless the tribunal decides otherwise each party to the dispute shall bear the costs of its own member of the Tribunal and of its representation in the arbitration proceedings; the cost of the Chairman and the remaining costs shall be borne in parts&#xE9;galespar lesdeuxpartiesau dispute.</p>
        <p>(3) If both parties are contracting parties to the Convention of 18 March 19651pour the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of Other States, the dispute shall, at the request of the investor, be submitted to the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes (c.i.r.d.i.) in lieu of the procedure provided for in paragraph (2) of this article.1pour the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of Other States, the dispute shall, at the request of the investor, be submitted to the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes (c.i.r.d.i.) in lieu of the procedure provided for in paragraph (2) of this article.</p>
        <p>(4) The Contracting State that is a party to the dispute may at any time during the procedure provided for in paragraphs (2) and (3) of this Article or in the enforcement of the award in question, enforce the fact that the investor has received pursuant to an insurance contract, compensation covering the whole or part of the damage.</p>
        <p>(5) Neither Contracting State shall pursue through diplomatic channels a dispute submitted to international arbitration unless the other Contracting State does not comply with the award rendered by an arbitral tribunal.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Disputes between Contracting Parties">
        <p>(1) Disputes between contracting parties regarding the interpretation or application of the provisions of this Agreement shall be settled through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>(2) If both contracting parties fail to reach a settlement within 12 months from the date on which the dispute has arisen, the latter shall be submitted, at the request of either contracting party to an arbitral tribunal composed of three members. each Contracting Party shall appoint an arbitrator. the two arbitrators so nominated shall appoint a chairman who shall be a national of a third State.</p>
        <p>(3) If one of the Contracting Parties has not appointed its arbitrator and has not followed the invitation of the other contracting party to make such appointment within two months of the arbitrator shall be appointed, upon request by the latter Contracting Party by the President of the International Court of Justice.</p>
        <p>(4) If the two arbitrators cannot reach an agreement about the choice of the Chairman within two months after their appointment the latter shall be appointed upon the request of either Contracting Party by the President of the International Court of Justice.</p>
        <p>(5) If in the cases specified under paragraphs (3) and (4) of this article, the President of the International Court of Justice is prevented from exercising his mandate or if he is a national of either Contracting Party, the appointment shall be made by the Vice-President and if the latter is prevented or if he is a national of either Contracting Party, they will be made by the most senior member of the Court who is not a national of either of the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>(6) Unless the Contracting Parties decide otherwise, the tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
        <p>(7) The decisions of the Tribunal are final and binding on the contracting parties.</p>
        <p>(8) Unless the tribunal decides otherwise, each Contracting Party shall bear the costs of its own member of the Tribunal and of its representation shall be borne in equal parts by both contracting parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Compliance">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall at all times compliance with the obligations assumed by it in respect of investments of investors of the other contracting party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Final Provisions">
        <p>(1) This Agreement shall enter into force on the day on which the two Governments have notified each other that the constitutional formalities required for the conclusion and entry into force of international agreements have been completed; it shall remain valid for a period of ten years. if it is not denounced in writing six months before the expiry of this period, there shall be considered on the same terms as renewed for a period of two years, and so on.</p>
        <p>(2) In the event of termination, the provisions of articles 1 to 11 of this Agreement shall apply for a period of ten years for investments made prior to the termination of the Agreement.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>Done at Bern, 3&nbsp; July 1992, in four originals, two in French and two in Vietnamese, each text being equally authentic.</p>
      <p/>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
