<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Bangladesh - Indonesia BIT (1998)</name>
    <code>T1998-19</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">BGD</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">IDN</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>1998-02-09</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1999-04-22</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>372</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{BGD,IDN}_1998-02-09.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T1981-11">OIC Investment Agreement (1981)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF INDONESIA AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF BANGLADESH CONCEERNING THE PROMOTION AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENT</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Republic of Indonesia and the government of the People's Republic of Bangladesh (hereinafter referred to as "Contracting Parties");</p>
      <p>Bearing in mind the friendly and cooperative relations existing between the two countries and their peoples;</p>
      <p>Intending to create favourable conditions for investments by investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party on the basis of sovereign equality and mutual benefit; and</p>
      <p>Recognizing that the Agreement on the Promotion and Protection of such Investments will be conducive to the stimulation of investment activities in both countries;</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="I" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purpose of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>1. The term "investment" shall mean any kind of asset invested by investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party, in conformity with the laws and regulations of the latter including:</p>
        <p>a. Movable and immovable property as well as other rights such as mortgages, privileges, and guarantees and any other similar rights;</p>
        <p>b. Rights derived from shares, bonds or any other form of interest in companies or joint venture in the territory of the other Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>c. Claims to money or to any performance having a financial value;</p>
        <p>d. Intellectual property rights, technical processes, goodwill, and know-how;</p>
        <p>e. Business concessions conferred by law or under contract related to investment including concessions to search for or exploit natural resources.</p>
        <p>2. The term "investor" means national of one Contracting Party who invests in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>The term "national" shall comprise with regard to either Contracting Party; (i) Natural person having the nationality of that Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>(ii) Legal person constituted under the law of that Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>3. The term "without delay" shall be deemed to be fulfilled if a transfer is made within such period as is normally required by international financial practices.</p>
        <p>4. "Territory" shall mean:</p>
        <p>a) In respect of the People's Republic of Bangladesh:</p>
        <p>The territory of the People's Republic of Bangladesh as defined in its constitution and its laws.</p>
        <p>b) In respect of the Republic of Indonesia:</p>
        <p>The territory of the Republic of Indonesia as defined in its laws.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="II" title="Promotion and protection of investment">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall encourage and create favourable conditions for investors of the other Contracting Party to invest in its territory, and shall admit such capital in accordance with its laws and regulations.</p>
        <p>2. Investments of investors of either Contracting Party shall at all times be accorded fair and equitable treatment and shall enjoy adequate protection and security in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="III" title="Most-favoured nation provisions">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall ensure fair and equitable treatment of the investments of investors of the other Contracting Party and shall not impair by unreasonable or discriminatory measures, the operation, management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal thereof by those investors. Each Contracting Party shall accord to such investment adequate physical security and protection.</p>
        <p>2. More particularly, each Contracting Party shall accord to such investment treatment which in any case shall not be less favourable than that accorded to investments of investors of any third state.</p>
        <p>3. If a Contracting Party has accorded special advantages to investors of any third state by virtue of agreements establishing customs unions, economic unions, monetary unions or similar institutions, or on the basis of interim agreements leading to such unions of institutions, that Contracting Party shall not be obliged to accord such advantages to investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="IV" title="Expropriation">
        <p>Neither Contracting Party shall take any measures of expropriation. nationalization or any other dispossession, having effect equivalent, to nationalization or expropriation against the investments of an investor of the other Contracting Party and any interest relating there to except under the following conditions:</p>
        <p>(a) The measures are taken for a lawful purpose or public purpose and under process of law;</p>
        <p>(b) The measures are non discriminatory;</p>
        <p>(c) The measures are accompanied by provisions for the payment of prompt, adequate and effective compensation. Such compensation shall amount to the fair market value prevailing immedidately before the measure of dispossession became public knowledge. Such market value shall be determined in accordance with internationally acknowledged practices and methods or, where such fair market value cannot be determined, it shall be such reasonable amount as may be mutually agreed between the Contracting Parties hereto, and it shall be freely transferable in freely usable currencies from the Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="V" title="Compensation for losses">
        <p>1. Investors of one Contracting Party, whose investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party suffer losses owing to war or other aimed conflict, revolution, a state of national emergency, revolt, insurrection or riot in the territory of the latter Contracting Party, shall be accorded by the latter Contracting Party treatment, as regards restitutions, indemnification, compensation or other settlement.</p>
        <p>2. The treatment shall not be less favourable than that which the latter Contracting Party accords to its own investors or investors of any third state, whichever is more favourable to the investors concerned.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="VI" title="Transfer">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall guarantee within the scope of its laws and regulations in respect to investments by investors of the other Contracting Party to grant to chose investors without delay, the transfer of:</p>
        <p>a. Profits, interests, dividends and other current income;</p>
        <p>b. Funds necessary: (i) For the acquisition of raw or auxiliary materials, semi fabricated or finished products, or</p>
        <p>(ii) To replace capital assets in order to safeguard the continuity of an investment;</p>
        <p>c. Additional funds necessary for the development of an investment;</p>
        <p>d. Funds in repayment of loans;</p>
        <p>e. Royalties or fees;</p>
        <p>f. Earnings of natural persons;</p>
        <p>g. The proceeds of sale or liquidation of the investment;</p>
        <p>h. Compensation for losses;</p>
        <p>i. Compensation for expropriation.</p>
        <p>2. Such transfer shall be made at the prevailing rate of exchange on the date of transfer with respect to current transaction in the currency to be transferred.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="VII" title="Subrogation">
        <p>If the investments of an investor of the one Contracting Party are insured against non-commercial risks under a system established by law, any subrogation of the insurer or re-insurer to the rights of the said investor pursuant to the terms of such insurance shall be recognized by the other Contracting Party, provided, however, that the insurer or the re-insurer shall not be entitled to exercise any rights other than the rights which the investor would have been entitled to exercise.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="VIII" title="Settlement of disputes between investor and the contracting party">
        <p>1. Any dispute between a Contracting Party and an investor of the other Contracting Party, concerning an investment of the latter in the territory of the former, be settled amicably through consultations and negotiations.</p>
        <p>2. If such a dispute cannot be settled within a period of six months from the date of a written notification either party requesting amicable settlement, the dispute shall, at the request of the investor concerned, be submitted either to the competent court of the Contracting Party accepting the investment or to international arbitration of conciliation.</p>
        <p>3. Each Contracting Party hereby consents to submit any dispute arising between that Contracting Party and an investor of the other Contracting Party concerning an investment of that investor in the territory of the former Contracting Party to the International Center for Settlement of Investment Disputes for settlement by conciliation or arbitration under the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of other States opened for signature at Washington, D.C. on 18 March 1965.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="IX" title="Settlement of disputes between the contracting parties concerning interpretation and application of the agreement">
        <p>Disputes between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or application of this Agreement should, if possible, be settled through diplomatic channels.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="X" title="Applicability of this agreement">
        <p>This Agreement shall apply to investments by investors of the People's Republic of Bangladesh is the territory of the Republic of Indonesia which have been previously granted admission in accordance with the Law No. 1 of 1967 on Foreign Investment and any law amending or replacing it, and to investments by investors of the Republic of Indonesia in the territory of the People's Republic of Bangladesh which have been granted admission in accordance with the Foreign Private Investment (Promotion and Protection) Act, 1980.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XI" title="Application of other provisions">
        <p>If the provisions of law of either Contracting Party or obligations under international law existing at present or established hereafter between the Contracting Parties in addition to the present Agreement contain a regulation, whether general or specific, entitling investments by investors of the other Contracting Party to a treatment more favourable than is provided for by the present Agreement, such regulation shall to the extent that it is more favourable prevail over the present Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XII" title="Consultation and amendment">
        <p>1. Either Contracting Party may request that consultations be held on any matter concerning this Agreement. The other party shall accord sympathetic consideration to the proposal and shall afford adequate opportunity for such consultations.</p>
        <p>2. This Agreement may be amended at any time, if deemed necessary, by mutual consent.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="XIII" title="Entry into force, duration and termination">
        <p>1. The present Agreement shall enter into force three months after the date of the latest notification by any Contracting Party of the accomplishment of its internal procedures of ratification. It shall remain in force for a period of ten years and shall continue in force thereafter for another period of ten years and so forth unless denounced in writing by either Contracting Party one year before its expiration.</p>
        <p>2. In respect of investments made prior to the date of termination of this Agreement becomes effective, the provisions of Article I to XII shall remain in force for a further period of ten years from the date of termination of the present Agreement.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done in duplicate on 9th February, 1998 at Dhaka in Bangladesh in English Language.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of Indonesia</p>
      <p>Ali Alatas</p>
      <p>Minister of Foreign Affairs</p>
      <p>For the Government of the People's Republic of Bangladesh</p>
      <p>Abdus Samad Azad</p>
      <p>Minister of Foreign Affairs</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
