<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Costa Rica - Finland BIT (2001)</name>
    <code>T2001-84</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">CRI</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">FIN</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2001-11-28</date_signed>
    <date_into_force/>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">es</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>1045</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>https://www.finlex.fi/fi/esitykset/he/2002/20020027.pdf; unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>es</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{CRI,FIN}_2001-11-28.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T2012-8">Central America - EU Association Agreement (2012)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Agreement between the Government of the Republic of Costa Rica and the Government of the Republic of Finland on the Promotion and Protection of Investments</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Republic of&nbsp;Finland and the Government of the Republic of Costa Rica, hereinafter referred to as&nbsp;the &#x201C;Contracting Parties&#x201D;,</p>
      <p>DESIRING to intensify economic cooperation to the mutual benefit of both&nbsp;countries and to maintain fair and equitable&nbsp;conditions for investments by investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the&nbsp;other Contracting Party,</p>
      <p>RECOGNISING that the promotion and&nbsp;protection of investments on the basis of&nbsp;this Agreement will stimulate business initiatives,</p>
      <p>HAVE AGREED AS FOLLOWS:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purpose of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>1. The term &#x201C;Investment&#x201D; means any kind&nbsp;of asset established or acquired by an investor of one Contracting Party in the territory&nbsp;of the other Contracting Party in accordance&nbsp;with the laws and regulations of the latter&nbsp;Contracting Party including, in particular,&nbsp;though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>(a) movable and immovable property and&nbsp;any property rights such as mortgages,&nbsp;liens, pledges, leases, usufruct and similar&nbsp;rights;</p>
        <p>(b) shares, stocks, debentures or any other&nbsp;form of participation in a company;</p>
        <p>(c) titles or claims to money or rights to&nbsp;any performance having an economic value,&nbsp;directly related to an investment;</p>
        <p>(d) intellectual property rights, such as&nbsp;patents, copyrights, technical processes,&nbsp;trade marks, industrial designs, business&nbsp;names, know how and goodwill, geographical indications and layout-designs;</p>
        <p>(e) concessions conferred by law, by administrative act or under a contract by a&nbsp;competent authority, including concessions&nbsp;to undertake any economic and commercial&nbsp;activity, including any rights to search for,&nbsp;develop, cultivate, extract or exploit natural&nbsp;resources.</p>
        <p>Any alteration of the form of an investment does not affect their character as investments.</p>
        <p>Returns shall be considered as a component of investment.</p>
        <p>2. The term &#x201C;Returns&#x201D; means the amounts&nbsp;yielded by investments and in particular,&nbsp;though not exclusively, shall include profits, dividends, interest, royalties, capital&nbsp;gains, other current income or any payments in kind related to an investment.</p>
        <p>3. The term &#x201C;Investor&#x201D; means for either&nbsp;Contracting Party, the following subjects&nbsp;who invest in the territory of the other Contracting Party in accordance with the laws&nbsp;of the latter and the provisions of this&nbsp;Agreement:</p>
        <p>(a) any natural person who is a national of&nbsp;either Contracting Party in accordance with&nbsp;its laws; or</p>
        <p>(b) any legal person such as a company,&nbsp;corporation, firm, business association, institution, or any other organisation duly incorporated or constituted in accordance&nbsp;with the laws and regulations of the Contracting Party and having its seat in the territory of that Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>4. The term "Territory" means the land&nbsp;territory, internal waters and territorial sea&nbsp;and the airspace above them and the maritime zones beyond the territorial sea, including the seabed and subsoil, over which&nbsp;the Contracting Party has sovereignty, exercises sovereign rights or exclusive jurisdiction in accordance with its national laws in&nbsp;force and international law for the purpose&nbsp;of exploration and exploitation of the natural resources of such areas.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and Protection of Investments">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall encourage&nbsp;and create favourable conditions in its territory to investments by investors of the other&nbsp;Contracting Party and shall admit such investments in accordance with its laws and&nbsp;regulations.</p>
        <p>2. Each Contracting Party shall in its territory at all times accord to investments of&nbsp;investors of the other Contracting Party fair&nbsp;and equitable treatment and full and constant legal protection and security.</p>
        <p>3. Neither Contracting Party shall in its&nbsp;territory impair by unreasonable or arbitrary&nbsp;measures the management, maintenance,&nbsp;use, enjoyment, acquisition or disposal of&nbsp;investments of investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>4. Neither Contracting Party shall in its&nbsp;territory impose unreasonable or discriminatory measures on investments by investors of the other Contracting Party concerning purchase of materials, means of production, operation, transport, marketing of its&nbsp;products or similar orders.</p>
        <p>5. Each Contracting Party shall, in accordance with its laws and regulations, give a&nbsp;sympathetic consideration to applications&nbsp;for necessary permits in connection with the&nbsp;investments in its territory. Such permits&nbsp;should also include authorisations for engaging top managerial and technical personnel of the investor&#x2019;s choice, regardless&nbsp;of their nationality.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Treatment of Investments">
        <p>1. Investments made by investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the&nbsp;other Contracting Party shall be accorded&nbsp;treatment which is not less favourable than&nbsp;the host Party accords to the investments&nbsp;made by its own investors or by investors&nbsp;&nbsp;which are granted the most favoured nation&nbsp;treatment, whichever is the more favourable&nbsp;to the investor.</p>
        <p>2. Investors of one Contracting Party shall&nbsp;be accorded by the other Contracting Party,&nbsp;as regards the management, maintenance,&nbsp;use, enjoyment or disposal of their investments, treatment which is not less favourable than the latter Contracting Party accords its own investors or investors which&nbsp;are granted the most favoured nation treatment, whichever is the more favourable to&nbsp;the investor.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Exceptions">
        <p>The provisions of this Agreement shall&nbsp;not be construed so as to oblige one Contracting Party to extend to the investors of&nbsp;the other Contracting Party the benefit of&nbsp;any treatment, preference or privilege by&nbsp;virtue of:</p>
        <p>a) any existing or future free trade area,&nbsp;customs union, common market or regional&nbsp;labour market agreement or any other similar institution of regional economic integration to which one of the Contracting Parties&nbsp;is or may become a party,</p>
        <p>b) any international agreement or arrangement relating wholly or mainly to&nbsp;taxation, or</p>
        <p>c) any multilateral convention or treaty&nbsp;relating wholly or mainly to investments.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Transparency">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall promptly&nbsp;publish, or otherwise make publicly available, its laws, regulations, procedures and&nbsp;administrative rulings and judicial decisions&nbsp;of general application as well as international agreements which may affect the operation of the Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Expropriation">
        <p>1. Investments by investors of a Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall not be expropriated, nationalised or subjected to any other measures, direct or indirect, having effect&nbsp;equivalent to expropriation or nationalisation (hereinafter referred to as &#x201C;expropriation&#x201D;) except for a public purpose, on a&nbsp;non-discriminatory basis, under due process&nbsp;of law and against prompt, adequate and effective compensation.</p>
        <p>2. The compensation shall amount to the&nbsp;fair market value of the expropriated investment, immediately before the action of&nbsp;expropriation was taken. The fair market&nbsp;value shall not reflect any change in value&nbsp;of the investment occurring because the expropriation had become publicly known&nbsp;earlier.</p>
        <p>3. Such fair market value shall be expressed in a freely convertible currency, on&nbsp;the basis of the market rate of exchange existing for that currency at the moment referred to in paragraph 2 of this Article.</p>
        <p>Compensation shall also include interest at&nbsp;a commercial deposit rate established on a&nbsp;market basis where the expropriation was&nbsp;made, which will be calculated from the&nbsp;date of dispossession of the expropriated&nbsp;property until the date of actual payment.</p>
        <p>4. The investor whose investments are&nbsp;expropriated, shall have the right to prompt&nbsp;review by a judicial or other competent authority of that Contracting Party of its case&nbsp;and of valuation of its investments in accordance with the principles set out in this&nbsp;Article.</p>
        <p>5. Nothing in this Article shall affect the&nbsp;right of a Contracting Party to negotiate&nbsp;with the other Contracting Party, or with&nbsp;any other third State, quantitative restrictions that are in line with applicable international trade agreements, nor the Contracting&nbsp;Party&#x2019;s right to allocate such quantitative&nbsp;restrictions using the mechanisms and the&nbsp;criteria the Contracting Party considers appropriate.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Compensation for Losses">
        <p>1. Investors of one Contracting Party&nbsp;whose investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party suffer losses owing to&nbsp;war or other armed conflict, a state of national emergency, revolt, insurrection or&nbsp;riot in the territory of the latter Contracting&nbsp;Party, shall be accorded by the latter Contracting Party treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or&nbsp;other settlement no less favourable than that&nbsp;which the latter Contracting Party accords&nbsp;to its own investors or to investors which&nbsp;are granted the most favoured nation treatment, whichever is the more favourable to&nbsp;the investor. Resulting payments, if any,&nbsp;shall be effectively realisable, freely convertible and immediately transferable.</p>
        <p>2. Without prejudice to paragraph (1) of&nbsp;this Article, an investor of one Contracting&nbsp;Party who, in any of the situations referred&nbsp;to in that paragraph, suffers a loss in the territory of the other Contracting Party resulting from:</p>
        <p>(a) requisitioning of its investment or a&nbsp;part thereof by the latter's forces or authorities, or</p>
        <p>(b) destruction of its investment or a part&nbsp;thereof by the latter's forces or authorities,&nbsp;which was not required by the necessity of&nbsp;the situation,</p>
        <p>shall be accorded prompt, adequate and&nbsp;effective restitution or compensation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Free Transfer">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall ensure to&nbsp;investors of the other Contracting Party the&nbsp;unrestricted transfer, into and out of its territory, of their investments and of payments&nbsp;related with such investments. Such transfers shall include in particular, though not&nbsp;exclusively:</p>
        <p>(a) the principal and additional amounts&nbsp;to maintain, develop or increase the investment;</p>
        <p>(b) returns;</p>
        <p>(c) proceeds obtained from the total or&nbsp;partial sale or disposal of an investment, including the sale of shares;</p>
        <p>(d) the amounts required for payment of&nbsp;expenses which arise from the operation of&nbsp;the investment, such as loans repayments,&nbsp;payment of royalties, management fees, licence fees or other similar expenses;</p>
        <p>(e) compensation payable pursuant to Articles 6 and 7;</p>
        <p>(f) payments arising out of the settlement&nbsp;of a dispute;</p>
        <p>(g) payments under a contract including a&nbsp;loan agreement;</p>
        <p>(h) earnings and other remuneration of&nbsp;personnel engaged from abroad working in&nbsp;connection with an investment.</p>
        <p>2. Transfers referred to in paragraph 1. of&nbsp;this Article shall be effected without any restriction or delay, in a freely convertible&nbsp;currency. Unless otherwise agreed by the&nbsp;investor, transfers shall be made at the prevailing market rate of exchange applicable&nbsp;on the date of transfer with respect to spot&nbsp;transactions in the currency to be transferred and shall be effectively realisable and&nbsp;immediately transferable. If a market rate is&nbsp;unavailable, the applicable rate of exchange&nbsp;shall correspond to the cross rate obtained&nbsp;form those rates which would be applied by&nbsp;the International Monetary Fund on the date&nbsp;of payment for conversions of the currencies concerned into Special Drawing&nbsp;Rights.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Subrogation">
        <p>If a Contracting Party or its designated&nbsp;agency makes a payment under an indemnity against non-commercial risks given in&nbsp;respect of an investment in the territory of&nbsp;the other Contracting Party, the latter Contracting Party shall recognise the assignment of any right or claim from the investor&nbsp;to the former Contracting Party, or its designated agency, as well as the entitlement&nbsp;by virtue of subrogation, to exercise the&nbsp;&nbsp;rights and enforce the claims of that investor. The subrogation rights or claims shall&nbsp;not exceed the original rights or claims of&nbsp;such investors.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Disputes between an Investor and a Contracting Party">
        <p>1. Any dispute between an investor of one&nbsp;Contracting Party and the other Contracting&nbsp;Party concerning an investment in the territory of the latter Contracting Party will be&nbsp;notified in writing by the investor to the&nbsp;host Contracting Party. Such notification&nbsp;shall include relevant information. To the&nbsp;extent possible the dispute shall be settled&nbsp;amicably between the parties to the dispute.</p>
        <p>2. If the dispute cannot thus be settled&nbsp;within three (3) months, following the date&nbsp;in which the notification referred to in paragraph 1 above was sent by the investor&nbsp;through certified mail or equivalent to the&nbsp;Contracting Party in whose territory the investment was made, the dispute may, at the&nbsp;choice of the investor, be submitted:</p>
        <p>(a) to the competent courts of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investment is made;</p>
        <p>(b) or to arbitration by the International&nbsp;Centre for the Settlement of Investment&nbsp;Disputes (I.C.S.I.D.), established by the&nbsp;Convention on the Settlement of Investment&nbsp;Disputes between States and Nationals of&nbsp;other States, opened for signature at Washington on 18 March 1965;</p>
        <p>(c) or to the Additional Facility Rules of&nbsp;ICSID, provided that only one of the Contracting Parties is a party to the ICSID Convention;</p>
        <p>(d) or to an ad hoc arbitration tribunal,&nbsp;which unless otherwise agreed upon by the&nbsp;parties to the dispute, is to be established&nbsp;under the Arbitration Rules of the United&nbsp;Nations Commission on International Trade&nbsp;Law (UNCITRAL).</p>
        <p>Both Contracting Parties give their irrevocable consent in respect of the fact that&nbsp;all disputes relating to investments are submitted to the above mentioned tribunal or alternative arbitration procedures.</p>
        <p>3. Once the investor has submitted the&nbsp;dispute either to a competent Tribunal of&nbsp;the disputing Contracting Party or to an arbitral procedure, the selection of one or the other shall be final.</p>
        <p>4. The arbitral award shall be based on:</p>
        <p>(a) the provisions of this Agreement;</p>
        <p>(b) the national laws of the Contracting&nbsp;Party where the investment is made;</p>
        <p>(c) the generally recognised principles of&nbsp;International Law.</p>
        <p>5. Neither of the Contracting Parties,&nbsp;which is a party to a dispute, can raise an&nbsp;objection, at any phase of the arbitration&nbsp;procedure or of the execution of an arbitration award, on account of the fact that the&nbsp;investor, which is the opposing party of the&nbsp;dispute, had received an indemnification&nbsp;covering a part or the whole of its losses by&nbsp;virtue of an insurance.</p>
        <p>6. The award shall be final and binding&nbsp;for the parties to the dispute and shall be&nbsp;executed according to national law.</p>
        <p>7. The Contracting Parties shall abstain&nbsp;from addressing through diplomatic channels any matter submitted either to the domestic tribunals or to arbitration tribunals&nbsp;according to the terms of this Article, except in the case that the disputing Party has&nbsp;not complied with the judicial or arbitral&nbsp;decision.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Disputes between the Contracting Parties">
        <p>1. Disputes between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation and application of this Agreement shall, as far as&nbsp;possible, be settled through diplomatic&nbsp;channels.</p>
        <p>2. If the dispute cannot thus be settled&nbsp;within six (6) months, following the date on&nbsp;which such negotiations were requested by&nbsp;either Contracting Party, it shall at the request of either Contracting Party be submitted to an Arbitral Tribunal.</p>
        <p>3. Such an Arbitral Tribunal shall be constituted for each individual case in the following way. Within two (2) months of the receipt&nbsp;of the request for arbitration, each&nbsp;Contracting Party shall appoint one member&nbsp;of the Tribunal. Those two members shall&nbsp;then select a national of a third State who on approval by the two Contracting Parties&nbsp;shall be appointed Chairman of the Tribunal. The Chairman shall be appointed&nbsp;within four (4) months from the date of appointment of the other two members.</p>
        <p>4. If within the periods specified in paragraph 3 of this Article the necessary appointments have not been made, either Contracting Party may, in the absence of any&nbsp;other agreement, invite the President of the&nbsp;International Court of Justice to make any&nbsp;necessary appointments. If the President is a national of either Contracting Party or is otherwise prevented from discharging the&nbsp;said function, the Member of the International Court of Justice next in seniority who is not a national of either Contracting Party&nbsp;or is not otherwise prevented from discharging the said function, shall be invited&nbsp;to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>5. The Arbitral Tribunal shall dictate its&nbsp;judgement on the basis of the provisions of&nbsp;this Agreement and on the basis of recognised principles of International Law.</p>
        <p>6. The Arbitral Tribunal shall reach its&nbsp;decision by a majority of votes. The decisions of the Tribunal shall be final and&nbsp;binding on both Contracting Parties. Each&nbsp;Contracting Party shall bear the costs of the&nbsp;member appointed by that Contracting Party and of its representation at the arbitral&nbsp;proceedings. Both Contracting Parties shall&nbsp;assume an equal share of the cost of the&nbsp;Chairman, as well as any other costs. The&nbsp;Tribunal may make a different decision regarding the sharing of the costs. In all other&nbsp;respects the Arbitral Tribunal shall determine its own rules of procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Entry and Sojourn of Personnel">
        <p>Subject to its applicable laws relating to the entry and sojourn of non-nationals, a&nbsp;&nbsp;Contracting Party shall permit natural persons of the other Contracting Party and&nbsp;other personnel and personnel employed in&nbsp;connection with the investment by an investor of the other Contracting Party to enter&nbsp;and remain in its territory for the purpose of&nbsp;engaging in activities connected with investments, as well as members of their&nbsp;families.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Application of other Rules">
        <p>If the provisions of law of either Contracting Party or obligations under international&nbsp;law existing at present or established hereafter between the Contracting Parties in addition to this Agreement contain a regulation, whether general or specific, entitling&nbsp;investments made by investors of the other&nbsp;Contracting Party to a treatment more favourable than is provided for by this&nbsp;Agreement, such provisions shall, to the extent that they are more favourable to the investor, prevail over this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="14" title="Consultations">
        <p>The Contracting Parties shall consult each&nbsp;other from time to time for reviewing the&nbsp;implementation of this Agreement and studying any issue that may arise from this&nbsp;Agreement. Such consultations shall be&nbsp;held between the competent authorities of&nbsp;both Contracting Parties at a place and at a&nbsp;time agreed upon through diplomatic channels.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="15" title="Application of Agreement">
        <p>This Agreement shall apply to all investments made by investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party, whether made before or after&nbsp;the entry into force of this Agreement, but&nbsp;shall not apply to any dispute concerning an&nbsp; investment which arose or any claim, which&nbsp;was settled before its entry into force</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="16" title="Entry Into Force , Duration and Termination">
        <p>1. The Contracting Parties shall notify&nbsp;each other when their constitutional requirements for the entry into force of this&nbsp;Agreement have been fulfilled. The Agreement shall enter into force on the thirtieth&nbsp;day following the date of receipt of the last&nbsp;notification.</p>
        <p>2. This Agreement shall remain in force&nbsp;for an initial period of ten (10) years and&nbsp;shall thereafter remain in force on the same&nbsp;terms until either Contracting Party notifies&nbsp;the other in writing of its intention to terminate the Agreement in twelve (12) months.</p>
        <p>3. In respect of investment made prior to&nbsp;the date of termination of this Agreement&nbsp;the provisions of Articles 1 through 15 shall&nbsp;remain in force for a further period of ten&nbsp;(10) years from the date of termination of&nbsp;this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned representatives, duly authorised&nbsp;thereto, have signed the present Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done in duplicate at San Jos&#xE9; on the 28th&nbsp;of November 2001 in the Finnish, Spanish&nbsp;and English languages, all texts being&nbsp;equally authoritative. In case of divergence,&nbsp;the English text shall prevail.</p>
      <p>For the Government of&nbsp;the Republic of Finland</p>
      <p>For the Government of&nbsp;the Republic of Costa Rica</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
