<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Guatemala - Italy BIT (2003)</name>
    <code>T2003-66</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">GTM</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">ITA</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2003-09-08</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2008-03-03</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>1827</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{GTM,ITA}_2003-09-08.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <relation type="IT_OVERLAP" document-code="T1985-29">EEC - Central America Cooperation Agreement (1985)</relation>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T2012-8">Central America - EU Association Agreement (2012)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF GUATEMALA AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE ITALIAN REPUBLIC FOR THE PROMOTION AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS&nbsp;</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Italian Republic and the Government of the Republic of Guatemala (hereafter referred to as the Contracting Parties),</p>
      <p>Desiring to establish favourable conditions for improved economic cooperation between the two Countries, and especially in relation to capital investment by investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party;</p>
      <p>And</p>
      <p>Acknowledging that offering encouragement and mutual protection to such investment, based on international Agreements, will contribute to stimulating business ventures, which foster the prosperity of both Contracting Parties,</p>
      <p>Hereby have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>1. The term "investment" shall be construed to mean any kind of property invested, before or after the entry into force of this Agreement, by a natural or legal person of a Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party, in conformity with the laws and regulations of that Party, irrespective of the legal form chosen, as well as of the legal framework.</p>
        <p>Without limiting the generality of the foregoing, the term "investment" comprises in particular, but not exclusively:</p>
        <p>a) Movable and immovable property and any ownership right in rem, including real guarantee rights on property of a Third Party, to the extent that it can be invested;</p>
        <p>b) Shares, debentures, equity holdings or any other instruments of credit, as well as Government and public securities in general;</p>
        <p>c) Credits for sums of money or any service right having an economic value connected with an investment, as well as reinvested incomes and capital gains;</p>
        <p>d) Copyright, commercial trade marks, patents, industrial designs and other intellectual and industrial property rights, Know-how, trade secrets, trade names and goodwill;</p>
        <p>e) Any economic rights accruing by law or by contract and any licence and franchise granted in accordance with the provisions in force on economic activities, including the right to prospect for, extract and exploit natural resources;</p>
        <p>f) Any increases in value of the original investment.</p>
        <p>Any modification in the form of the investment does not imply a change in the nature thereof.</p>
        <p>2. The term "investor" shall be construed to mean any natural or legal person of a Contracting Party investing in the territory of the other Contracting Party as well as the foreign subsidiaries, affiliates and branches controlled in anyway by the above natural and legal persons.</p>
        <p>3. The term "natural person", in reference to either Contracting Party, shall be construed to mean any natural person holding the nationality of that State in accordance with its laws.</p>
        <p>4. The term "legal person", in reference to either Contracting Party, shall be construed to mean any entity having its head office in the territory of one of the Contracting Parties and recognised by it, such as public institutions, corporations, partnerships, foundations and associations, regardless of whether their liability is limited or otherwise.</p>
        <p>5. The term "income" shall be construed to mean the money accruing to an investment, including in particular profits or interests, interest income, capital gains, dividends, royalties or payments for assistance, technical services and others as well as any considerations in kind such as, but not exclusively, raw materials, produce, products or live-stock.</p>
        <p>6. The term "territory" shall be construed to mean, in addition to the zones contained within the land boundaries, the "maritime zones". The latter also comprise the marine and submarine zones including inland waters over which the Contracting Parties exercise sovereignty, and sovereign or jurisdictional rights, under international law.</p>
        <p>7. "Nondiscriminatory treatment" means treatment that is at least as favourable as the better of national treatment or most-favoured-nation treatment.</p>
        <p>8. "Right of access" means the right to be admitted to carry out investment in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>9. The term "activities connected with an investment" shall include, "inter alia", the organization, control, operation, maintenance and disposal of companies, branches, agencies, offices, or other organizations for the conduct of business; the access to the financial markets, in particular the borrowing of funds, the purchase, sale and issue of shares and other securities and the purchase of foreign exchange for imports necessary for the conduct of business affairs; the marketing of goods and services; the procurement, sale and transport of raw and processed materials, energy, fuels and production means; the dissemination of commercial information.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and Protection of Investments">
        <p>1. Both Contracting Parties shall encourage investors of the other Contracting Party to invest in their territory.</p>
        <p>2. Investors of one of the Contracting Parties shall have the right of access to the investment activities, in the territory of the other Contracting Party, not less favourable than the one granted as per Article 3.1.</p>
        <p>3. Both Contracting Parties shall at all times ensure just and fair treatment of the investments of investors of the other Contracting Party. Both Contracting Parties shall ensure that the management, maintenance, use, transformation, enjoyment or assignment of the investments effected in their territory by investors of the other Contracting Party, as well as companies and enterprises in which these investments have been effected, shall in no way be subject to unjustified or discriminatory measures.</p>
        <p>4. Each Contracting Party shall provide, in its Territory a legal framework apt to guarantee to investors the continuity of legal treatment, including the compliance, in good faith, of all undertakings assumed with regard to each specific investor.</p>
        <p>5. Neither of the Contracting Parties will set any conditions for the creation, the expansion or the continuation of investments, which may imply the taking over or the imposing of any limitation to the sale of the production on domestic and international markets, or which specifies that goods must be procured locally, or similar conditions.</p>
        <p>6. Companies which are legally constituted under the applicable laws or regulations of one Contracting Party and which are owned or controlled by the other Contracting Party, shall be permitted to engage top managerial personnel of their choice, regardless of nationality.</p>
        <p>7. The Contracting Parties may stipulate with investors of the other Contracting Party, who carry out investment of national interest in the territory of the Contracting Parties, an investment agreement, which will govern the specific legal relationship related to said investment.</p>
        <p>8. The nationals of one Contracting Party who are authorised to work in the territory of the other Contracting Party in connection with investments subject to this Agreement, shall enjoy appropriate conditions under which to perform their professional activities in accordance with the legislation of the latter.</p>
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall, in accordance with its legislation and its international obligations relating to the entry and stay of foreigners, permit the nationals of the other Contracting Party working in connection with an investment under this Agreement, as well as members of their families, to enter into, remain and leave its territory.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="National Treatment and the Most Favoured Nation Clause">
        <p>1. Both Contracting Parties, within the bounds of their own territory, shall offer investments effected by, and the income accruing to, investors of the other Contracting Party no less favourable treatment than that accorded to investments effected by, and income accruing to, its own nationals or investors of Third States.</p>
        <p>The same treatment will be granted to the activities connected with an investment.</p>
        <p>2. In case, from the legislation of one of the Contracting Parties, or from the international obligations in force or that may come into force for the future for one of the Contracting Parties, should come out a legal framework according to which the investors of the other Contracting Party would be granted a more favourable treatment than the one foreseen in this Agreement, the treatment granted to the investors of such other Parties will apply also for the outstanding relationships.</p>
        <p>3. The provisions under point 1 and 2 of this Article do not refer to the advantages and privileges which one Contracting Party may grant to investors of Third States by virtue of their membership of a Customs or Economic Union, of a Common Market, of a Free Trade Area, of a regional or subregional Agreement, of an international multilateral economic Agreement or under Agreements signed in order to prevent double taxation or to facilitate cross border trade.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Compensation for Damage or Losses">
        <p>Where investments of investors of either Contracting Party suffer losses or damages owing to war, armed conflict, a state of national emergency, revolt, insurrection, riot or other similar events in the territory of the other Contracting Party, such investors shall be accorded by the latter Contracting Party adequate treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or other settlement, not less favourable than that which the latter Contracting Party accords to its own investors or to investors of any third State. Compensation payments shall be freely transferable without undue delay.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Nationalisation or Expropriation">
        <p>1. The investments and the goods related to the connected activities to which this Agreement relates shall not be subject to any measure which might limit the right of ownership, possession, control or enjoyment of the investments, permanently or temporarily, save where specifically provided by current, national or local, legislation or regulations and orders handed down by courts or Tribunals having jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>2. Investments and the activities connected with an investment of investors of one of the Contracting Parties shall not be, de jure or de facto, directly or indirectly, nationalized, expropriated, requisitioned or subjected to any measures having an equivalent effect, including measures affecting companies and their assets controlled by the investor in the territory of the other Contracting Party, except for public purpose or national interest and in exchange for immediate, full and effective compensation, and on condition that measures are taken on a non-discrimatory basis and in conformity with all legal provisions and procedures.</p>
        <p>3. The just compensation shall be established on the basis of real international markets values immediately prior to the moment in which the decision to nationalise or expropriate is announced or made public.</p>
        <p>In the absence of an understanding between the host Contracting Party and the investor during the nationalisation, or expropriation procedure, compensation shall be based on the same reference parameters, and exchange rates, taken into account in the documents for the constitution of the investment.</p>
        <p>The exchange rate applicable to any such compensation shall be that prevailing on the date immediately prior to the moment in which the nationalisation or expropriation has been announced or made public.</p>
        <p>4. Without restricting the scope of the above paragraph, in case that the object of nationalisation, expropriation, or similar, is a company with foreign capital, the evaluation of the share of the investor will be, in the currency of the investment not lower than the starting value, increased by capital increases and revaluation of capital, undistributed profits and reserve funds, and diminished by the value of capital reductions and losses.</p>
        <p>5. Compensation will be considered as actual if it will have been paid in the same currency in which the investment has been made by the foreign investor, in as much as such currency is &#x2014; or remains &#x2014; convertible, or, otherwise, in any other currency accepted by the investor. Compensation shall include interests calculated on a six months Euro Interbank Offered Rate (EURIBOR) basis from the date of nationalisation or expropriation to the date of payment.</p>
        <p>6. Compensation will be considered as timely if it takes place without undue delay. In any case, within two months.</p>
        <p>7. A national or company of either Party that asserts that all or part of its investment has been expropriated shall have a right to prompt review by the appropriate judicial or administrative authorities of the other Party to determine whether any such expropriation has occurred and, if so, whether such expropriation, and any compensation thereof, conforms to the principles of international law, and to decide all other matters relating thereto.</p>
        <p>8. In the absence of an agreement between the investor and the responsible authority, the amount of compensation will be established according to the procedures for disputes resolution as per Article 9 of this Agreement.</p>
        <p>Compensation will be freely transferable.</p>
        <p>9. The provisions of paragraph 2. of this Article shall also apply to profits accruing to an investment and, in the event of winding-up, the proceeds of liquidation.</p>
        <p>10. If, after the dispossession, the good concerned has not been utilized, wholly or partially, for that purpose, the owner or his assignees are entitled to recover the good at the market price.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Free Transfer of Capital, Profits and Income">
        <p>1. Each of the Contracting Parties shall guarantee that the investors of the other may transfer the following abroad, without undue delay, in any convertible currency:</p>
        <p>a) Capital and additional capital, including reinvested income, used to maintain and increase investment;</p>
        <p>b) The net income, dividends, royalties, payments for assistance and technical services, interests and other profits;</p>
        <p>c) Income deriving from the total or partial sale or the total or partial liquidation of an investment;</p>
        <p>d) Funds to repay loans connected to an investment and the payment of the related interests;</p>
        <p>e) Remuneration and allowances paid to nationals of the other Contracting Party for work and services performed in relation to an investment effected in the territory of the other Contracting Party, in the amount and manner prescribed by the national legislation and regulations in force.</p>
        <p>2. Without restricting the scope of Article 3 of this Agreement, the Contracting Parties undertake to apply to the transfers mentioned in paragraph 1 of this Article the same favourable treatment that is accorded to investments effected by investors of Third States, in case it is more favourable.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Subrogation">
        <p>In the event that one Contracting Party or an Institution thereof has provided a guarantee in respect of non-commercial risks for the investment effected by one of its investors in the territory of the other Contracting Party, and has effected payment to said investor on the basis of that guarantee, the other Contracting Party shall recognise the assignment of the rights of the investor to the first-named Contracting Party. In relation to the transfer of payments to the Contracting Party or its Institution by virtue of this assignment, the provisions of Article 4, 5 and 6 of this Agreement shall apply.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Transfer Procedures">
        <p>1. The transfers referred to in Article 4, 5, 6 and 7 shall be effected without undue delay and, at all events, after all fiscal obligations have been met, and shall be made in a convertible currency. All the transfers shall be made at the prevailing exchange rate applicable on the date on which the investor applies for the related transfer, with the exception of the provisions under point 3 of article 5 concerning the exchange rate applicable in case of nationalisation or expropriation.</p>
        <p>2. The fiscal obligations under the previous paragraph are deemed to be complied with when the investor has fulfilled the proceedings provided for by the law of the Contracting Party on the territory of which the investment has been carried out.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Settlement of Disputes between Investors and Contracting Parties">
        <p>1. Any dispute which may arise between one of the Contracting Parties and the investors of the other Contracting Party on investments, including disputes relating to the amount of compensation, shall be settled in a friendly way.</p>
        <p>2. In case the Investor and one entity of one of the Parties have stipulated an investment agreement, the procedure foreseen in such investment agreement shall apply.</p>
        <p>3. . In the event that such dispute cannot be settled in a friendly way within six months of the date of the written application for settlement, the investor in question may submit at his choice the dispute for settlement to:</p>
        <p>a) The Contracting Party's Court having territorial jurisdiction;</p>
        <p>b) An ad-hoc Arbitration Tribunal, in compliance with the arbitration regulation of the UN Commission on the International Trade Law (UNCITRAL). The host Contracting Party undertakes hereby to accept the reference to said arbitration.</p>
        <p>c) The International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes, for the implementation of the arbitration procedures under the Washington Convention of March 18th, 1965, on the settlement of investment disputes between States and nationals of other States, if or as soon as both the Contracting Parties have acceded to it.</p>
        <p>4. Under paragraph 3, lett. b), of this Article, arbitration shall be conducted pursuant to the following provisions:</p>
        <p>The Arbitration Tribunal shall be composed of three arbitrators; if they are not nationals of either Contracting Party, they shall be nationals of States having diplomatic relations with both Contracting Parties, appointed by the President of the Arbitration Institute of the Stockholm/Paris Chamber, in his capacity as Appointing Authority. The arbitration will take place in Stockholm/Paris, unless the two Parties in the arbitration have agreed otherwise. When delivering its decision, the Arbitration Tribunal shall apply the provisions contained in this Agreement, as well as the principles of international law recognized by the two Contracting Parties. The arbitration decision made in the territory of the Contracting Parties shall be implemented in compliance with their respective national legislation and the relevant international Conventions they have subscribed.</p>
        <p>5. Both Contracting Parties shall refrain for negotiating through diplomatic channels any matter relating to an arbitration or judicial procedures underway until these procedures have been concluded, and one of the Contracting Parties has failed to comply with the ruling of the Arbitration Tribunal or the Court of law within the period envisaged by the ruling, or else within the period which can be determined on the basis of the international or domestic law provisions which can be applied to the case.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Settlement of Disputes between the Contracting Parties">
        <p>1. Any dispute which may arise between the Contracting Parties relating to the interpretation and application of this Agreement shall, as far as possible, be settled in a friendly way through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2. In the event that the dispute cannot be settled within six months of the date on which one of the Contracting Parties notifies, in writing, the other Contracting Party, the dispute shall, at the request of one of the Contracting Parties, be laid before an ad-hoc Arbitration Tribunal as provided in this Article.</p>
        <p>3. The Arbitration Tribunal shall be constituted in the following manner: within two months from the moment on which the request for arbitration is received, each of the two Contracting Parties shall appoint a member of the Tribunal. The two members shall then choose a national of a Third State to serve as a President. The President shall be appointed within three months of the date on which the other two members are appointed.</p>
        <p>4. If, within the period specified in paragraph 3. of this Article, the appointments have not been made, each of the two Contracting Parties can, in default of other arrangement, ask the President of the International Court of Justice to make the appointment. In the event that the President of the Court is a national of one of the Contracting Parties or it is, for any reason, impossible for him to make the appointment, the application shall be made to the Vice President of the Court. If the Vice-President of the Court is a national of one of the Contracting Parties, or is unable to make the appointment for any reason, the most senior member of the International Court of Justice, who is not a national of one of the Contracting Parties, shall be invited to make the appointment.</p>
        <p>5. The Arbitration Tribunal shall rule with a majority vote, and its decisions shall be binding. Both Contracting Parties shall pay the costs of their own arbitration and of their representative at the hearings. The President's costs and any other cost shall be divided equally between the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>The Arbitration Tribunal shall lay down its own procedures.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Relations between Governments">
        <p>The provisions of this Agreement shall be applied irrespective of whether or not the Contracting Parties have diplomatic or consular relations.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Application of other Provisions">
        <p>1. If a matter is governed both by this Agreement and by another International Agreement to which both Contracting Parties are signatories, or by general international law provisions, the most favourable provisions shall be applied to the Contracting Parties and to their investors.</p>
        <p>2. Whenever the treatment accorded by one Contracting Party to the investors of the other Contracting Party, according to its laws and regulations or other provisions or specific contract or investment authorisations or agreement, is more favourable than that provided under this Agreement, the most favourable treatment shall apply.</p>
        <p>In case the host Contracting Party has not applied such treatment, in conformity with the above, and the investor suffers a damage as a consequence thereof, the investors shall be entitled to an adequate compensation of such damages to be paid without undue delay and in a freely convertible currency.</p>
        <p>3. After the date when the investment has been made, any substantial modification in the legislation of the Contracting Party regulating directly or indirectly the investment shall not be applied retroactively and the investments made under this Agreement shall therefore be protected.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Scope of Application">
        <p>The provisions of this Agreement shall, from the date of entry into force thereof , also apply to investments that legally exist on that date, but they shall not apply to investment disputes which arose before its entry into force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="14" title="Entry Into Force">
        <p>The present Agreement shall enter into force on the date of receipt of last of the two notifications by which the two Contracting Parties shall have communicate officially by each other the completion of the respective constitutional procedures as provided for such cases.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="15" title="Duration and Expiry">
        <p>1. This Agreement shall remain effective for a period of 10 years from the date of the notification under Article 14 and shall remain in force for further periods of 5 years thereafter, save if one of two Contracting Parties withdraws in writing by not later than one year before its expiry date.</p>
        <p>2. In the case of investments effected prior to the expiry dates, as provided under paragraph 1 of this Article, the provisions of Articles 1 to 13 shall remain effective for a further five years after the aforementioned dates.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>DONE AT GUATEMALA CITY, this 8th day of September, 2003, in two originals, each in Italian, Spanish, and English languages, all texts being equally authentic.</p>
      <p>In case of any divergence, the English text shall prevail.</p>
      <p>FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE ITALIAN REPUBLIC</p>
      <p>FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF GUATEMALA</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
