<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Finland - Iran, Islamic Republic of BIT (2002)</name>
    <code>T2002-73</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">FIN</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">IRN</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2002-11-04</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2004-06-25</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">fi,en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>1503</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>fi,en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{FIN,IRN}_2002-11-04.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Agreement on the Promotion and Protection of Investments between the Government of the Republic of Finland and the Government of the Islamic Republic of Iran </p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Republic of Finland and the Government of the Islamic Republic of Iran, hereinafter referred to as "the Contracting Parties",</p>
      <p>DESIRING to intensify economic cooperation  tothe mutual benefit of both Contracting  Parties;   </p>
      <p>INTENDING toutilise their economic resources  and potential facilities in the area of  investmentsas well as to create and maintain  favourable conditions for investmentsof investors  of the Contracting Parties in the territory  of theother Contracting Party;   </p>
      <p>RECOGNISING the need to promote and  protectinvestments of the investors of one  Contracting Party in the territory ofthe other  Contracting Party;  </p>
      <p>HAVE AGREED AS FOLLOWS:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>Forthe purpose of this Agreement, the  meaning of the terms used therein areas follows:    </p>
        <p>1. The term "investment" refers toevery  kind of asset invested by investors of one  Contracting Partyin the territory of the other  Contracting Party in accordance with the  lawsand regulations of the latter Contracting  Party (hereinafter referred toas the "host  Contracting Party") including the following:  </p>
        <p>a)movable or immovable property as well  as rights related thereto;</p>
        <p>b)shares or any other kind of participation in a companies;</p>
        <p>c)industrial or intellectual property rights such as patents, utilitymodels, industrial designs and industrial models, trade marks and  tradenames, know-how and goodwill;   </p>
        <p>d) rights conferred by law includingrights  to search for, extract and exploit natural resources.  </p>
        <p>2. Theterm "investor" with regard to either Contracting Party refersto:  </p>
        <p>a) natural persons who, according to the  laws of thatContracting Party, are considered  to be its nationals;  </p>
        <p>b) legalpersons which are established under the laws of that Contracting Partyand having their seat and real economic activity  in the territoryof that Contracting Party.  </p>
        <p>3. The term "returns" refers to theamounts yielded by an investment including profit derived  frominvestments, dividends, royalties  and fees.  </p>
        <p>4. The term"territory" refers to:  </p>
        <p>a) in the case of the Republic ofFinland, the land territory, internal waters and territorial seaand the airspace above them and the  maritime zones beyond the territorialsea over  which the Republic of Finland has sovereignty, exercisessovereign rights or exclusive  jurisdiction in accordance with itsnational laws  in force and international law, and  </p>
        <p>b) in the case ofthe Islamic Republic of  Iran, areas under the sovereignty or jurisdiction of the Islamic Republic of Iran as, the  case may be, and includesits maritime areas.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion of investments">
        <p>Either Contracting Party shall, within the  frameworkof its laws and regulations, encourage  and create favourable conditionsfor  attraction of investments of investors of the  other ContractingParty in its territory.   </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Admission of investments">
        <p>1. Either Contracting Party shall admit investments  ofinvestors of the other Contracting  Party in its territory in accordancewith its laws and regulations.  </p>
        <p>2. When an investment is admitted,either  Contracting Part shall, in accordance with its  laws,regulations and established national  policies, grant all necessarypermits for the  realisation of such investments. Each Contracting  Partyshall further, within the  framework of its legislation, give asympathetic  consideration to applications for engaging  topmanagerial and technical personnel of  their choice, from abroad.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Protection and treatment of investments">
        <p>1. Investments of investors of eitherContracting  Party effected within the territory of  the otherContracting Party, shall receive the  host Contracting Party's full andconstant protection  and fair and equitable treatment. Such  investmentsand returns related thereto, shall  be accorded treatment which is notless favourable  than the host Contracting Party accords  to theinvestments and returns made by  its own investors or by investors of themost  favoured nation, whichever is the more favourable  to theinvestor.  </p>
        <p>2. Investors of one Contracting Party shall  be accordedby the other Contracting Party,  as regards the management, maintenance,  use,enjoyment or disposal of their investments,  treatment which is not lessfavourable  than the host Contracting Party accords its  owninvestors or to investors of the most favoured  nation, whichever is themore favourable  to the investor.  </p>
        <p>3. Each Contracting Party shallnot impair  by unreasonable, arbitrary or discriminatory  measuresthe management, maintenance, use,  enjoyment acquisition or disposal ofinvestments  in its territory of investors of the other  ContractingParty.  </p>
        <p>4. If a Contracting Party accords special  advantages orrights to investors of any third  state by virtue of an existing or futureagreement  establishing a free trade area, a customs  union, acommon market or a similar regional  organisation or by virtue of anarrangement on the avoidance of double taxation or  through anymultilateral convention or treaty  related to investments, it shall not beobliged  to accord such advantages or rights to investors  of theother Contracting Party.   </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="More favourable provisions">
        <p>Notwithstanding the terms set forth in this  Agreement,more favourable provisions  which have been or may be agreed upon  byeither of the Contracting Parties with respect  to an investment of aninvestor of the  other Contracting Party are applicable only  to thatinvestment.   </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Application of other rules">
        <p>1. If the provisions of law of either Contracting  Partyor obligations under bilateral  agreements established hereafter betweenthe  Contracting Parties in addition to this Agreement  contain aregulation, whether general or  specific, entitling investments made byinvestors  of the other Contracting Party to a treatment  morefavourable than is provided for by  this Agreement, such provisions shall,to the  extent that they are more favourable to the  investor,prevail over this Agreement.  </p>
        <p>2. Each Contracting Party shall observe the  commitmentsit has entered into with respect  to investments of investors of the otherContracting  Party.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Expropriation and compensation">
        <p>1. Investments of investors of either Contracting  Partyshall not be nationalised, confiscated,  expropriated or subjected tosimilar  measures by the other Contracting Party except  where suchmeasures are taken for a  public purpose, in a non-discriminatory manner  andupon payment of compensation.  </p>
        <p>2. The compensation shall amount to the  realvalue of the investment immediately before  the act of nationalisation,confiscation or  expropriation was taken or became public  knowledge,whichever earlier.  </p>
        <p>3. Compensation shall be fully realisable  andshall be paid without delay. However, in  case of delay, the compensationshall include  the costs thereof. It shall be effectively realizable andfreely transferable. Any dispute as  to the conformity of suchexpropriation with  the relevant legislation, or as to the amount of  compensationshall be subject to review by  due process of law in the competent courtsof  the country where the investment has taken  place.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Losses">
        <p>1. Investors of either Contracting Party  whose investmentssuffer losses due to any  armed conflict, revolution or similar state of  emergencyin the territory of the other Contracting  Party shall be accorded by theother Contracting Party treatment no less favourable  than thataccorded to its own investors  or to investors of the most favourednation,  whichever more favourable to the investor.  Possibleresulting payments shall be effectively  realisable, freely convertibleand  transferred without delay.  </p>
        <p>2. Without prejudice to paragraph(1) of  this Article, an investor of one Contracting  Party who, inany of the situations referred to  in that paragraph, suffers a loss inthe territory  of the other Contracting Party resulting  from:  </p>
        <p>(a)requisitioning of its investment or a part  thereof by the latter's armedforces or authorities, or  </p>
        <p>(b) destruction of its investment or a part thereof by the latter's armed forces or authorities,  which was notrequired by the necessity  of situation,  </p>
        <p>shall be accordedrestitution or compensation  equivalent to the real value of theinvestment.    </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Repatriation and transfer">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Partyshall ensure the  transfers related to investments referred to in  thisAgreement shall be made freely and  without delay into and out of itsterritory.  Such transfers shall in particular include:  </p>
        <p>(a) theprincipal and additional amounts to  maintain, develop or increase theinvestment;</p>
        <p>(b) returns;  </p>
        <p>(c) proceeds from the sale or liquidationof  all or part of an investment;  </p>
        <p>(d) the amounts required forpayment of  expenses which arise from the operation of  theinvestment, such as loans repayments,  payment of royalties and licencefees or other  similar expenses;  </p>
        <p>(e) sums paid pursuant to Articles7 and 8  of this Agreement;  </p>
        <p>(f) monthly salaries and wages and other remuneration received by the employees who  have obtained thecorresponding work permits  related to an investment;  </p>
        <p>(g) paymentsarising out of the settlement of disputes under Article 12;  </p>
        <p>2. Theabove transfers shall be effected in a freely convertible currency and atthe applicable rate of exchange on the date of transfer.  </p>
        <p>3. Theinvestor may choose to agree otherwise  with the host Contracting Party onthe  manner of repatriation or transfers referred to  in thisArticle.  </p>
        <p>4. Notwithstanding paragraphs (1) to (3) of  this Article,a Contracting Party may prevent  a transfer through the equitable, nondiscriminatory and good faith application of measures to protectthe rights of creditors or  in connection with criminal offences, orders  orjudgements in administrative and adjudicatory  proceedings, provided thatsuch measures  and their application shall not be used as  a means ofavoiding the Contracting Party's commitments or obligations under this Agreement. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Subrogation">
        <p>If a Contracting Party or its designated agency subrogates under due process of law  an investor pursuant toa payment made under  an insurance or guarantee agreement  againstnon-commercial risks:   </p>
        <p>(a) such subrogation shall be recognised by  theother Contracting Party;  </p>
        <p>(b) the subrogee shall not be entitled toexercise  any rights other than the rights which  the investor wouldhave been entitled to exercise;  </p>
        <p>(c) disputes between the subrogee and the host Contracting Party shall be settled in accordance  with Article12 of this Agreement.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Scope of the agreement">
        <p>1. This Agreement shall apply to investments madeby investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of the otherContracting  Party, whether made before or after  the entry intoforce of this Agreement, but  shall not apply to any dispute concerning an investment which arose or any claim, which was settled before itsentry into force.  </p>
        <p>2. In the case of the Islamic Republic of  Iranonly investments approved by the competent authorities of thatContracting Party  are covered by this Agreement. The competent  authorityin the Islamic Republic of Iran  is Organization for Investment, Economic  andTechnical Assistance of Iran  (O.I.E.T.A.I.), or the agency which might  succeedit.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Settlement of disputes between an investor and a contracting party">
        <p>1. Any dispute between an investor of one  ContractingParty and the other Contracting Party concerning an investment in the territory of the latter Contracting Party shall,if possible, be settled amicably.   </p>
        <p>2. If the dispute cannotthus be settled within three (3) months, following the date of requestfor settlement, the dispute may, at the  choice of the investor, besubmitted to:  </p>
        <p>(a) a competent court of the Contracting  Party inwhose territory the investment has  been made, or  </p>
        <p>(b) theInternational Centre for Settlement  of Investment Disputes (ICSID), forthe implementation of the arbitration procedure under  theConvention on the Settlement of Investment  Disputes between States andNationals  of other States, opened for signature  at Washington on 18March 1965, if or as  soon as both Contracting Parties have acceded  toit; or  </p>
        <p>(c) an ad hoc arbitration tribunal, which unless otherwiseagreed upon by the parties to the dispute, is to be established under the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commission  on InternationalTrade Law  (UNCITRAL).  </p>
        <p>3. During arbitration proceedings or theenforcement of an award, the Contracting Party involved in thedispute shall not raise the objection that the investor of the otherContracting Party has received compensation under an  insurancecontract in respect of all or part of the damages.  </p>
        <p>4. The awardshall be final and binding for the parties to the dispute and shall beexecuted  according to national law .  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Settlement of disputes between the contracting &#xA0;parties">
        <p>1. Disputesbetween the Contracting Parties  concerning the interpretation andapplication of this Agreement shall, as far as possible, be  settledthrough diplomatic channels.  </p>
        <p>2. If the dispute cannot thus be settled  withinsix (6) months, following the date on  which such negotiations wererequested by  either Contracting Party, it shall at the request  ofeither Contracting Party be submitted to an Arbitral Tribunal.   </p>
        <p>3.Such an Arbitral Tribunal shall be constituted for each individual casein the following  way. Within two (2) months of the receipt  of therequest for arbitration, each Contracting  Party shall appoint one memberof  the Tribunal. Those two members shall then select a national ofa third State who on approval  by the two Contracting Parties shall be  appointedChairman of the Tribunal. The Chairman shall be appointed within four (4) months from the date of appointment of the  other two members.However, the Chairman  shall be a national of a state having diplomatic relationswith both Contracting parties  at the time of the appointment.  </p>
        <p>4. Ifwithin the periods specified in paragraph 3 of this Article the necessaryappointments  have not been made, either Contracting  Party may, inthe absence of any  other agreement, invite the President of the  InternationalCourt of Justice to make any necessary appointments. If the President isa  national of either Contracting Party or is otherwise  preventedfrom discharging the said  function, the Member of the International Courtof Justice next in seniority who is not a  national of either ContractingParty or is  otherwise prevented from discharging the  said function,shall be invited to make the  necessary appointments.  </p>
        <p>5. TheArbitral Tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Thedecisions  of the Tribunal shall be final and binding on bothContracting Parties. Each Contracting Party shall bear the costs of themember appointed  by that Contracting Party and of its representationat the arbitral proceedings. Both Contracting Parties shall assume an  equalshare of the cost of the Chairman, as  well as any other costs. TheTribunal may make a different decision regarding the sharing of thecosts. In all other respects, the Arbitral  Tribunal shall determine itsown rules  of procedure and the place of arbitration.  </p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="14" title="Validity of the agreement">
        <p>1. This Agreement shall be ratified by the competentauthorities of each Contracting  Party.   </p>
        <p>2. This Agreementshall enter into force  for a period of fifteen (15) years on the 30th  dayafter the date of the receipt of the last notification  of eitherContracting Party to the  other Contracting Party that it has fulfilled  thenecessary requirements for the entry into  force of this Agreement. Afterthe said period, this Agreement shall remain in force  thereafterunless one of the Contracting Parties  notifies the other ContractingParty in  writing of its unwillingness to continue with  it, sixmonths prior to the expiration or termination  thereof.  </p>
        <p>3. After theexpiration of the validity or termination  of this Agreement theprovisions of  Articles 1 to 13 shall apply to investments  underthis Agreement for a further period of  fifteen (15) years.  </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <attachments>
      <p>IN WITNESSWHEREOF, the undersigned  representatives, duly authorised thereto, have  signedthe present Agreement.   </p>
      <p>Done in duplicate at Tehran on the 4th of  November2002 corresponding to Aban 13,  1381 in the Solar Hijri Year, in theFinnish,  Persian, and English languages, all texts being  equallyauthentic. In case of divergence  in interpretation, the English textshall prevail. </p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of Finland  </p>
      <p>For the Government of the Islamic Republic of Iran    </p>
    </attachments>
  </main>
</treaty>
