<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Ghana - Mauritius BIT (2001)</name>
    <code>T2001-131</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">GHA</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">MUS</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2001-05-18</date_signed>
    <date_into_force/>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>1789</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{GHA,MUS}_2001-05-18.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF MAURITIUS AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF GHANA FOR THE PROMOTION AND RECIPROCAL PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Republic of Ghana and the Government of the Republic of Mauritius (hereinafter referred to as the "Contracting Parties");</p>
      <p>DESIRING to create favourable conditions for greater flow of investments made by investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party; and</p>
      <p>RECOGNISING that the promotion and reciprocal protection of such investments will lend greater stimulation to the development of business initiatives and will increase prosperity in the territories of both Contracting Parties;</p>
      <p>HAVE agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>(1) In this Agreement,</p>
        <p>(a) "investment" means every kind of asset admissible under the relevant laws and regulations of the Contracting Party in whose territory the respective business undertaking is made, and in particular, though not exclusively, includes:</p>
        <p>(i) Movable and immovable property as well as other rights in rem such as mortgages, liens or pledges;</p>
        <p>(ii) Shares and stocks, debentures and any other form of participation in a company;</p>
        <p>(iii) Claims to money, or to any performance under contract having an economic value;</p>
        <p>(iv) Intellectual property rights, in particular copyrights, patents, utility-model patents, designs, trade-marks, trade-names, technical processes, know-how, and goodwill;</p>
        <p>(v) Economic value of concession rights or permits conferred in accordance with the law or under contract, including concessions to search for, cultivate, extract or exploit natural resources;</p>
        <p>(b) "returns" means the amount yielded by an investment and in particular, though not exclusively, profit, interest, capital gains, dividends, royalties and fees;</p>
        <p>(c) "investor" means in respect to either Contracting Party:</p>
        <p>(i) The "national", that is a natural person deriving his or her status as a national of that Contracting Party from the relevant laws of that Contracting Party; and</p>
        <p>(ii) The "company" that is a legal person, such as a corporation, firm or association, incorporated or constituted in accordance with the law of that Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>(d) "territory" means -</p>
        <p>(1) In the case of the Republic of Mauritius -</p>
        <p>(i) All the territories and islands which, in accordance with the laws of Mauritius constitute the State of Mauritius;</p>
        <p>(ii) The territorial sea of Mauritius; and</p>
        <p>(iii) Any area outside the territorial sea of Mauritius which in accordance with international law has been or may hereafter be designated, under the laws of Mauritius, as an area, including the Continental Shelf, within which the rights of Mauritius with respect to the sea, the sea-bed and sub-soil and their natural resources may be exercised;</p>
        <p>(2) In the case of the Republic of Ghana-</p>
        <p>(i) The territorial sea of the Republic of Ghana; and</p>
        <p>(ii) Any area outside the territorial sea of the Republic of Ghana which in accordance with international law has been or may hereafter be designated, under the laws of the Republic of Ghana, as an area, including the continental shelf, within which the rights of Ghana with respect to the sea, the sea-bed and subsoil and their natural resources may be exercised.</p>
        <p>(2) Any change in the form in which assets are or have been invested does not affect their character as investments as defined in this Agreement, provided such change is not contrary to the laws of the Contracting Parties in whose territory the investment has been made.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Scope of the agreement">
        <p>(1) This Agreement shall only apply -</p>
        <p>(a) In respect of investments in the territory of the Republic of Mauritius, to all investments made by investors of the Republic of Ghana.</p>
        <p>(b) In respect of the investments in the territory of the Republic of Ghana, to all investments made by investors of the Republic of Mauritius.</p>
        <p>(2) This Agreement shall apply to investments made prior to and after its entry into force by investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party. For the avoidance of any doubt, it is declared that all investments shall, subject to this Agreement, be governed by the laws in force in the territory of the Contracting Party in which such investments are made. It shall not, however, apply to investment disputes arising before its entry into force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Promotion and protection of investments">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party shall, subject to its general policy in the field of foreign investment encourage the making of investments in its territory by investors of the other Contracting Party, and, subject to compliance with the provisions of its laws, shall admit such investments.</p>
        <p>(2) Each Contracting Party shall use its best endeavours to grant, in accordance with its laws, the necessary permits in connection with the carrying out of such investments and, whenever necessary, licensing agreements and contracts for technical, commercial or administrative assistance.</p>
        <p>(3) Investments admitted under Article 2 shall be accorded fair and equitable protection in accordance with this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Treatment of investments">
        <p>(1) Investments and returns of investors of either Contracting Party shall at all times be accorded fair and equitable treatment in the territory of the other Contracting Party. Neither Contracting Party shall in any way impair by unreasonable nor discriminatory measures the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal of investments in its territory by investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(2) Each Contracting Party shall in its territory accord to investors and to investments and returns of investors of the other Contracting Party treatment not less favourable than that which it accords to investments and returns of investors of any third State.</p>
        <p>(3) The provisions of paragraph (2) shall not be construed so as to oblige either Contracting Party to extend to the investors of the other Contracting Party the benefit of any treatment, preference or privilege resulting from:</p>
        <p>(a) Any customs union, free trade area, common market or any similar international agreement or interim arrangement leading up to such customs union, free trade area, or common market of which either of the Contracting Parties is a member;</p>
        <p>(b) Any international agreement or arrangement relating wholly or mainly to taxation or any domestic legislation relating wholly or mainly to taxation;</p>
        <p>(c) Special advantages to foreign development finance institutions operating in the territory of either Contracting Party for the exclusive purpose of development assistance through mainly nonprofit activities.</p>
        <p>(4) Each Contracting Party shall observe the obligations under its laws and under this Agreement which bind the Contracting Party and the investors of the other Contracting Party in matters relating to investments.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Compensation for losses">
        <p>Investors of either Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party suffer losses owing to war or other armed conflict, revolution, a state of national emergency, revolt, insurrection or riot in the territory of the latter Contracting Party shall be accorded by the latter Contracting Party treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or other settlement, not less favourable than that which the latter Contracting Party accords to investors of any third State. Resulting payments shall be freely transferable at the rate of exchange applicable on the date of transfer pursuant to the exchange regulations in force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Expropriation">
        <p>(1) Investments of investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall not be nationalised, expropriated or subjected to measures having effects equivalent to nationalisation or expropriation except for public purposes, under due process of law, on a non-discriminatory basis and against prompt, adequate and effective compensation amounting to the full and genuine value of the investment. Such compensation shall be made without delay, and be effectively realizable. Resulting payments shall be freely transferable at the rate of exchange applicable on the date of transfer pursuant to the exchange regulations in force.</p>
        <p>(2) The investor affected by the expropriation shall have a right, under the law of the expropriating Contracting Party to prompt review, by a court of law or other independent and impartial forum of that Contracting Party of the expropriation case.</p>
        <p>(3) Where a Contracting Party expropriates, nationalises or takes measures having effect equivalent to nationalisation or expropriation against the assets of a company which is incorporated or constituted under the laws in force in any part of its own territory, and in which investors of the other Contracting Party own shares, it shall ensure that the provisions of paragraph (1) of this article are applied to the extent necessary to guarantee compensation as specified therein to such investors of the other Contracting Party who are owners of those shares.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Repatriation of investment and returns">
        <p>(1) Each Contracting Party shall, in accordance with its relevant laws, allow investors of the other Contracting Party the free transfer of funds relating to their investments and returns, including compensation paid pursuant to the provisions of articles 5 and 6 of this Agreement.</p>
        <p>(2) All transfers shall be effected without delay in the convertible currency in which capital was originally invested or in any other convertible currency agreed to by the investor and the Contracting Party concerned, subject, however, to the right of the former Contracting Party to impose equitably and in good faith such measures as may be necessary to safeguard the integrity and independence of its currency, its external financial position and balance of payments. Unless otherwise agreed by the investor, transfers shall be made at the rate of exchange applicable on the date of transfer pursuant to the exchange regulations.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of disputes between an investor and a contracting party">
        <p>(1) Any dispute between an investor of one Contracting Party and the other Contracting Party in connection with an investment in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall, as far as possible, be settled amicably through negotiations between the parties to the dispute.</p>
        <p>(2) If the dispute cannot be settled through negotiations within six months, either party to the dispute shall be entitled to initiate judicial action before the competent court of the Contracting Party in whose territory of investment was made or it may be submitted to an international arbitral tribunal established by both parties.</p>
        <p>(3) Where the dispute is referred to international arbitration, the investor and the Contracting Party concerned in the dispute may agree to refer the dispute either to:</p>
        <p>(a) The International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (having regard to the provisions, where applicable, of the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between states and nationals of other states, opened for signature at Washington D.C. on 18th March, 1965 and the Additional Facility for the Administration of conciliation, Arbitration and Fact-Finding proceedings); or</p>
        <p>(b) An international arbitrator or ad hoc arbitration tribunal to be appointed by a special agreement between the parties of establish under the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commission on International Law.</p>
        <p>(4) If after a period of six months from written notification of the claim there is no agreement to one of the above alternative procedures, the parties to the dispute shall be bound to submit it to arbitration under the arbitration rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law as then in force. The parties to the dispute may agree in writing to modify these rules.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>(1) Any dispute between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or application of this Agreement should, if possible, be settled through negotiations between the Governments of the two Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>(2) If the dispute cannot be settled within a period of six months following the date on which such negotiations were requested by either Contracting Party, it may upon the request of either Contracting Party, be submitted to an arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>(3) Such an arbitral tribunal shall be constituted for each individual case in the following way: within two months of the receipt of the request for arbitration, each Contracting Party shall appoint one arbitrator for the tribunal. Those two arbitrators shall then select a national of a third State who, upon approval by the two Contracting Parties, shall be appointed Chairman of the tribunal. The Chairman shall be appointed within two months from the date of appointment of the other two arbitrators.</p>
        <p>(4) If within the periods specified in paragraph (3) of this Article the necessary appointments have not been made, either Contracting Party may, in the absence of any other agreement, invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make any necessary appointments. If the President is a national of either Contracting Party or if he is otherwise prevented from discharging the said function, the Vice-President shall be invited to make the necessary appointments. If the Vice-President is a national of either Contracting Party or if he too is prevented from discharging the said function, the Member of the International Court of Justice next in seniority who is not a national of either Contracting Party and not prevented from discharging such functions shall be invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>(5) The arbitral tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Such decision shall be binding on both Contracting Parties. Each Contracting Party shall bear the cost of its own arbitrator to the tribunal and of its representation in the arbitral proceedings. The cost of the Chairman and the remaining costs shall be borne equally by the Contracting Parties. The tribunal may, however, in its decision direct that a higher proportion of costs shall be borne by one of the two Contracting Parties, and this award shall be binding on, and executed by, both Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>(6) Apart from the above, the tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Subrogation">
        <p>(1) If a Contracting Party or its designated agency makes a payment to its own investor under a guarantee it has given in respect of an investment made in the territory of the other Contracting Party, the latter Contracting Party shall recognise the assignment to the former Contracting Party of all the rights and claims of the indemnified investor, and shall also recognise that the former Contracting Party or its designated Agency is entitled to exercise such rights and enforce such claims by virtue of subrogation, to the same extent as the original investor.</p>
        <p>(2) The former Contracting Party or its designated Agency shall be entitled in all circumstances to the same treatment in respect of the rights and claims acquired by it by virtue of the assignment and any payments received in pursuance of those rights and claims as the party indemnified was entitled to receive by virtue of this Agreement in respect of the investment concerned and its related returns.</p>
        <p>(3) Any payments received by the former Contracting Party or its designated Agency in pursuance of the rights and claims acquired shall be freely available to the former Contracting Party for the purpose of meeting any expenditure incurred in the territory of the latter Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Application of other rules">
        <p>(1) If the provisions of the law of either Contracting Party or obligations under international law existing at present or established hereafter between the Contracting Parties, in addition to the present Agreement, contain rules, whether general or specific, entitling investments and returns of investors of the other Contracting Party to treatment more favourable than that provided for by the present Agreement, such rules shall, to the extent that they are more favourable, prevail over the present Agreement.</p>
        <p>(2) Each Contracting Party shall, however, honour any obligation it may have entered into with regard to investments of investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Entry into force, duration and termination">
        <p>(1) The Contracting Parties shall notify each other promptly of the fulfillment of their legal procedures required for entry into force of this Agreement. The Agreement shall enter into force on the day following the date of receipt of the last notification.</p>
        <p>(2) This Agreement shall remain in force for a period of ten years. Thereafter it shall continue in force until the expiration of twelve months from the date on which either Contracting Party shall have given written notice of termination of this Agreement to the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(3) In respect of investments approved and/or made prior to the date the notice of termination of this Agreement becomes effective, the provisions of the preceeding Articles shall remain in force with respect to such investments for a further period of ten years from that date or for any longer period as provided for or agreed upon in the relevant contract or approval granted to the investor.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, duly authorized thereto, have signed this Agreement in ....., on this ..... day of ..... of the year of 2001 ...., in duplicate in the English Language.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of Mauritius</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of Ghana</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
