<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Finland - Georgia BIT (2006)</name>
    <code>T2006-59</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">FIN</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">GEO</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2006-11-24</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2007-12-30</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">fi, en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>1497</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>fi, en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{FIN,GEO}_2006-11-24.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T1996-129">EC - Georgia Cooperation Agreement (1996)</relation>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T2014-26">EU - Georgia Association Agreement (2014)</relation>
    <relation type="IT_COEXISTS_WITH" document-code="T1994-84">The Energy Charter Treaty (1994)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Agreement between the Government of the Republic of Finland and the Government of Georgia on the Promotion and Protection of Investments</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Republic of Finland and the Government of Georgia, hereinafter referred to as "the Contracting Parties",</p>
      <p>RECOGNISINGthe need to protect investments of the investors of one Contracting Party inthe territory of the other Contracting Party on a non-discriminatory basis;</p>
      <p>DESIRING topromote greater economic co-operation between them, with respect to investmentsby nationals and companies of one Contracting Party in the territory of the otherContracting Party;</p>
      <p>RECOGNISINGthat agreement on the treatment to be accorded such investments will stimulatethe flow of private capital and the economic development of the Contracting Parties;</p>
      <p>AGREEINGthat a stable framework for investment will contribute to maximising the effectiveutilisation of economic resources and improve living standards;</p>
      <p>RECOGNISINGthat the development of economic and business ties can promote respect forinternationally recognised labour rights;</p>
      <p>AGREEINGthat these objectives can be achieved without relaxing health, safety and environmentalmeasures of general application; and</p>
      <p>Havingresolved to conclude an Agreement concerning the promotion and protection of investments;</p>
      <p>HAVE AGREED AS FOLLOWS:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purpose of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>1. The term"investment" shall mean every kind of asset or rights established oracquired by an investor of one Contracting Party in the territory of the otherContracting Party in accordance with the laws and regulations of the latterContracting Party, including in particular, though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>(a) movableand immovable property or any property rights such as mortgages, liens,pledges, leases, usufruct and similar rights;</p>
        <p>(b) sharesin and stocks and debentures of a company or any other forms of participation ina company;</p>
        <p>(c) claimsto money or rights to a performance having an economic value;</p>
        <p>(d)intellectual property rights, such as patents, copyrights, trade marks,industrial designs, business names, geographical indications as well astechnical processes, know-how and goodwill; and</p>
        <p>(e)concessions conferred by law, by an administrative act or under a contract by acompetent authority, including concessions to search for, develop, extract orexploit natural resources.</p>
        <p>Investmentsmade in the territory of one Contracting Party by any legal entity of that sameContracting Party, but actually owned or controlled, directly or indirectly, byinvestors of the other Contracting Party, shall likewise be considered asinvestments of investors of the latter Contracting Party if they have been madein accordance with the laws and regulations of the former Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>Any changein the form in which assets are invested or reinvested does not affect their characteras investments.</p>
        <p>2. The term"returns" shall mean the amounts yielded by investments and shall in particular,though not exclusively, include profits, dividends, interest, royalties,capital gains or any payments in kind related to an investment.</p>
        <p>Reinvestedreturns shall enjoy the same treatment as the original investment.</p>
        <p>3. The term"investor" shall mean, for either Contracting Party, the followingsubjects who invest in the territory of the other Contracting Party inaccordance with the laws of the latter Contracting Party and the provisions ofthis Agreement:</p>
        <p>(a) anynatural person who is a national or citizen of either Contracting Party and permanentlyresiding in its territory in accordance with its laws; or</p>
        <p>(b) anylegal entity such as company, corporation, firm, partnership, businessassociation, institution or organisation, incorporated or constituted inaccordance with the laws and regulations of the Contracting Party and havingits registered office within the jurisdiction of that Contracting Party, whetherits liabilities are limited or not.</p>
        <p>4. The term"territory" shall mean:</p>
        <p>(a) in thecase of the Republic of Finland its land territory, internal waters andterritorial sea, and the airspace above it, as well as the maritime zonesbeyond the territorial sea, including the seabed and subsoil, over which itexercises sovereign rights or jurisdiction in accordance with its national lawsin force and international law, for the purpose of exploration and exploitationof the natural resources of such areas; and</p>
        <p>(b) in thecase of Georgia the territory within the state borders of Georgia recognized byinternational law, including its land territory, internal waters andterritorial sea, the air space above them, as well as the exclusive economiczone and continental shelf adjacent to its territorial sea in respect of whichGeorgia exercises its sovereign rights in accordance with international law, forthe purpose of exploration and exploitation of the natural resources of suchareas.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and protection of investments">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall promote in its territory investments by investors of the other Contracting Party and shall, in accordance with its laws and regulations, admit such investments.</p>
        <p>2. Each Contracting Party shall in its territory accord to investments and returns of investments of investors of the other Contracting Party fair and equitable treatment and full and constant protection and security.</p>
        <p>3. Neither Contracting Party shall in its territory impair by unreasonable or arbitrary measures the acquisition, expansion, operation, management, maintenance, use, enjoyment and sale or other disposal of investments of investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Treatment of investments">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall accord to investors of the other Contracting Party and to their investments, a treatment no less favourable than the treatment it accords to its own investors and their investments, with respect to the acquisition, expansion, operation, management, maintenance, use, enjoyment and sale or other disposal of investments.</p>
        <p>2. Each Contracting Party shall accord to investors of the other Contracting Party and to their investments, a treatment no less favorable than the treatment it accords to investors of the most favoured nation and to their investments with respect to the establishment, acquisition, expansion, operation, management, maintenance, use, enjoyment and sale or other disposal of investments.</p>
        <p>3. Each Contracting Party shall accord to investors of the other Contracting Party and to their investments, the better of the treatment required by in paragraph 1 and paragraph 2 of this Article, whichever is the more favorable according to the investor concerned.</p>
        <p>4. Neither Contracting Party shall in its territory impose mandatory measures on investments by investors of the other Contracting Party, concerning purchase of materials, means of production, operation, transport, marketing of its products or similar orders having unreasonable or discriminatory effects.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Exemptions">
        <p>The provisions of this Agreement shall not be construed so as to oblige one Contracting Party to extend to the investors and investments of the other Contracting Party the benefit of any treatment, preference or privilege by virtue of any existing or future:</p>
        <p>(a) Free trade area, customs union, common market, economic and monetary union or other similar regional economic integration agreement, including regional labour market agreements, to which one of the Contracting Parties is or may become a party, or</p>
        <p>b) Agreement for the avoidance of double taxation or other international agreement relating wholly or mainly to taxation, or</p>
        <p>c) multilateral agreement relating wholly or mainly to investments.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Expropriation">
        <p>1. Investmentsby investors of a Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Partyshall not be expropriated, nationalized or subjected to any other measures, director indirect, having an effect equivalent to expropriation or nationalisation(hereinafter referred to as "expropriation"), except for a purposewhich is in the public interest, on a non-discriminatory basis, in accordancewith due process of law, and against prompt, adequate and effective compensation.</p>
        <p>2. Suchcompensation shall amount to the value of the expropriated investment at the timeimmediately before the expropriation or before the impending expropriationbecame public knowledge, whichever is the earlier.</p>
        <p>The value shall be determined in accordance with generally accepted principles of valuation, taking into account, inter alia, the capital invested, replacement value, appreciation, current returns, the projected flow of future returns, goodwill and other relevant factors.</p>
        <p>3.Compensation shall be fully realizable and shall be paid without anyrestriction or delay. It shall include LIBOR-equal or equivalent interest ratefor the currency of payment from the date of dispossession of the expropriatedproperty until the date of actual payment.</p>
        <p>4. TheContracting Parties affirm that when a Contracting Party expropriates theassets or a part thereof of a company which has been incorporated orconstituted in accordance with the law in force in its territory, and in whichinvestors of the other Contracting Party own shares, or when the object ofexpropriation is a joint-venture constituted in the territory of a ContractingParty, the host Contracting Party shall ensure that the articles of associationand possible other relevant documents of the companies or joint-ventures concerned,as they exist at the time of expropriation, are fully respected.</p>
        <p>5. Withoutprejudice to the provisions of Article 9 of this Agreement, the investor whoseinvestments are expropriated shall have the right to prompt review of its caseand of valuation of its investments in accordance with the principles set outin this Article, by a judicial or other competent authority of that ContractingParty.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Compensation for losses">
        <p>1. Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party suffer losses owing to war or otherarmed conflict, a state of national emergency, revolt, insurrection or riot inthe territory of the latter Contracting Party, shall be accorded by the latterContracting Party, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation orother settlement, a treatment no less favourable than the one accorded by the latterContracting Party to its own investors or investors of the most favourednation, whichever, according to the investor, is the more favourable.</p>
        <p>2. Withoutprejudice to paragraph 1 of this Article, investors of one Contracting Party who,in any of the situations referred to in that paragraph, suffer losses in theterritory of the other Contracting Party resulting from:</p>
        <p>(a)requisitioning of its investment or a part thereof by the latter's armed forcesor authorities, or</p>
        <p>(b)destruction of its investment or a part thereof by the latter's armed forces orauthorities, which was not required by the necessity of the situation,</p>
        <p>shall beaccorded by the latter Contracting Party restitution or compensation which in eithercase shall be prompt, adequate and effective and with respect to compensation, shallbe in accordance with Article 5 paragraphs 2-3 from the date of requisitioningor destruction until the date of actual payment.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Free transfer">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall ensure to the investors of the other Contracting Party the free transfer, into and out of its territory, of their investments and transfer payments related to investments. Such payments shall include in particular, though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>(a)principal and additional amounts to maintain, develop or increase theinvestment;</p>
        <p>(b)returns;</p>
        <p>(c)proceeds obtained from the total or partial sale or disposal of an investment, includingthe sale of shares;</p>
        <p>(d) amountsrequired for the payment of expenses which arise from the operation of theinvestment, such as loans repayments, payment of royalties, management fees,licence fees or other similar expenses;</p>
        <p>(e)compensation payable pursuant to Articles 5, 6 and 8;</p>
        <p>(f)payments arising from the settlement of a dispute;</p>
        <p>(g)earnings and other remuneration of personnel engaged from abroad and working inconnection with an investment.</p>
        <p>2. EachContracting Party shall further ensure that the transfers referred to inparagraph 1 of this Article shall be made without any restriction in a freelyconvertible currency of the choice of the investor and at the prevailing marketrate of exchange applicable on the date of transfer to the currency to betransferred and shall be immediately transferable.</p>
        <p>3. In theabsence of a market for foreign exchange, the rate to be used shall be the mostrecent exchange rate for the conversions of currencies into Special Drawing Rights.</p>
        <p>4. In caseof a delay in transfer caused by the host Contracting Party, the transfer shallalso include LIBOR-equal or equivalent interest rate for the currency inquestion from the date on which the transfer was requested until the date ofactual transfer and shall be borne by that Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>5.Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 to 3 of this Article, a Contracting Party maydelay a transfer payment through the equitable, nondiscriminatory and goodfaith application of its laws and regulations ensuring investors' compliancewith respect to the payment of taxes and dues in force at the time the request fortransfer by the investor concerned was made, and provided that such measuresand their application shall not unnecessarily impair transfers ensured by thisAgreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Subrogation">
        <p>If a Contracting Party or its designated agency makes a payment under an indemnity, guaranteeor contract of insurance given in respect of an investment of an investor inthe territory of the other Contracting Party, the latter Contracting Partyshall recognise the assignment of any right or claim of such an investor to theformer Contracting Party or its designated agency, and the right of the former ContractingParty or its designated agency to exercise by virtue of subrogation any suchright and claim to the same extent as its predecessor in title.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Disputes between an investor and a contracting party">
        <p>1. Anydispute arising directly from an investment between one Contracting Party and aninvestor of the other Contracting Party should be settled amicably between thetwo parties concerned.</p>
        <p>2. If thedispute has not been settled within three (3) months from the date on which it wasraised in writing, the dispute may, at the choice of the investor, besubmitted:</p>
        <p>(a) to thecompetent courts of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investment ismade; or</p>
        <p>(b) toarbitration by the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID),established pursuant to the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputesbetween States and Nationals of other States, opened for signature at Washingtonon 18 March 1965 (hereinafter referred to as the "Centre"), when bothof the Contracting Parties are members of the Centre; or</p>
        <p>(c) toarbitration by the Additional Facility of the Centre, if only one of theContracting Parties is a signatory to the Convention referred to insubparagraph (b) of this paragraph; or</p>
        <p>(d) to anyad hoc arbitration tribunal which unless otherwise agreed upon by the Partiesto the dispute, is to be established under the Arbitration Rules of the United NationsCommission on International Trade Law (UNCITRAL).</p>
        <p>3. Aninvestor who has submitted the dispute to a national court may neverthelesshave recourse to one of the arbitral tribunals mentioned in paragraphs 2 (b) to(d) of this Article if, before a judgement has been delivered on the subjectmatter by a national court, the investor declares not to pursue the case anylonger through national proceedings and withdraws the case.</p>
        <p>4. Anyarbitration under this Article shall, at the request of either party to thedispute, be held in a state that is a party to the Convention on theRecognition and Enforcement of Foreign Arbitral Awards (New York Convention), openedfor signature at New York on 10 June 1958. Claims submitted to arbitration underthis Article shall be considered to arise out of a commercial relationship or transactionfor the purposes of Article 1 of the New York Convention.</p>
        <p>5. EachContracting Party hereby gives its unconditional consent to the submission of adispute between it and an investor of the other Contracting Party toarbitration in accordance with this Article.</p>
        <p>6. Neitherof the Contracting Parties, which is a party to a dispute, can raise anobjection, at any phase of the arbitration procedure or of the execution of anarbitral award, on account of the fact that the investor, which is the otherparty to the dispute, has received an indemnification covering a part or thewhole of its losses by virtue of an insurance.</p>
        <p>7. Theaward shall be final and binding on the parties to the dispute and shall beexecuted in accordance with national law of the Contracting Party in whoseterritory the award is relied upon, by the competent authorities of theContracting Party by the date indicated in the award.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>1. Disputes between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation and application of this Agreement shall, as far as possible, be settled through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2. If thedispute cannot thus be settled within six (6) months following the date on, whichsuch negotiations were requested by either Contracting Party, it shall at therequest of either Contracting Party be submitted to an Arbitral Tribunal.</p>
        <p>3. Such anArbitral Tribunal shall be constituted for each individual case in thefollowing way. Within two (2) months of the receipt of the request forarbitration, each Contracting Party shall appoint one member of the Tribunal.Those two members shall then select a national of a third State who on approvalby the two Contracting Parties shall be appointed Chairman of the Tribunal. TheChairman shall be appointed within four (4) months from the date of appointmentof the other two members.</p>
        <p>4. If thenecessary appointments have not been made within the periods specified inparagraph 3 of this Article, either Contracting Party may, in the absence ofany other agreement, invite the President of the International Court of Justiceto make the necessary appointments. If the President is a national of eitherContracting Party or is otherwise prevented from discharging the said function,the Member of the International Court of Justice next in seniority who is not anational of either Contracting Party or is not otherwise prevented from dischargingthe said function, shall be invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>5. TheArbitral Tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Thedecisions of the Tribunal shall be final and binding on both ContractingParties. Each Contracting Party shall bear the costs of the member appointed bythat Contracting Party and of its representation in the arbitral proceedings.</p>
        <p>BothContracting Parties shall assume an equal share of the costs of the Chairman,as well as any other costs. The Tribunal may make a different decisionregarding the sharing of the costs. In all other respects, the Arbitral Tribunalshall determine its own rules of procedure.</p>
        <p>6. Issues subject to dispute referred toin paragraph 1 of this Article shall be decided in accordance with theprovisions of this Agreement and the generally recognised principles ofinternational law.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Permits">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall, subjectto its laws and regulations, treat favourably the applications relating toinvestments and grant expeditiously the necessary permits required in itsterritory in connection with investments by investors of the other ContractingParty.</p>
        <p>2. EachContracting Party shall, subject to its laws and regulations, grant temporaryentry and stay and provide any necessary confirming documentation to naturalpersons who are employed from abroad as executives, managers, specialists ortechnical personnel in connection with an investment by an investor of theother Contracting Party, and who are essential for the enterprise as long asthese persons continue to meet the requirements of this paragraph, as well as granttemporary entry and stay to members of their families (spouse and minorchildren) for the same period as to the persons employed.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Application of other rules">
        <p>1. If theprovisions of law of either Contracting Party or obligations underinternational law, existing at present or established hereafter between theContracting Parties in addition to this Agreement, contain a regulation, whethergeneral or specific, entitling investments made by investors of the other ContractingParty to a treatment more favourable than is provided by this Agreement, suchprovisions shall, to the extent that they are more favourable to the investor,prevail over this Agreement.</p>
        <p>2. EachContracting Party shall observe any other obligation it may have with regard toa special agreement on a specific investment of an investor of the otherContracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Application of the agreement">
        <p>ThisAgreement shall apply to all investments made by investors of eitherContracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party, whether madebefore or after the entry into force of this Agreement, but shall not apply toany dispute concerning an investment, which arose or any claim, which wassettled before its entry into force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="14" title="General exceptions">
        <p>1. Nothingin this Agreement shall be construed as preventing a Contracting Party from takingany action necessary for the protection of its essential security interests intime of war or armed conflict, or other emergency in international relations.</p>
        <p>2. Providedthat such measures are not applied in a manner, which would constitute a meansof arbitrary or unjustifiable discrimination by a Contracting Party, or adisguised investment restriction, nothing in this Agreement shall be construedas preventing the Contracting Parties from taking any measure necessary for themaintenance of public order.</p>
        <p>3. The provisions of this Article shall not apply to Paragraph 1(e) of Article 7 of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="15" title="Transparency">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall promptly publish, or otherwise make publicly available, its laws, regulations, procedures and administrative rulings and judicial decisions of general application, as well as international agreements which may affect the investments of investors of the other Contracting Party, in the territory of the former Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>2. Nothingin this Agreement shall require a Contracting Party to furnish or allow access toany confidential or proprietary information, including information concerningparticular investors or investments, the disclosure of which would impede lawenforcement or be contrary to its laws protecting confidentiality or prejudicelegitimate commercial interests of particular investors.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="16" title="Consultations">
        <p>TheContracting Parties shall, at the request of either Contracting Party, holdconsultations for the purpose of reviewing the implementation of this Agreementand studying any issue that may arise from this Agreement. Such consultationsshall be held between the competent authorities of the Contracting Parties in aplace and at a time agreed on through appropriate channels.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="17" title="Entry into force, duration and termination">
        <p>1. TheContracting Parties shall notify each other when their constitutional requirementsfor the entry into force of this Agreement have been fulfilled. The Agreementshall enter into force on the thirtieth day following the date of receipt ofthe last notification.</p>
        <p>2. ThisAgreement shall remain in force for a period of twenty (20) years and shallthereafter remain in force on the same terms until either Contracting Partynotifies the other in writing of its intention to terminate the Agreement intwelve (12) months.</p>
        <p>3. Inrespect of investments made prior to the date of termination of this Agreement,the provisions of Articles 1 to 16 shall remain in force for a further periodof twenty (20) years from the date of termination of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned representatives, being duly authorised thereto, have signed the present Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done in duplicate at Helsinki on 24th of November 2006 in the Finnish, Georgian and English languages, all texts being equally authentic. In case of divergence, the English text shall prevail.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of Finland</p>
      <p>For the Government of Georgia</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
