<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Greece - India BIT (2007)</name>
    <code>T2007-58</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">GRC</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">IND</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2007-04-26</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2008-04-10</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated>2017-03-23</date_terminated>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type>Unilaterally denounced</termination_type>
    <docreference>1800</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>https://dea.gov.in/bipa</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{GRC,IND}_2007-04-26.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>Unilaterally denounced</IT_TERMINATION_TYPE>
    <relation type="IT_OVERLAP" document-code="T1993-87">EC - India Cooperation Agreement (1993)</relation>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE HELLENIC REPUBLIC AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF INDIA ON THE PROMOTION AND RECIPROCAL PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Hellenic Republic and the Government of the Republic of India, hereinafter referred to as the "Contracting Parties"</p>
      <p>DESIRING to intensify investment flows to the mutual benefit of both States on a long term basis,</p>
      <p>HAVING as their objective to create favourable conditions for investments by investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party,</p>
      <p>RECOGNIZING that the promotion and protection of investments, on the basis of this Agreement, will stimulate the business initiative in this field,</p>
      <p>HAVE AGREED AS FOLLOWS:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>1 . "Investment" means every kind of asset invested by an investor of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party in accordance with the legislation of the latter Contracting Party, and in particular, though not exclusively, includes:</p>
        <p>a) Movable and immovable property and any rights in rem such as servitudes, usufructs, mortgages, liens or pledges;</p>
        <p>b) Shares in and stock and debentures of a company and any other form of participation in a company;</p>
        <p>c) Claims to money or to any performance under contract having an economic value, as well as loans connected to an investment;</p>
        <p>d) Intellectual property rights;</p>
        <p>e) Concessions under public law, including concessions to search for, extract or exploit natural resources as well as other rights conferred by law, by contract or by decision of the authority, in accordance with the law;</p>
        <p>A possible change in the form in which the investments have been made does not affect their character as investments.</p>
        <p>2 . "Returns" means the amounts yielded by an investment and in particular, though not exclusively, includes profit, interest, capital gains, dividends, royalties and fees.</p>
        <p>3 . "Investor" means with regard to either Contracting Party:</p>
        <p>a) Natural persons having the nationality of that Contracting Party in accordance with its law;</p>
        <p>b) Legal persons or other entities, including companies, corporations, business associations and partnerships, which are constituted or otherwise duly organised under the laws of that Contracting Party and have their substantive business activities in the territory of that same Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>4 . "Territory" means in respect of:</p>
        <p>a) The Hellenic Republic, the territory under its sovereignty including the territorial sea, as well as maritime areas over which the Hellenic Republic exercises, in conformity with international law, sovereign rights or jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>b) The Republic of India, the territory of the Republic of India including its territorial waters and the air space above it and other maritime zones, including the Exclusive Economic Zone and continental shelf over which the Republic of India has sovereignty, sovereign rights or exclusive jurisdiction in accordance with its laws in force, the 1982 United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea and international law.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Scope of Application">
        <p>This Agreement shall apply to investments in the territory of one Contracting Party, made in accordance with its legislation, by investors of the other Contracting Party, prior to as well as after its entry into force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Promotion and Protection of Investments">
        <p>1 . Each Contracting Party promotes in its territory investments by investors of the other Contracting Party and admits such investments in accordance with its legislation.</p>
        <p>2 . Investments and returns of investors of a Contracting Party shall, at all times, be accorded fair and equitable treatment and shall enjoy full protection and security in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Treatment of Investments">
        <p>1 . Each Contracting Party shall accord to investments, including returns, made in its territory by investors of the other Contracting Party, treatment not less favourable than that which it accords to investments of its own investors or to investments of investors of any third State, whichever is more favourable.</p>
        <p>2 . Each Contracting Party shall accord to investors of the other Contracting Party, as regards the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal of their investments in its territory, treatment not less favourable than that which it accords to its own investors or to investors of any third State, whichever is more favourable.</p>
        <p>3 . The provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article shall not be construed so as to oblige one Contracting Party to extend to the investors of the other Contracting Party the benefit of any treatment, preference or privilege resulting from:</p>
        <p>a) Its participation in any existing or future customs union, economic union, regional economic integration agreement or similar international agreement, or</p>
        <p>b) Any international agreement or any other matter relating wholly or mainly to taxation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Expropriation">
        <p>1 . Investments and returns of investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party, shall not be expropriated, nationalized or subjected to any other measure the effects of which would be tantamount to expropriation or nationalization (hereinafter referred to as "expropriation"), except in the public interest, under due process of law, on a non discriminatory basis and against payment of compensation. Such compensation shall amount to the market value of the investment affected immediately before the actual measure was taken or became public knowledge, whichever is the earlier, it shall include interest from the date of expropriation until the date of payment at a normal commercial rate, it shall be paid without undue delay and shall be effectively realizable and freely transferable in a freely convertible currency.</p>
        <p>2 . The provisions of paragraph 1 of this Article shall also apply where a Contracting Party expropriates the assets of a company which is constituted under the laws in force in any part of its own territory and in which investors of the other Contracting Party own shares.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Compensation for Losses">
        <p>1 . Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party suffer losses owing to war or other armed conflict, a state of national emergency, civil disturbance or other similar events in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall be accorded by the latter Contracting Party treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or other settlement, no less favourable than that which the latter Contracting Party accords to its own investors or to investors of any third State, whichever is more favourable.</p>
        <p>2 . Without prejudice to paragraph 1 of this Article, investors of one Contracting Party who, in any of the situations referred to in that paragraph suffer losses in the territory of the other Contracting Party resulting from:</p>
        <p>a) Requisitioning of their investment or part thereof by the latter's forces or authorities,</p>
        <p>Or</p>
        <p>b) Destruction of their investment or part thereof by the latter's forces or authorities, which was not required by the necessity of the situation,</p>
        <p>Shall be accorded restitution or adequate compensation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Transfers">
        <p>1 . Each Contracting Party shall ensure to the investors of the other Contracting Party, the free transfer of all payments relating to an investment.</p>
        <p>The transfers shall be effected without undue delay, in a freely convertible currency, at the market rate of exchange applicable on the date of transfer.</p>
        <p>2 . Such transfers shall include in particular, though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>a) Capital and additional amounts to maintain or increase the investment;</p>
        <p>b) Returns;</p>
        <p>c) Repayments made pursuant to a loan agreement in connection with an investment;</p>
        <p>d) Proceeds of sale or liquidation of the whole or any part of the investment;</p>
        <p>e) Compensation under Articles 5 and 6;</p>
        <p>f) Earnings and other remuneration of personnel engaged from abroad in connection with an investment;</p>
        <p>g) Payments arising out of the settlement of a dispute.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Subrogation">
        <p>1 . If the investments of an investor of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party are insured against non-commercial risks under a legal system of guarantee, any subrogation of the insurer into the rights of the said investor pursuant to the terms of such insurance shall be recognized by the other Contracting Party, without prejudice to the rights of the investor under Article 10 of this Agreement.</p>
        <p>2 . The insurer shall not be entitled to exercise any rights other than the rights which the investor would have been entitled to exercise.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Settlement of Disputes between the Contracting Parties">
        <p>1 . Any dispute between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or application of this Agreement shall, if possible, be settled by negotiations, through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2 . If the dispute cannot thus be settled within six months from the beginning of the negotiations, it shall, upon request of either Contracting Party be submitted to an arbitration tribunal.</p>
        <p>3 . The arbitration tribunal shall be constituted ad hoc as follows: Each Contracting Party shall appoint one arbitrator and these two arbitrators shall agree upon a national of a third State as chairman. The arbitrators shall be appointed within three months, the chairman within five months from the date on which either Contracting Party has informed the other Contracting Party that it intends to submit the dispute to an arbitration tribunal.</p>
        <p>4 . If within the periods specified in paragraph 3 of this Article the necessary appointments have not been made, either Contracting Party may, in the absence of any other agreement, invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointments. If the President of the Court is a national of either Contracting Party or if he is otherwise prevented from discharging the said function, the Vice-President or if he too is a national of either Contracting Party or is otherwise prevented from discharging the said function, the Member of the Court next in seniority, who is not a national of either Contracting Party, shall be invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>5 . The arbitration tribunal shall decide on the basis of respect of the law, including particularly this Agreement as well as the generally acknowledged rules and principles of international law.</p>
        <p>6 . Unless the Contracting Parties decide otherwise, the tribunal shall determine its own procedure. The tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Such decision shall be final and binding on the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>7 . Each Contracting Party shall bear the cost of the arbitrator appointed by itself and of its representation. The cost of the chairman as well as the other costs will be born in equal parts by the Contracting Parties. The tribunal may, however, in its decision direct that a higher proportion of costs shall be born by one of the two Contracting Parties and this award shall be binding on both Contracting Parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Settlement of Disputes between an Investor and a Contracting Party">
        <p>1 . Disputes between an investor of a Contracting Party and the other Contracting Party concerning an obligation of the latter under this Agreement, in relation to an investment of the former, shall, if possible, be settled by the disputing parties in an amicable way.</p>
        <p>2 . If such disputes cannot be settled within six months from the date either party requested amicable settlement, the investor concerned may submit the dispute for resolution, either:</p>
        <p>a) To the competent courts of the Contracting Party in the territory of which the investment has been made, or</p>
        <p>b) To international arbitration.</p>
        <p>3 . Where the dispute is referred to international arbitration the investor concerned may submit the dispute to:</p>
        <p>a) The International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes, under the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of other States, opened for signature at Washington D.C. on 18 March 1965, for arbitration or conciliation if both Contracting Parties are parties to the said Convention or</p>
        <p>b) To the International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes for arbitration or conciliation under its Additional Facility Rules or</p>
        <p>c) An ad hoc arbitral tribunal to be established under the arbitration rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law (UNCITRAL).</p>
        <p>4 . The arbitral tribunal shall decide the dispute in accordance with the provisions of this Agreement and the applicable rules and principles of international law. The awards of arbitration shall be final and binding on both parties to the dispute. Each Contracting Party shall carry out without delay any such award and shall provide in its territory for the enforcement of such award, which shall then be enforced in accordance with domestic law.</p>
        <p>5 . During arbitration proceedings or the enforcement of the award, the Contracting Party involved in the dispute shall not raise the objection that the investor of the other Contracting Party has received compensation under an insurance contract in respect of all or part of the damage.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Entry and Sojourn of Personnel">
        <p>Subject to each Contracting Party's laws, regulations and procedures relating to the entry, stay and work of natural persons:</p>
        <p>a) A Contracting Party shall examine in good faith requests by investors of the other Party, and key personnel who are employed by such investors, to enter and remain temporarily in its territory to engage in activities connected with the investments, including the provision of advice or key technical services.</p>
        <p>b) Companies which are legally constituted under the applicable laws and regulations of one Contracting Party, and which are investments of investors of the other Contracting Party, shall be permitted to engage top managerial and technical personnel of their choice, regardless of nationality.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Applicable Laws">
        <p>1 . Except as otherwise provided in this Agreement, all investments shall be governed by the laws in force in the territory of the Contracting Party in which such investments are made.</p>
        <p>2 . Nothing in this Agreement precludes the host Contracting Party from taking action for the protection of its essential security interests or in circumstances of extreme emergency in accordance with its laws applied on a non discriminatory basis.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Application of other Rules">
        <p>If the provisions of law of either Contracting Party or obligations under international law existing at present or established hereafter between the Contracting Parties in addition to this Agreement, contain a regulation, whether general or specific, entitling investments by investors of the other Contracting Party to a treatment more favourable than is provided for by this Agreement, such regulation shall, to the extent that it is more favourable, prevail over this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="14" title="Consultations">
        <p>Representatives of the Contracting Parties shall, whenever necessary, hold consultations on any matter affecting the implementation of this Agreement. These consultations shall be held on the proposal of one of the Contracting Parties at a place and at a time to be agreed upon through diplomatic channels.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="15" title="Entry Into Force, Duration, Termination">
        <p>1 . This Agreement shall enter into force thirty days after the date on which the Contracting Parties have exchanged written notifications informing each other that the procedures required by their respective laws to this end have been completed. It shall remain in force for a period of ten years from that date.</p>
        <p>2 . Unless notice of termination has been given by either Contracting Party at least one year before the date of expiry of its validity, this Agreement shall thereafter be extended tacitly for periods of ten years, each Contracting Party reserving the right to terminate the Agreement upon notice of at least one year before the date of expiry of its current period of validity.</p>
        <p>3 . In respect of investments made prior to the date of termination of this Agreement, the foregoing Articles shall continue to be effective for a further period of ten years from that date.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>Done in duplicate at Athens, on 26th April 2007, in the Greek, Hindi and English languages, all texts being equally authentic.</p>
      <p>In case of divergence the English text shall prevail.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Hellenic Republic</p>
      <p>CHRISTOS FOLIAS</p>
      <p>DEPUTY MINISTER OF ECONOMY AND FINANCE</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of India</p>
      <p>BHASKAR BALAKRISHNAN</p>
      <p>AMBASSADOR OF INDIA</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
