<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Bahrain - Belarus BIT (2002)</name>
    <code>T2002-20</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">BHR</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">BLR</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2002-10-26</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2008-06-16</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>335</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>http://www.mof.gov.bh</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{BHR,BLR}_2002-10-26.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE KINGDOM OF BAHRAIN AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF BELARUS ON THE PROMOTION AND RECIPROCAL PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Kingdom of Bahrain and the Government of the Republic of Belarus, hereinafter referred to as the "Contracting Parties",</p>
      <p>Desiring to intensify their economic cooperation for the mutual benefit of both States.</p>
      <p>Intending to create favourable conditions for investments made by investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party,</p>
      <p>Recognizing that the promotion and reciprocal protection of investments under this Agreement will stimulate business initiatives in both States</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement,</p>
        <p>1.  The term "investment" means every kind of asset invested by investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contacting Party in accordance with the laws and regulations of the latter and shall include in particular, though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>i)  movable and immovable property and any other property rights such as mortgages, liens, pledges and any other similar rights as defined in accordance with the laws and regulations of the Contracting Party in which territory the property is situated;</p>
        <p>ii)  shares in, stocks, debentures and any other forms of participation in companies;</p>
        <p>iii)  claims to money or to any performance under contract having economic value;</p>
        <p>iv) Intellectual and industrial property rights (such as copyrights, patents, utility models, industrial designs or models, trade or service marks, trade names, indications of origin), "know-how" and "goodwill" and any other similar rights recognized by both Contracting Parties in accordance with their respective laws and regulations;</p>
        <p>v)  concessions conferred by law of the Contracting Party in which territory investments are made, including concessions to search for, cultivate, extract and exploit natural resources.</p>
        <p>vi) Any change of the form in which assets are invested or reinvested shall not affect their character as investments, provided that such a change does not contradict the laws and regulations of the relevant Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>2.  The term "returns" means the amounts yielded by an investment and includes, in particular though not exclusively, profit, dividends, interests, capital gains, royalties and fees.</p>
        <p>3.  The term "investor" means with regard to either Contracting Party:</p>
        <p>i) Natural persons who are the nationals of one Contracting Party in accordance with its law, and who make investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>ii) Legal persons, including companies, business associations and other partnerships organizations, which are constituted or otherwise duly organized under the laws of that Contracting Party and have their main office in the territory of that Contracting Party and which make nvestments in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>4.  The term "territory" in respect of either Contracting Party means the territory of the State of the Contracting Party concerned including land, internal waters, territorial sea, seabed and/subsoil and any exclusive economic zone over which the Contracting Party have sovereign rights or jurisdiction in accordance with internatmnal law.</p>
        <p>5.  The terms "laws and regulations", "law(s)" , "nationals" in respect of either Contracting Party mean the law and regulations of the State of the Contracting Party concerned and nationals of the State of the Contracting Party concerned accordingly.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and protection of investments">
        <p>1.  Each Contracting Party shall promote and create favourable conditions for investors of the other Contracting Party to make investments in its territory, and shall admit such investments in accordance with its laws and regulations.</p>
        <p>2.  Investments of investors of each Contracting Party shall at all times be accorded fair and equitable treatment and shall enjoy full legal protection in the territory of the other Contracting Party under this Agreement. Neither Contracting Party shall in any way impair by unreasonable or discriminatory measures the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal of investments in its territory of investors of the other Contracting Party. Each Contracting Party shall observe any obligation it may have entered into with regard to investments of investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="National and most favoured nation treatment">
        <p>1.  Each Contracting Party shall accord in its territory to investments or returns of investors of the other Contracting Party, treatment no less favourable that that which it accords to investment or returns of its own investors or to investment or returns of investors of any third State.</p>
        <p>2.  Each Contracting Party shall accord in its territory to investors of the other Contracting Party, as regards management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal of their investment,treatment not less favourable than that which it accords to its own investors or to investors of any third State.</p>
        <p>3. The provisions of this Article shall not be construed so as to oblige one Contracting Party to extend to the investors of the other Contracting Party the benefit of any treatment, preference or privilege resulting from:</p>
        <p>i) Any existing or future free trade area, custom union, common market, or</p>
        <p>ii) Similar international agreement, inclusing other forms of regional economic cooperation or similar international agreement, to which either of ther Contracting Parties is or may become a party, or</p>
        <p>iii) Any international agreement which is related wholly or mainly to taxation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Expropriation">
        <p>1.  Investment of investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall not be requisitioned, expropriated, nationalized or subjected to measures having effect equivalent to expropriation (hereinafter referred to as expropriation) except for a public purpose in accordance with due process of law, on a non-discriminatory basis and against prompt, adequate and effective compensation.</p>
        <p>2.  Such compensation shall amount to the actual value of the investment expropriated immediately before the expropriation or before the impending expropriation became public knowledge, whichever is the earlier. The actual value shall amount in accordance with adopted international practice and shall include interest calculated on the LIBOR basis from the date of expropriation until the date of payment with regard to the currency in which the investment is made. The compensation shall be made without delay in the currency in which investment has been made, shall be effectively realizable and freely transferable.</p>
        <p>3.  The investor who has suffered losses shall have a right, under the law of the Contracting Party making the expropiation to prompt review, by a judicial or other independent authority of that Contracting Party, of his or its case and of the valuation of his or its investment in accordance with the principles set out in this Article.</p>
        <p>4.  Where a Contracting Party expropriates the assets of a company which is incorporated or constituted under the laws in force in any part of its territory, and in which investors of the other Contracting Party own shares, it shall ensure that the provisions of paragraph 1 of this Article are applied so as to guarantee, prompt, adequate and effective compensation in respect of their investment to such investors of the other Contracting Party who are owners of those shares.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Compensation for losses">
        <p>1.  Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party suffer losses owing to war or other armed conflict, revolution, a State of national emergency, revolt, insurrection or riot in the territory of the latter Contracting Party shall be accorded by the latter Contracting Party treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or other settlement, no less favourable than that which the latter Contracting Party accords to its own investors or to investors of any third State. Resulting payments shall be freely transferable.</p>
        <p>2.  Without prejudice to the first paragraph herein, investors of one Contracting Party who in any of the situations referred to in that paragraph suffer losses in the territory of the other Contracting Party resulting from:</p>
        <p>i)  the requisitioning of their property by its forces or authorities; or</p>
        <p>ii)  the destruction of their property by its forces or authorities, which was not caused in combat action or was not required by the necessity of the situation shall be accorded restitution or adequate compensation. Any resulting payments shall be freely transferable.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Free transfer">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall guarantee to investors of the other Contracting Party, after they have fulfilled all their fiscal obligations, the free transfer of payments relating to their investments, particularly, though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>i)  returns as defined in paragraph 2, Article 1 of this Agreement;</p>
        <p>ii)  repayments of loans recognized by both Contracting Parties as investment;</p>
        <p>iii)  amounts assigned to cover expenses relating to the management of the investment;</p>
        <p>iv) Capital and additional amounts necessary for the maintenance or development of the investment;</p>
        <p>v)  proceeds from the sale or partial or total liquidation of the investment, including possible increment values;</p>
        <p>v) Compensation under Articles 4 and 5 of this Agreement.</p>
        <p>2. The transfers mentioned in this Article shall be made without delay in a freely convertible currency at the market rate of exchange applicable on the date of transfer pursuant to the exchange regulations in force of the Contracting Party from which territory the transfer is made.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Subrogation">
        <p>1.  If one Contracting Party or its designated agency makes a payment under an indemnity given in respect of an investment in the territory of the other Contracting Party, the latter Contracting Party shall recognize the assignment to the former Contracting Party or its designated agency by law or by local transaction of all the rights and claims of the party indemnified and that the former Contracting Party or its designated agency is entitled to exercise such rights and enforce such claims by virtue of subrogation to the same extend as the party indemnified.</p>
        <p>2.  The former Contracting Party or its designated agency shall be entitled in all circumstances to the same treatment in respect of the rights and claims acquired by virtue of the assignment of any payments received in pursuance of those rights and claims as the party indemnified was entitled to receive by virtue of this Agreement in respect of the investment concerned and its related returns.</p>
        <p>3.  Any payments received in non-convertible currency by the former Contracting Party or its designated agency in pursuance of the rights and claims acquired shall be freely available to the former Contracting Party for the purpose of meeting any expenditure incurred in the territory of the latter Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>1. Disputes between the Contracting Parties regarding the interpretation or application of this Agreement shall, as far as possible, be settled by negotiation through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2. If the Contracting Parties cannot settle any dispute as defined in paragraph 1 of this Article within six months after the beginning of negotiations, the dispute shall, upon request of either Contracting Party, be submitted to an arbitral tribunal, in accordance with the provisions of this Article.</p>
        <p>3.  The arbitral tribunal shall be constituted ad hoc as follows: each Contracting Party shall appoint one arbitrator and these two arbitrators shall agree upon a national of a third country as Chairman to be appointed by the two Contracting Parties. The arbitrators shall be appointed within two months and the Chairman within three months from the date on which either Contracting Party has informed the other of its intention to submit the dispute to an arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>4.  If within the period specified in paragraph 3 of this Article the necessary appointments have not been made, either Contracting Party may, in the absence of any other agreement, invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointments. If the President is a national of either Contracting Party or if he is otherwise prevented from discharging the said function, the Vice-President shall be invited to make the necessary appointments. If the Vice-President is a national of either Contracting Party or if he is also prevented from discharging the said function, the Member of the International Court of Justice next in seniority who is not a national of either Contracting Party shall be invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>5.  The Chairman of the arbitral tribunal shall be a national of a third State with which both Contracting Parties have diplomatic relations.</p>
        <p>6.  The arbitral tribunal established under this Article shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Such decision shall be final and binding on both Contracting Parties. Each Contracting Party shall bear the cost of its own member of the tribunal and of its representation in the arbitral proceedings. The cost of the Chairman and any other costs shall be borne in equal parts by the Contracting Parties. The tribunal may, however, to determine a different decision regarding the costs. The tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Settlement of disputes between a contracting party and an investor of the other contracting party">
        <p>1. Any dispute which may arise between an investor of a Contracting Party and the other Contracting Party concerning the investment of this investor, shall be the subject to consultations between the parties to the dispute for the purpose of solving the case amicably.</p>
        <p>If these consultations do not result in a solution within six months from the date of request for settlement, the investor may submit the dispute, at his choice, for settlement to:</p>
        <p>i)  the competent court of the Contracting Party in the territory of which the investment has been made; or</p>
        <p>ii)  the International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID) established by the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of Other States, opened for signature in Washington on March 18 th, 1965; or</p>
        <p>iii)  an ad hoc arbitral tribunal, which, unless otherwise agreed upon by the parties to the dispute, shall be, established under the arbitration rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law (UNCITRAL).</p>
        <p>2.  The decisions of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and binding on either party.</p>
        <p>3.  During the arbitration proceedings or the enforcement of the award, the Contracting Party involved in the dispute shall not allege as defence its sovereignty or the fact that the investor of the other Contracting Party 7 has received compensation under an insurance contract in respect of all or a part of his or its losses.</p>
        <p>4.  Neither Contracting Party shall pursue to settle through diplomatic channels a dispute submitted to international arbitration unless the other Contracting Party does not abide by and comply with the award reached by an arbitral tribunal.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Application of other rules">
        <p>If the provisions of law of either Contracting Party or obligations under intemational law existing at present or established hereafter between the Contracting Parties in addition to this Agreement contain rules, whether general or specific, entitling investments by investors of the other Contracting Party to a treatment more favourable than is provided for by the present Agreement, such rules shall to the extent that they are more favourable prevail over this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Pre-agreement investments">
        <p>This Agreement shall be applied to all investments, made by investors of one of the Contracting Parties in the territory of the other Contracting Party in accordance with the respective laws and regulations, prior to as well as after the entry into force of this Agreement, but shall not be applied to any dispute concerning investments that may have arisen before the entry into force of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Consultations">
        <p>Representatives of the Contracting Parties shall, whenever necessary, hold consultations on any matter affecting the implementation of this Agreement. These consultations shall be held on the proposal of one of the Contracting Parties at a place and at time to be agreed upon through diplomatic channels.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Entry into force, duration and termination">
        <p>This Agreement shall enter into force thirty (30) days after the Contracting Parties notify each other in writing that their respective internal constitutional requirements, necessary for the entry into force of this Agreement, have been fulfilled.</p>
        <p>This Agreement shall remain in force for a period often (10) years. Thereafter it shall continue to be in force for the same periods unless the expiration of twelve (12) months from the date on which either Contracting Party shall give a written notice of termination to the other Contracting Party. In respect of investment madxe prior to the date of termination of this Agreement the provisions of Articles 1 to 12 shall remain in force for a further period of ten (10) years from the date of termination of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>In witness whereof, the undersigned representatives duly authorized thereto, have signed the present Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done at Manama this 26th day of October 2002, in two originals in the Arabic, Russian and English languages, each text being equally authentic. In case of any divergence in interpretation, the English text shall prevail.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Kingdom of Bahrain</p>
      <p>Abdulla Hassan Saif</p>
      <p>Minister of Finance and National Economy</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of Belarus</p>
      <p>Mikhail Khvostov</p>
      <p>Minister of Foreign Affairs</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
