<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Greece - Viet Nam BIT (2008)</name>
    <code>T2008-48</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">GRC</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">VNM</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2008-10-13</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2011-12-08</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en,el</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>1823</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{GRC,VNM}_2008-10-13.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en,el</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Agreement between the Government of the Greek Republic and the Government of the Socialist Republic of Vietnam on the promotion and mutual protection of investments</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Greek Republic and the Government of the Socialist Republic of Viet Nam, hereinafter referred to as "the Parties",</p>
      <p>DESIRING tointensify their economic cooperation to the mutual benefit of both States on along term basis,</p>
      <p>HAVING astheir objective to create favourable conditions for investments by investors ofeither Contracting Party in the territory of the other Party,</p>
      <p>RECOGNIZINGthat the promotion and protection of investments, on the basis of this Agreement,will stimulate the initiative in this field,</p>
      <p>HAVE AGREEDAS FOLLOWS:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>1.  "Investment" means every kind of asset invested by an investor of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party in accordance with the legislation of the latter Contracting Party and includes in particular, but not exclusively:</p>
        <p>a) movableand immovable property and any other property rights;</p>
        <p>b) sharesin and stock and debentures of a company and any other form of participation ina company,</p>
        <p>c) claimsto money or to any performance under contract having an economic value, as well asloans connected to an investment, except for</p>
        <p>i) claimsto money that arise solely from commercial contracts for the sale of goods and services;</p>
        <p>ii) the extensionof credit in connection with a commercial transaction, such as trade financing.</p>
        <p>d)intellectual property rights;</p>
        <p>e)concessions under public law, including concessions to search for, cultivate,extract or exploit natural resources as well as other rights conferred by law,by contract or by decision ofthe authority, in accordance with the law.</p>
        <p>A possiblechange in the form in which the investments have been made does not affecttheir character as investments.</p>
        <p>2."Returns" means the amounts yielded by an investment and inparticular, though not exclusively, includes profit, interest, capital gains,dividends, royalties, and fees.</p>
        <p>3."Investor" means with regard to either Contracting Party:</p>
        <p>a) naturalpersons having the nationality of that Contracting Party in accordance with itslaw;</p>
        <p>b) legalpersons or other entities, including companies, corporations, business associationsand partnerships; which are constituted or otherwise duly organised under thelaws of that Contracting Party and have their effective economic activities inthe territory of that same Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>4."Territory" means:</p>
        <p>a) Withrespect to the Hellenic Republic, the territory under its sovereignty includingthe territorial sea, as well as maritime areas over which the Hellenic Republicexercises, in conformity with international law, sovereign rights orjurisdiction.</p>
        <p>b) Withrespect to the Socialist Republic of Viet Nam, its land territory, islands,internal waters,territorial sea and airspace above them, the maritime areas beyond territorialsea including seabed and subsoil thereof over which the Socialist Republic ofViet Nam exercises sovereignty,sovereign rights and jurisdiction in accordance with national legislationand international law.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Scope of application">
        <p>ThisAgreement shall apply to investments in the territory of one Contracting Party,made in accordance with its legislation, including any registration or approvalrequirements, by investors of the other Contracting Party, prior to as well asafter its entry into force.</p>
        <p>However,this Agreement shall not apply to any dispute that arose or any claim that wassettled before its entry into force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Promotion and protection of investments">
        <p>1. EachContracting Party promotes in its territory investments by investors of theother Contracting Party and admits such investments in accordance with itslegislation.</p>
        <p>2.Investments and returns of investors of a Contracting Party shall, at alltimes, be accorded fair and equitable treatment and shall enjoy full protectionand security in the territory of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>EachContracting Party shall ensure that the management, maintenance, use, enjoymentor disposal, in its territory, of investments by investors of the otherContracting Party, is not in any way impaired by unjustifiable ordiscriminatory measures.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Treatment of investments">
        <p>1. EachContracting Party shall accord to investments, including returns, by investorsof the other Contracting Party, once established in its territory, treatment notless favourable than that which it accords to investments of its own investorsor to investments of investors of any third State, whichever is morefavourable.</p>
        <p>2. EachContracting Party shall accord to investors of the other Contracting Party, asregards the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal of theirinvestments in its territory, treatment not less favourable than that which itaccords to its own investors or to investors of any third State, whichever ismore favourable.</p>
        <p>3.Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article, the Government of theSocialist Republic of Viet Nam may apply exceptions to the principle ofnational treatment, in accordance with its legislation and within the frameworkof its development policy.</p>
        <p>4. Theprovisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article shall not be construed so asto oblige one Contracting Party to extend to the investors of the otherContracting Party the benefit of any treatment, preference or privilegeresulting from:</p>
        <p>a) itsparticipation in any or future customs union, economic union, regional economicintegration agreement or similar international agreement; or</p>
        <p>b) any internationalagreement or arrangement or any domestic legislation relating wholly or mainlyto taxation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Expropriation">
        <p>1.Investments and returns of investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party, shall not be expropriated,nationalized or subjected to any other measure the effects of which would betantamount to expropriation or nationalization (hereinafter referred to as"expropriation"), except in the public interest, under due process oflaw, on a non discriminatory basis and against payment of prompt, adequate andeffective compensation. Such compensation shall amount to the market value of theinvestment affected immediately before the actual measure was taken or becamepublic knowledge, whichever is the earlier and shall be freely transferable ina freely convertible currency.</p>
        <p>2.Notwithstandingparagraph 1, with respect to the Socialist Republic of Viet Nam, any measure ofexpropriation relating to land shall be subject to its laws and regulationsconcerning the terms of such expropriation and the payment of compensation.</p>
        <p>3. Theprovisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article shall also apply where aContracting Party expropriates the assets of a company which is constitutedunder the laws in force in any part of its own territory and in which investorsof the other Contracting Party own shares.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Compensation for losses">
        <p>1.Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of theother Contracting Party suffer losses owing to war or other armed conflict, astate of national emergency, civil disturbance or other similar events in theterritory of the other Contracting Party shall be accorded by the latterContracting Party treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensationor other settlement, no less favourable than that which the latter ContractingParty accords to its own investors or to investors of my third State, whicheveris more favourable.</p>
        <p>2. Withoutprejudice to paragraph 1 of this Article, investors of one Contracting Partywho, in any of the situations referred to in that paragraph suffer losses inthe territory of the other Contracting Party resulting from:</p>
        <p>a)requisitioning of their investment or part thereof by the latter's forces orauthorities, or</p>
        <p>b)destruction of their investment or part thereof by the latter's forces orauthorities, which was notrequired by the necessity of the situation,</p>
        <p>shall beaccorded restitution or compensation which in either case shall be prompt,adequate and effective.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Transfers">
        <p>1. EachContracting Party shall permit, in respect of investments of investors of theother Contracting Party, the unrestricted transfer of all payments relating toan investment.</p>
        <p>Thetransfers shall be effected without delay, in a freely convertible currency, atthe market rate of exchange applicable on the date of transfer, and inaccordance with any procedures or formalities applicable in the hostContracting Party.</p>
        <p>2. Suchtransfers shall include in particular, though not exclusively:</p>
        <p>a) capitaland additional amounts to maintain or increase the investment;</p>
        <p>b) returns;</p>
        <p>c) funds inrepayment of loans;</p>
        <p>d) proceedsof sale or liquidation of the whole or any part of the investment;</p>
        <p>e)compensation under Articles 5 and 6;</p>
        <p>f) paymentsarising out of the settlement of a dispute.</p>
        <p>3.Notwithstanding Paragraphs 1 and 2, a Contracting Party may prevent or delay a transferthrough the equitable, non-discriminatory, and good faith application of itslaws and regulations relating to:</p>
        <p>(a)bankruptcy, insolvency, or the protection of the rights of creditors;</p>
        <p>(b)issuing, trading, or dealing in securities, futures, options, or derivatives;</p>
        <p>(c)criminal or penal offences and the recovery of the proceeds of crime;</p>
        <p>(d)financial reporting or record keeping of transfers when necessary to assist law enforcementor financial regulatory authorities;</p>
        <p>(e)ensuring compliance with orders or judgments in judicial or administrative proceedings;</p>
        <p>(t) taxation;</p>
        <p>(g) socialsecurity, public retirement, or compulsory savings schemes; and</p>
        <p>(h)severance entitlements d employees.</p>
        <p>4. In caseof serious balance of payments difficulties or the threat thereof, eachContracting Party may temporarily restrict transfers, provided that such aContracting Party implements measures or a programme in accordance with theInternational Monetary Fund standards. These restrictions would be imposed onan equitable, non-discriminatory and in good faith basis.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Subrogation">
        <p>If theinvestments of an investor of one Contracting Party in the territory of theother Contracting Party are insured against non-commercial risks under a legalsystem of guarantee, any subrogation of the insurer into the rights of the saidinvestor pursuant to the terms of such insurance shall be recognized by theother Contracting Party, without prejudice to the rights of the investor underArticle 10 of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Settlement of disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>1. Anydispute between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation orapplication of this Agreement shall, if possible, be settled by negotiations,through diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>2. If thedispute cannot thus be settled within six months from the beginning of thenegotiations, it shall, upon request of either Contracting Party be submittedto an arbitration tribunal.</p>
        <p>3. Thearbitration tribunal shall be constituted ad hoc as follows: Each ContractingParty shall appoint one arbitrator and these two arbitrators shall agree upon anational of a third State as chairman. The arbitrators shall be appointedwithin three months, the chairman within five months from the on which eitherContracting Party has informed the other Contracting Party that it intends tosubmit the dispute to an arbitration tribunal.</p>
        <p>4. Ifwithin the periods specified in paragraph 3 of this Article the necessaryappointments have not been made, either Contracting may, in the absence of any otheragreement, invite the President of the International Court of Justice to makethe necessary appointments. If the President of the Court is a national ofeither Contracting Party or if he is otherwise prevented from discharging thesaid function, the Vice-President or if he too is a national of either ContractingParty or is otherwise prevented from discharging the said function, the Memberof the Court next in seniority, who is not a national of either ContractingParty, shall be invited to make the necessary appointments.</p>
        <p>5. Thearbitration tribunal shall decide on the basis of respect of the law, includingparticularly this Agreement and other relevant agreements between theContracting Parties, as well as the generally acknowledged rules and principlesof international law.</p>
        <p>6. Unlessthe Contracting Parties decide otherwise, the tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
        <p>Thetribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Such decision shallbe final and binding on the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>7. EachParty shall bear the cost of the arbitrator appointed by itself and of its representation.The cost of the chairman as well as the other costs will be born in equal partsby the Contracting Parties. The tribunal may, however, in its decision directthat a higher proportion of costs shall be borne by one of the two Parties andthis award shall be binding on both Contracting Parties.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Settlement of disputes between an investor and a contracting party">
        <p>1. Disputesbetween an investor of a Contracting Party and the other Contracting Party concerningan obligation of the latter under this Agreement, in relation to an investmentof the former, shall, if possible, be settled by the disputing parties in anamicable way.</p>
        <p>2. If suchdisputes cannot be settled within six months from the date either partyrequested amicable settlement, the investor concerned may submit the disputefor resolution, either:</p>
        <p>a) to thecompetent courts of the Contracting Party in the territory of which the investmenthas been made, or</p>
        <p>b) inaccordance with any applicable previously dispute settlement procedure, or</p>
        <p>c) to internationalarbitration.</p>
        <p>Once the investor has submitted the dispute under any of the procedures stipulatedabove, that choice is final.</p>
        <p>3. Wherethe dispute is referred to international arbitration die investor concerned maysubmit the dispute to:</p>
        <p>a) the InternationalCentre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (the "Centre"),</p>
        <p>establishedunder the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States andNationals of Other States, opened for signature at Washington D.C. on 18 March 1965(the "Washington Convention") , arbitration or conciliation, if both ContractingParties are parties to the Washington Convention or</p>
        <p>b) theAdditional Facility of the Centre, if only one of the Contracting Parties is a signatoryto the Washington Convention, for arbitration or conciliation, or</p>
        <p>c) an adhoc arbitral tribunal to be established under the arbitration rules of theUnited NationsCommission on International Trade Law (U.N.C.I.T.R.A.L.).</p>
        <p>EachContracting Party hereby consents to the submission of such dispute tointernational arbitration.</p>
        <p>A naturalperson possessing the nationality of a Contracting Party may not pursue a claimagainst that Party under this paragraph.</p>
        <p>4. Thearbitral tribunal shall decide the dispute in accordance with the provisions ofthis Agreement, the law of the Contracting Party which is party to the dispute,(including its rules on the conflict of laws) and such rules of internationallaw as may be applicable. The awards of arbitration shall be final and bindingon both parties to the dispute. Each Contracting Party shall carry out withoutundue delay any such award and shall provide in its territory for the enforcementof such award.</p>
        <p>5. Duringarbitration proceedings or the enforcement of the award, the Contracting Partyinvolved in the dispute shall not raise the objection that the investor of theother Contracting Party has received compensation under an insurance contractin respect of all or part of the damage.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Application of other rules">
        <p>1. If theprovisions of law of either Contracting Party or obligations under internationallaw existing at present or established hereafter between the ContractingParties in addition to this Agreement, contain a regulation, whether general orspecific, entitling investments by investors of the other Contacting Party to atreatment more favourable than is provided for by this Agreement, suchregulation shall, to the extent that it is more favourable, prevail over this Agreement.</p>
        <p>2. EachContracting Party shall observe any other obligation it may have entered intowith regard to a specific investment of an investor of the other ContractingParty.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Consultation">
        <p>Representativesof the Contracting Parties shall, whenever necessary, hold consultations on anymatter affecting the implementation of this Agreement. These consultationsshall be held on the proposal of one of the Contracting Parties at a place andat a time to be agreed upon through diplomatic channels.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Entry into force - duration - termination">
        <p>1. ThisAgreement shall enter into force thirty days after the date on which theContracting Parties have exchanged notifications informing each other that theprocedures required by their respective laws for its entry into force have beencompleted. It shall remain in force for a period of ten years from that date.</p>
        <p>2. Unlessnotice of termination has been given by either Contracting Party at least oneyear before the date of expiry of its validity, this Agreement shall thereafterbe extended automatically for periods often years, each Contracting Partyreserving the right to terminate the Agreement upon notice of at least one yearbefore the date of expiry of its current period of validity.</p>
        <p>3. Inrespect of investments made prior to the date of termination of this Agreement,the foregoing Articles shall continue to be effective for a further period of tenyears from that date.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>Done induplicate at Hanoi, on October 13th, 2008, in the Greek, Vietnamese and Englishlanguages, all texts being equally authentic.</p>
      <p>In case of divergencethe English text shall prevail.</p>
      <p>FOR THEGOVERNMENT OF THE HELLENIC REPUBLIC</p>
      <p>PETROSDOUKAS</p>
      <p>DEPUTYMINISTER FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS</p>
      <p>FOR THEGOVERNMENT OF THE SOCIALIST REPUBLIC OF VIET NAM</p>
      <p>NGUYEN BICHDAT</p>
      <p>DEPUTYMINISTER OF PLANNING AND INVESTMENT</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
