<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Russian Federation - Syrian Arab Republic BIT (2005)</name>
    <code>T2005-86</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">RUS</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">SYR</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2005-01-26</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2007-07-13</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">ru</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>2854</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>unctad</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{RUS,SYR}_2005-01-26.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>ru</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE RUSSIAN FEDERATION AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE SYRIAN ARAB REPUBLIC ON THE PROMOTION AND MUTUAL PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Russian Federation and the Government of the Syrian Arab Republic, hereinafter referred to as the Contracting Parties,</p>
      <p>Desiring to create favorable conditions for investments of investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party,</p>
      <p>Recognizing that the promotion and reciprocal protection of investments under this Agreement will stimulate the flow of capital and promote the development of mutually beneficial trade-economic and scientific-technical cooperation,</p>
      <p>We have agreed to the following:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement, the following definitions shall mean:</p>
        <p>a)  "investor" (in respect of each of the Contracting Parties):</p>
        <p>Any natural person who is a citizen of the state of the</p>
        <p>Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>Any legal entity created or organized under the laws of that Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>b)  "investment" - all kinds of assets, invested by an investor of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party in accordance with the legislation of the latter state, and in particular:</p>
        <p>Movable and immovable property;</p>
        <p>Shares, stocks and other forms of participation in commercial capital</p>
        <p>Organizations;</p>
        <p>A claim on the funds invested to create economic value or that have an economic value and associated with an investment;</p>
        <p>Exclusive rights to intellectual property (copyrights, patents, industrial designs, models, trademarks and service marks, technology, information having a commercial value, and know-how);</p>
        <p>Right to engage in entrepreneurial activity, conferred by law or contract, including, in particular, related to the exploration, development, production and exploitation of natural resources.</p>
        <p>No change in the form of investment does not affect their qualification as investments if such change does not contradict the legislation of the State of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investments were made;</p>
        <p>c)  "income" - money received from the investment and, in particular, profits, dividends, interest, royalties and other fees;</p>
        <p>d)  "national territory of a Contracting Party":</p>
        <p>for the Russian Federation - the Russian Federation, as well as its exclusive economic zone and continental shelf, defined in accordance with the UN Convention on the Law of the Sea (1982);</p>
        <p>For the Syrian Arab Republic: in accordance with international law - the land territory of the Syrian Arab Republic and its internal waters and territorial sea, the subsoil beneath and the air space above them, over which the Syrian Arab Republic exercises sovereign rights and maritime space within which The Syrian Arab Republic has the right to exercise sovereign rights for the purpose of exploration, exploitation and conservation of natural resources;</p>
        <p>e)  "State law of a Contracting Party" -</p>
        <p>Laws and other Republic normative legal acts of the Russian Federation and legal acts of the Syrian Arab</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Protection of investments">
        <p>1. Each Contracting Party shall promote conditions for investors of other Contracting Party to make investments in the territory of its State and admit such investments in accordance with its legislation.</p>
        <p>2.  Each Contracting Party shall ensure, in accordance with its national law, full protection in its territory of investments of investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Investment regime">
        <p>1.  Each Contracting Party shall ensure in its territory fair investments of investors of the State of the other Contracting Party for the management and disposal.</p>
        <p>2.  The regime referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article, should be no less favorable than that accorded to the investments of its own investors or investors of any third state, depending on which of them, in view of the investor, it is more favorable.</p>
        <p>3.  Each Contracting Party reserves the right, in accordance with the laws of your state to determine the economic areas and activities where restricted or prohibited the activities of foreign investors.</p>
        <p>4.  Treatment granted in accordance with paragraph 2 of this Article shall not apply to the advantages which the Contracting Parties providing or will provide in the future:</p>
        <p>In connection with participation in a free trade area, customs or economic union;</p>
        <p>On the basis of agreements to avoid double taxation or other agreements on taxation;</p>
        <p>In accordance with the agreements of the Russian Federation with the countries formerly part of the former Union of Soviet Socialist Republics;</p>
        <p>In accordance with the agreements of the Syrian Arab Republic and other Arab countries.</p>
        <p>5.  Without prejudice to the provisions of Articles 4, 5 and 8 of this Agreement, the Contracting Parties shall grant each other treatment no more favorable than that which they grant each other, in accordance with the commitments made under the Agreement Establishing the World Trade Organization (WTO) of 15 in April 1994, including the commitments to the General agreement on trade in services (GATS), as well as any other multilateral agreement, which can be achieved with the participation of both Contracting Parties, and which will deal with the mode of investment.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Expropriation">
        <p>1.  Investments of investors of one Contracting Party made in the territory of the other Contracting Party may not be subjected to compulsory withdrawal is tantamount to expropriation or nationalization (hereinafter referred to as - expropriation), except in cases where these measures are carried out in the public interest under compliance with the procedure established in accordance with the law of the state of the other Contracting Party, are not discriminatory and entail the payment of prompt, adequate and effective compensation.</p>
        <p>2.  The compensation shall correspond to the market value of the expropriated investment calculated on the date when the official was aware of the actual or impending expropriation. Compensation shall be paid without delay in a freely convertible currency and freely translated from the territory of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party. From the date of expropriation until the date of actual payment of compensation in the amount of the compensation will bear interest at the rate established in the domestic interbank market, the state of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investments were made.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Damages">
        <p>State Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments suffer losses in the territory of the other Contracting Party owing to war, civil unrest or other similar circumstances, provided in respect of restitution, indemnification, compensation or other settlement mode, the most favorable of those which the State of the latter Contracting The Parties shall accord to investors of a third state, or to its own investors with respect to measures taken by it in connection with such damage.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Transfer of payments">
        <p>1.  Each Contracting Party shall guarantee to investors of the other Contracting Party, after fulfillment of all tax obligations, a free transfer abroad of payments in connection with the investments, and in particular:</p>
        <p>a)  revenue;</p>
        <p>b)  funds in repayment of loans and credits recognized by both Contracting Parties as investments, as well as the accrued interest;</p>
        <p>c)  funds received in connection with the partial or total liquidation or sale of investments;</p>
        <p>d)  the compensation provided for in Articles 4 and 5 of this Agreement;</p>
        <p>e)  wages and other remuneration received by investors and individuals of the other Contracting Party who are allowed to work in connection with an investment in the territory of the first Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>2.  Transfers of payments are made without delay in freely convertible currency at the rate applicable on the date of transfer, in accordance with the currency legislation of the State of the Contracting Party in whose territory investments were made.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Subrogation">
        <p>Contracting Party or its designated agency, which made a payment to the investor on the basis of guarantees against non-commercial risks in connection with its investment in the territory of the other Contracting Party will be able to exercise by subrogation the right of the investor to the same extent as the investor. These rights shall be exercised in accordance with the law of the State of the latter Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of disputes between a contracting party and an investor of the other contracting parties">
        <p>1.  Disputes between one Contracting Party and an investor of the other Contracting Party arising in connection with an investment of an investor in the territory of the first Contracting Party, including disputes relating to the size, conditions, or order the payment of compensation in accordance with Articles 4 and 5 of this Agreement or order transfer of payments provided for in article 6 of this Agreement shall be settled if possible through negotiations.</p>
        <p>2.  If the dispute can not be settled through negotiation within six months from the date of the request of any party to a dispute to resolve it through negotiations, it is at the option of the investor can be submitted to:</p>
        <p>The competent court or the state arbitration of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investments were made, or</p>
        <p>Arbitration Court ay Jos in accordance with the Arbitration Rules of the International Trade Law of the United Nations Commission (UNCITRAL), or</p>
        <p>International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes, established pursuant to the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of Other States, done at Washington, March 18, 1965, to resolve the dispute in accordance with the provisions of this Convention, provided that it has entered into force for both states.</p>
        <p>3.  The arbitration award shall be final and binding on both parties to the dispute. Each Contracting Party undertakes to ensure the execution of such a decision in accordance with the laws of the state.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Settlement of disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>1.  Disputes between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or application of this Agreement shall be settled through negotiations.</p>
        <p>If in this way the dispute is not settled within six months from the beginning of negotiations, at the request of either Contracting Party, he referred to the arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>2.  The arbitral tribunal shall be constituted for each individual case, for which each Contracting Party shall appoint one member of the arbitration tribunal within two months from the date of receipt of the notification of the arbitration proceedings. Then, these two members shall select a national of a third State, who on approval of the two Contracting Parties shall be appointed Chairman of the arbitral tribunal within a month from the date of appointment of the other two members.</p>
        <p>3.  If within the period specified in paragraph 2 of this Article, the necessary appointments have not been made, in the absence of any other agreement, any Contracting Party may request the International Court of Justice with a request to make such appointments. If the President of the International Court of Justice is a national of either Contracting Party or is otherwise unable to discharge the said function, then make the necessary appointments invited the Deputy President of the International Court of Justice. If the deputy chairman of the International Court of Justice is also a national of either Contracting Party or is otherwise unable to discharge the said function, then make the necessary appointments offered to the next-highest member of the International Court of Justice for him, which is not a national of either Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>4.  The arbitral tribunal shall render its decision by majority vote. This decision is final and binding on the Contracting Parties. Each Contracting Party shall bear the expenses related to the activities of its own appointed member of the tribunal and of its representation in the arbitration proceedings. The costs associated with the arbitration court Chairman of the activity, as well as</p>
        <p>Other expenses The Contracting Parties shall bear in equal shares. However, the Court may in its decision that one of the Contracting Parties shall bear a larger share of spending, and that decision will be binding on both Contracting Parties. The arbitral tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Consultations">
        <p>The Contracting Parties shall at the request of any of them, shall hold consultations on matters relating to the interpretation or application of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Application of the agreement">
        <p>This Agreement shall apply to all investments made by investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party after its entry into force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Entry into force and duration of the agreement">
        <p>1.  Each Contracting Party shall notify the other Contracting Party of the completion of internal procedures necessary for the entry into force of this Agreement. This Agreement shall enter into force on the date of the last of the two notifications.</p>
        <p>2.  This Agreement shall remain in force for ten years. After this period it shall be automatically extended for successive five-year periods, unless either Contracting Party notifies the other Contracting Party at least twelve months prior to the expiry of the period of its intention to terminate this Agreement.</p>
        <p>3.  This Agreement may be amended by mutual written consent of the Contracting Parties. Any amendment shall enter into force after each Contracting Party shall notify the other Contracting Party of the fulfillment of all internal procedures necessary for the entry into force of such amendment.</p>
        <p>4.  With respect to investments made prior to the date of termination of this Agreement and covered by its action, the provisions of this Agreement shall remain in force for the next ten years after the date of termination of its validity.</p>
        <p>Done in Moscow on 26 January 2005 in two copies, each in Russian, Arabic and English languages, all texts being equally authentic. In case of any discrepancy in the interpretation of this Agreement, the English text.</p>
        <p>(Signatures)</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </main>
</treaty>
