<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Hong Kong, China SAR - Kuwait BIT (2010)</name>
    <code>T2010-41</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">HKG</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">KWT</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2010-05-10</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2013-09-14</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>3511</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source>R Polanco database</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{HKG,KWT}_2010-05-10.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT</p>
      <p>BETWEEN</p>
      <p>THE GOVERNMENT OF</p>
      <p>THE HONG KONG SPECIAL ADMINISTRATIVE REGION OF THE PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF CHINA</p>
      <p>AND</p>
      <p>THE GOVERNMENT OF THE STATE OF KUWAIT FOR THE PROMOTION AND PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region of the People's Republic of China, having been duly authorised to conclude this Agreement by the Central People's Government of the People's Republic of China, and the Government of the State of Kuwait (hereinafter referred to as "the Contracting Parties"),</p>
      <p>Desiring to create favourable conditions for greater investment by investors of one Contracting Party in the area of the other;</p>
      <p>Recognising that the encouragement and reciprocal protection under this Agreement of such investments will be conducive to the stimulation of individual business initiative and will increase prosperity in both areas;</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement</p>
        <p>(a)  "area'</p>
        <p>1.  in respect of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region includes Hong Kong Island, Kowloon and the New Territories;</p>
        <p>2.  in respect of the State of Kuwait means the territory of the State of Kuwait including any area beyond the territorial sea which in accordance with international law has been or may hereafter be designated under the laws of the State of Kuwait, as an area over which the State of Kuwait may exercise sovereign rights or jurisdiction;</p>
        <p>(b)  "company" means in respect of either Contracting Party: corporations, partnerships, associations and any other legally recognised entities incorporated or constituted under the law in force in the area of that Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>(c)  "forces" means:</p>
        <p>1.  in respect of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, the armed forces of the People's Republic of China;</p>
        <p>2.  in respect of the State of Kuwait, the armed forces of the State of Kuwait;</p>
        <p>(d)  "freely convertible" means free of all currency exchange controls and transferable abroad in any currency;</p>
        <p>(e)  "investment" means every kind of asset, held or invested directly or indirectly, and in particular, though not exclusively, includes:</p>
        <p>1.  movable and immovable property and any other property rights such as mortgages, liens or pledges;</p>
        <p>2.  shares in and stock and debentures of a company and any other form of participation in a company;</p>
        <p>3. Claims to money or to any performance under contract having a</p>
        <p>Financial value;</p>
        <p>4.  intellectual property rights and goodwill;</p>
        <p>5.  business concessions conferred by law or under contract, including concessions to search for, cultivate, extract or exploit natural resources.</p>
        <p>A change in the form in which assets are invested does not affect their character as investments and the term "investment" includes all investments, whether existing at or made after the date of entry into force of this Agreement;</p>
        <p>(f)  "investors" means:</p>
        <p>1.  in respect of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region:</p>
        <p>-  Physical persons who have the right of abode in its area; in respect of the State of Kuwait:</p>
        <p>-  A natural person holding the nationality of the State of Kuwait in accordance with its applicable laws;</p>
        <p>And</p>
        <p>2.  in respect of either Contracting Party:</p>
        <p>Any company or legal entity constituted or incorporated under the law in force of that Contracting Party, such as institutions, funds, agencies, foundations and other statutory establishments and authorities;</p>
        <p>(g)  "returns" means the amounts yielded by an investment and in particular, though not exclusively, includes profit, interest, capital gains, dividends, proceeds of liquidation, and royalties and fees.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Promotion and protection of investment and returns">
        <p>(1)  Each Contracting Party shall encourage and create favourable conditions for investors of the other Contracting Party to make investments in its area, and, subject to its right to exercise powers conferred by its laws, shall admit such investments.</p>
        <p>(2)  Investments and returns of investors of each Contracting Party shall at all times be accorded fair and equitable treatment and shall enjoy full protection and security in the area of the other Contracting Party. Neither Contracting Party shall in any way impair by unreasonable or discriminatory measures the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal of investments in its area of investors of the other Contracting Party. Each Contracting Party shall observe any obligation it may have entered into with regard to investments of investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(3)  Once established, investments of investors of a Contracting Party shall not be subject to additional requirements which are not in accordance with the laws of the other Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Treatment of investments">
        <p>(1)  Neither Contracting Party shall in its area subject investments or returns of investors of the other Contracting Party to treatment less favourable than that which it accords to investments or returns of its own investors or to investments or returns of investors of any third party.</p>
        <p>(2)  Neither Contracting Party shall in its area subject investors of the other Contracting Party, as regards their management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal of their investments, to treatment less favourable than that which it accords to its own investors or to investors of any third party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Compensation for losses">
        <p>(1)  Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments in the area of the other Contracting Party suffer losses owing to war or other armed conflict, revolution, a state of national emergency, revolt, insurrection or riot in the area of the latter Contracting Party shall be accorded by the latter Contracting Party treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification, compensation or other settlement, no less favourable than that which the latter Contracting Party accords to its own investors or to investors of any third party. Resulting payments shall be freely convertible.</p>
        <p>(2)  Without prejudice to paragraph (1) of this Article, investors of one Contracting Party who in any of the situations referred to in that paragraph suffer losses in the area of the other Contracting Party resulting from</p>
        <p>(a)  requisitioning of their property by its forces or authorities; or</p>
        <p>(b)  destruction of their property by its forces or authorities which was not caused in combat action or was not required by the necessity of the situation,</p>
        <p>Shall be accorded restitution or reasonable compensation. Resulting payments shall be freely convertible.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Expropriation">
        <p>(1)  Investors of either Contracting Party shall not be deprived of their investments nor subjected to measures having effect equivalent to such deprivation in the area of the other Contracting Party except lawfully, for a public purpose related to the internal needs of that Party, and against compensation. Such compensation shall amount to the real value of the investment immediately before the deprivation or before the impending deprivation became public knowledge whichever is the earlier, shall include</p>
        <p>Interest at a normal commercial rate until the date of payment, shall be made without undue delay, be effectively realizable and be freely convertible. The investor affected shall have a right, under the law of the Contracting Party making the deprivation, to prompt review by a judicial or other independent authority of that Party, of the investor's case and of the valuation of the investment in accordance with the principles set out in this paragraph.</p>
        <p>(2)  Where a Contracting Party expropriates the assets of a company which is incorporated or constituted under the law in force in any part of its area, and in which investors of the other Contracting Party own shares, it shall ensure that the provisions of paragraph (1) of this Article are applied to the extent necessary to guarantee compensation referred to in paragraph (1) in respect of their investment to such investors of the other Contracting Party who are owners of those shares.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Transfer of investments and returns">
        <p>(1)  Each Contracting Party shall guarantee to investors of the other Contracting Party the unrestricted right to transfer their investments and returns abroad including the transfer of:</p>
        <p>(a)  payments from compensation pursuant to Articles 4 and 5 of this Agreement;</p>
        <p>(b)  payments referred to in Article 10 of this Agreement; and</p>
        <p>(c)  payments arising out of the settlement of disputes.</p>
        <p>(2)  Transfers of currency shall be effected without delay in any convertible currency. The term "without delay" shall mean such period as is normally required for the transfer of payments and the completion of the necessary formalities for such transfer. Unless otherwise agreed by the investor transfers shall be made at the rate of exchange applicable on the date of transfer.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7">
        <p>Exceptions</p>
        <p>The provisions of this Agreement relative to the grant of treatment not less favourable than that accorded to the investors of either Contracting Party or to investors of any third party shall not be construed so as to oblige one Contracting Party to extend to the investors of the other the benefit of any treatment, preference or privilege resulting from:</p>
        <p>(a)  any existing or future customs union, free trade area, or regional co-operation or economic organisation, or similar bilateral or multilateral agreement or arrangement to which either of the Contracting Parties is or may become a party; or</p>
        <p>(b)  any bilateral or multilateral agreement or arrangement relating wholly or mainly to taxation or any domestic legislation relating wholly or mainly to taxation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Settlement of investment disputes">
        <p>(1)  A dispute between an investor of one Contracting Party and the other Contracting Party concerning an investment of the former in the area of the latter which has not been settled amicably, shall, after a period of six months from written notification of the claim, be submitted to such procedures for settlement as may be agreed between the parties to the dispute. If no such procedures have been agreed within that six month period, the parties to the dispute shall be bound to submit it to arbitration under the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law as then in force. The parties may agree in writing to modify those Rules.</p>
        <p>(2)  An investor who has submitted a case for arbitration shall not be prevented from seeking an interim measure of protection in respect of the subject matter of the dispute from a court of a Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>(3)  The arbitration award shall be final and binding on the parties to the dispute. Each Contracting Party shall ensure the recognition and enforcement of the award in accordance with its relevant laws.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>(1)  If any dispute arises between the Contracting Parties relating to the interpretation or application of this Agreement, the Contracting Parties shall in the first place try to settle it by negotiation.</p>
        <p>(2)  If the Contracting Parties fail to reach a settlement of the dispute by negotiation, it may be referred by them to such person or body as they may agree on or, at the request of either Contracting Party, shall be submitted for decision to a tribunal of three arbitrators which shall be constituted in the following manner:</p>
        <p>(a)  within thirty days after receipt of a request for arbitration, each Contracting Party shall appoint one arbitrator. A national of a State which can be regarded as neutral in relation to the dispute, who shall act as President of the tribunal, shall be appointed as the third arbitrator by agreement between the two arbitrators, within sixty days of the appointment of the second;</p>
        <p>(b)  if within the time limits specified above any appointment has not been made, either Contracting Party may request the President of the International Court of Justice, in a personal and individual capacity, to make the necessary appointment within thirty days. If the President considers that he is a national of a State which cannot be regarded as neutral in relation to the dispute, the Vice-President who is not disqualified on that ground shall make the appointment.</p>
        <p>(3)  Except as hereinafter provided in this Article or as otherwise agreed by the Contracting Parties, the tribunal shall determine the limits of its jurisdiction and establish its own procedure. At the direction of the</p>
        <p>Tribunal, or at the request of either of the Contracting Parties, a conference to determine the precise issues to be arbitrated and the specific procedures to be followed shall be held not later than thirty days after the tribunal is fully constituted.</p>
        <p>(4)  Except as otherwise agreed by the Contracting Parties or prescribed by the tribunal, each Contracting Party shall submit a memorandum within forty five days after the tribunal is fully constituted. Replies shall be due sixty days later. The tribunal shall hold a hearing at the request of either Contracting Party, or at its discretion, within thirty days after replies are due.</p>
        <p>(5)  The tribunal shall attempt to give a written decision within thirty days after completion of the hearing or, if no hearing is held, after the date both replies are submitted. The decision shall be taken by a majority vote.</p>
        <p>(6)  The Contracting Parties may submit requests for clarification of the decision within fifteen days after it is received and such clarification shall be issued within fifteen days of such request.</p>
        <p>(7)  The decision of the tribunal shall be binding on the Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>(8)  Each Contracting Party shall bear the costs of the arbitrator appointed by it. The other costs of the tribunal shall be shared equally by the Contracting Parties including any expenses incurred by the President or Vice-President of the International Court of Justice in implementing the procedures in paragraph (2)(b) of this Article.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Subrogation">
        <p>(1)  If one Contracting Party or its designated Agency makes a payment to its investor under an indemnity given in respect of an investment in the area of the other Contracting Party, the latter Contracting Party shall recognise:</p>
        <p>(a)  the assignment to the former Contracting Party or its designated</p>
        <p>Agency by law or by legal transaction of all the rights and claims of the indemnified investor; and</p>
        <p>(b)  that the former Contracting Party or its designated Agency is entitled to exercise such rights and enforce such claims by virtue of subrogation, to the same extent as that investor.</p>
        <p>(2)  The former Contracting Party or its designated Agency shall be entitled in all circumstances to the same treatment in respect of the rights and claims acquired by it by virtue of the assignment and any payments received in pursuance of those rights and claims as the indemnified investor was entitled to receive by virtue of this Agreement in respect of the investment concerned and its related returns.</p>
        <p>(3)  Any payments received by the former Contracting Party or its designated Agency in pursuance of the rights and claims acquired shall be freely convertible. Such payments shall also be freely available to the former Contracting Party for the purpose of meeting any expenditure incurred in the area of the latter Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Entry into force">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall notify the other in writing when its respective requirements for the entry into force of this Agreement have been fulfilled, and the Agreement shall enter into force on the thirtieth day after the date of receipt of the later notification.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Duration and termination">
        <p>This Agreement shall remain in force for an initial period of twenty years and thereafter until the expiration of twelve months from the date on</p>
        <p>Which either Contracting Party shall have given written notice of termination to the other.</p>
        <p>In respect of investments made prior to the date when the notice of termination of this Agreement becomes effective, the provisions of this Agreement shall continue to be effective for a period of twenty years from the date of termination of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>In witness whereof the undersigned, duly authorised thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done at Hong Kong this 13 th day of May 2010 corresponding to the 29 th day of Jamada Oula 1431 H in two originals in the Chinese, Arabic and English languages, all texts being equally authentic. In case of divergency, the English text shall prevail.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the For the Government of</p>
      <p>Hong Kong Special the State of Kuwait</p>
      <p>Administrative Region of the People's Republic of China</p>
      <p>Rita Lau</p>
      <p>Secretary for Commerce and Economic Development</p>
      <p>Mustafa Jassim Al Shamali Minister of Finance</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
