<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Russian Federation - Singapore BIT (2010)</name>
    <code>T2010-57</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">RUS</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">SGP</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2010-09-27</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2012-06-16</date_into_force>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">en</orig_language>
    <termination_type/>
    <docreference>2847</docreference>
    <comments/>
    <source/>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>en</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
    <IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>{RUS,SGP}_2010-09-27.xml</IT_FILE_NAME_REFERENCE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>AGREEMENT</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE RUSSIAN FEDERATION AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF SINGAPORE ON THE PROMOTION AND MUTUAL PROTECTION OF INVESTMENTS</p>
      <p>The Russian Federation and the Government of the Republic of Singapore, each hereinafter referred to as "Contracting Party"</p>
      <p>Desiring to create favorable conditions for long-term mutually beneficial economic cooperation between them and in particular for investments by investors of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party;</p>
      <p>Recognizing that the promotion and reciprocal protection of such investments under this Agreement will stimulate the flow of capital and promote the development of mutually beneficial trade and economic cooperation, have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
        <p>For the purposes of this Agreement:</p>
        <p>1.  The term "investor" means any natural or legal person of one Contracting Party that has investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party in accordance with the legislation of the latter Contracting Party:</p>
        <p>(A)  the term "natural person" means any citizen of the state of the first Contracting Party in accordance with its legislation; and</p>
        <p>(B)  The term "legal person" means any legal entity created or organized in accordance with the legislation of the first Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>2.  The term "investment" means any kind of asset invested by an investor of one Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party in accordance with the legislation of the latter Contracting Party, including, but not limited to:</p>
        <p>(A)  any movable and immovable property and</p>
        <p>Property rights;</p>
        <p>(B)  any shares, stocks and other forms of equity participation in the capital of legal entities, and bonds;</p>
        <p>(C)  any rights to the funds or contracts having an economic value associated with an investment;</p>
        <p>(D)  any exclusive rights to intellectual property and sustainable business relationships;</p>
        <p>(E)  any right to engage in entrepreneurial activity, provided by the legislation of the latter Contracting Party or under contract, including agreements relating to the exploration, development, production and exploitation of natural resources. No change in the form of investment does not affect their qualification as investments if such change does not contradict the legislation of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investments were made.</p>
        <p>3.  The term "income" means money yielded from investments, including any profits, interest, capital gains, dividends, royalties or other remuneration.</p>
        <p>4.  The term "freely usable currency" means a freely usable currency, determined in accordance with the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund and any amendments thereto.</p>
        <p>5.  The term "territory" means, in respect of each Contracting Party, the territory of the Russian Federation and the Republic of Singapore, respectively, as well as its exclusive economic zone and continental shelf over which the Contracting Party exercises sovereign rights or jurisdiction in accordance with the United Nations Convention on the Sea law (1982), including for the purposes of exploration and exploitation of natural resources in these areas.</p>
        <p>6.  The term "law of a Contracting Party" means the laws and other normative legal acts of the Russian Federation or the laws and other normative legal acts of the Republic of Singapore, respectively.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="2" title="Application of this agreement">
        <p>This Agreement shall apply to all investments made by investors of either Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party beginning on or after January 1, 1990, but does not apply to any dispute or claim relating to the investments which have arisen or have been settled before its entry into force.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="3" title="Promotion and protection of investments">
        <p>Each Contracting Party shall endeavor to encourage and create favorable conditions for investors of the other Contracting Party to make investments in its territory and admit such investments in accordance with its legislation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="4" title="Investment mode">
        <p>1.  Each Contracting Party shall in its territory fair and equitable treatment to investments of investors of the other Contracting Party.</p>
        <p>2.  referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article Mode, should be not less favorable than that provided by a Contracting Party to investments of its own investors or investments of investors of any third state, depending on which one is more favorable.</p>
        <p>3.  Each Contracting Party reserves the right, in accordance with their legislation to apply and introduce exemptions from the provisions of this article with respect to national treatment.</p>
        <p>4.  The provisions of this article with respect to MFN should not be construed as obliging one Contracting Party to extend to investments of investors of the other Contracting Party the benefit of any treatment, preference or privilege which may be granted to the former Contracting Party by virtue of:</p>
        <p>(A)  any established or being established in the future free trade area, customs union, monetary union or any other similar economic</p>
        <p>Integration of education to which is or may become a Contracting Party;</p>
        <p>(B)  any rights or obligations of the Contracting Parties arising from international agreements or other arrangements wholly or partially related to taxation.</p>
        <p>5.  From the date of entry of the Russian Federation to the World Trade Organization (WTO), without prejudice to the provisions of Articles 5, 6, 8 and 9 of this Agreement, no Contracting Party shall be bound by this Agreement shall be accorded treatment more favorable than that accorded by that Contracting Party accordance with its obligations under the agreement establishing the WTO on April 15, 1994, including the commitments to the General agreement on trade in services.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="5" title="Expropriation">
        <p>1.  Neither Contracting Party shall not be nationalized, expropriated or subjected to measures effect equivalent to nationalization or expropriation (hereinafter referred to as - expropriation), investments of investors of the other Contracting Party, except in cases where the expropriation is carried out:</p>
        <p>(A)  a public purpose;</p>
        <p>(B)  in a non-discriminatory basis;</p>
        <p>(C)  in accordance with the relevant procedures established by the legislation; and</p>
        <p>(D)  the payment of compensation in accordance with this Article.</p>
        <p>2.  The expropriation must be accompanied by payment of prompt, adequate and effective compensation. Payment must match the fair market value of the expropriated investment calculated on the date immediately preceding the date of expropriation, or on the date immediately preceding the date when it became common knowledge about the impending expropriation, depending on which event occurs first. Such compensation shall be effectively realizable, paid without undue delay, in any freely usable currency at the option of the investor, and freely transferable in accordance with Article 7 of this Agreement. From the date of</p>
        <p>Expropriation until the date of actual payment of compensation in the amount of compensation shall bear interest at a commercial rate established on a market basis, not less than the London interbank offered rate (LIBOR) on six-month loans in US dollars.</p>
        <p>3.  Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 of this article, the expropriation of land in the territory of either Contracting Party shall be performed in accordance with the legislation of that Contracting Party for the purposes established by the said law, and accompanied by payment in accordance with the legislation of that Contracting Party compensation which should be determined with due regard to the market value and shall be paid without undue delay,</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="6" title="Damages">
        <p>Investors of one Contracting Party whose investments in the territory of the other Contracting Party suffering losses owing to war or other armed conflict, a state of emergency, rebellion, revolt, insurrection or other similar circumstances pas territory of the latter Contracting Party shall be provided in respect of restitution, indemnification, compensation or other type of settlement, if such a settlement is carried out, the regime most favorable of those latter Contracting Party shall accord to investors of any third state or to its own investors.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="7" title="Transfer payments">
        <p>1.  Each Contracting Party shall, in accordance with its legislation guarantees the investors of the other Contracting Party, after fulfillment of all their tax obligations free transfer abroad of payments related to their investments, and in particular:</p>
        <p>(A)  original capital or any additional funds to maintain or expand investments;</p>
        <p>(B)  income;</p>
        <p>(C)  funds received from the total or partial liquidation, sale or other disposition</p>
        <p>Investments;</p>
        <p>(D)  funds paid in accordance with the loan agreements related to investments;</p>
        <p>(E)  payments on contracts related to the investment; (D) wages received by nationals of the other Contracting Party who are authorized to work in connection with investments in the territory of the first Contracting Party in accordance with its legislation;</p>
        <p>(D)  payments made in accordance with Articles 5 and 6 of this Agreement.</p>
        <p>2.  Transfers of payments referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article shall be made at the exchange rate applicable on the date of transfer in a freely usable currency in accordance with the procedures established by the currency legislation of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investments were made.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="8" title="Subrogation">
        <p>Contracting Party or its designated agency, which made a payment to the investor of that Contracting Party on the basis of guarantees against non-commercial risks in connection with its investment in the territory of the other Contracting Party may exercise by subrogation the right of the investor to the same extent as the investor. If necessary, the procedure for the implementation of such rights may be established by the legislation of the latter Contracting Party.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="9" title="Settlement of disputes between a contracting party and">
        <p>Investor of the other Contracting Party</p>
        <p>1.  Any dispute between an investor of one Contracting Party and the other Contracting Party arising in connection with the possible violation of this Agreement shall be settled as far as possible by negotiations between the parties to the dispute. Party to the dispute, which asks for negotiations, send a written notice to the other side of the dispute.</p>
        <p>2.  If the dispute can not be settled through negotiation within six months from the date of the written request,</p>
        <p>Referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article, it may be referred to select an investor for consideration:</p>
        <p>(A)  as the competent court or tribunal of the Contracting Party in whose territory the investments were made;</p>
        <p>(B) , the arbitral tribunal ah os in accordance with the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law, adopted by the General Assembly of the United Nations on 15 December 1976 (UNCITRAL) and the amendments thereto;</p>
        <p>The International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes (the Centre), established under the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of Other States (the Convention), opened for signature in Washington, 18 March 1965, to resolve the dispute in accordance with the provisions of the Convention (provided that the Convention entered into force for both Parties); or</p>
        <p>Further, in accordance with the rules of the Centre (provided that the Convention has not entered into force for both or one of the Contracting Parties).</p>
        <p>The arbitration decision on the dispute shall be final and binding on both parties to the dispute. Each Contracting Party shall ensure the implementation of the arbitral award in accordance with its legislation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="10" title="Settlement of disputes between the contracting parties">
        <p>1.  Any dispute between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or application of this Agreement shall as far as possible by negotiations If this way the dispute can not be settled within six months from the beginning of negotiations, at the written request of any Contracting Party, he referred to the arbitral tribunal to be set up in each case in the manner specified in paragraphs 2 and 3.</p>
        <p>2.  Within three months from the date of receipt of the request for arbitration, each Contracting Party shall appoint one member of the arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>Then, these two members of the arbitral tribunal shall elect a national of a third State, who on approval</p>
        <p>Both Contracting Parties shall be appointed Chairman of the arbitral tribunal. Chairman of the arbitral tribunal shall be appointed within two months from the date of appointment of the other two members of the arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>3.  If within the period specified in paragraph 2 of this Article, the necessary appointments have not been made, any Contracting Party in the absence of a written agreement may apply to the International Court of Justice with a request to make such appointments. If the President of the International Court of Justice is a national of either Contracting Party or is otherwise unable to discharge the said function, then make the necessary appointments invited the Deputy President of the International Court of Justice. If the deputy chairman of the International Court of Justice is also a national of either Contracting Party or is otherwise unable to discharge the said function, then make the necessary appointments offered to the next in seniority-member International Court of Justice who is not a national of either Contracting Party in respect of where there are no other reasons that do not allow him to fulfill this request.</p>
        <p>4.  The arbitral tribunal shall render its decision by majority vote. The decision of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and binding on both Contracting Parties. Each Contracting Party shall bear the expenses related to the activities of the arbitral tribunal of its own member and of its representation in the arbitration proceedings; costs associated with the arbitration court Chairman and other expenses The Contracting Parties shall bear in equal shares. The arbitral tribunal may, however, provide in its decision that one of the Contracting Parties shall bear a larger share of the costs, and the decision will be binding on both Contracting Parties.</p>
        <p>5.  Except for the provisions referred to in paragraphs 1-4 of this article, the arbitral tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="11" title="Application of other provisions">
        <p>If the legislation of either Contracting Party or international agreements that exist at present or will be achieved in the future between the Contracting Parties in addition to this Agreement contain provisions granting investments of investors of the other Contracting Party treatment more favorable than is provided for by this Agreement, this Agreement shall apply without prejudice to such provisions.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="12" title="Consultations">
        <p>The Contracting Parties shall at the request of any of them, shall hold consultations on matters relating to the interpretation or application of this Agreement.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="article" num="13" title="Entry into force, duration, amendments and termination">
        <p>1.  Each Contracting Party shall notify the other Contracting Party of the completion of internal procedures necessary for the entry into force of this Agreement. This Agreement shall enter into force on the thirtieth day following the date of the last of the two notifications.</p>
        <p>2.  This Agreement is valid for fifteen years. After this period, it shall remain in force until either Contracting Party notifies the other Contracting Party at least twelve months of its decision to terminate this Agreement.</p>
        <p>3.  In respect of investments made prior to the date of termination of this Agreement, the provisions of Articles 1-12 shall remain in force for the next fifteen years after that date.</p>
        <p>4.  This Agreement may be amended by mutual written consent of the Contracting Parties. Each Contracting Party shall notify the other Contracting Party of the fulfillment of all internal procedures necessary for the entry into force of such amendment. The amendment shall enter into</p>
        <p>Effect from the date of the last of the two notifications.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, being duly authorized by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</p>
      <p>Done at Singapore, September 27, 2010 in two originals, each in the Russian and English languages, both texts being equally authentic.</p>
      <p>For the Government of the Russian Federation For the Government of the Republic of Singapore</p>
    </conclusion>
  </main>
</treaty>
