<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE root [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Indonesia - Switzerland BIT (2022)</name>
    <code>T2022-1</code>
    <partyisocode n="0">CHE</partyisocode>
    <partyisocode n="1">IDN</partyisocode>
    <date_signed>2022-05-25</date_signed>
    <date_into_force/>
    <date_terminated/>
    <type>WTI_TYPE_TREATY_BIT</type>
    <orig_language n="1">de,fr,it</orig_language>
    <translated>yes</translated>
    <termination_type/>
    <comments/>
    <source>https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil/documentation/communiques.msg-id-89127.html</source>
    <rev_date_into_force/>
    <rev_date_signed/>
    <side_date_into_force/>
    <side_date_signed/>
    <IT_TRANSLATED>yes</IT_TRANSLATED>
    <IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>de,fr,it</IT_ORIGIN_LANGUAGE>
  </meta>
  <main>
    <title>
      <p>Agreement between the Swiss Federal Council and the Government of the Republic of Indonesia on the the Promotion and Reciprocal Protection of investments</p>
    </title>
    <preamble>
      <p>Preamble</p>
      <p>The Swiss Federal Council</p>
      <p>and</p>
      <p>the Government of the Republic of Indonesia,</p>
      <p>hereinafter referred to as "Parties" or individually as "Party"</p>
      <p>desiring to intensify economic cooperation in the mutual interest of both States ;</p>
      <p>Recognizing that the creation of an enabling environment for business will contribute to&nbsp;stimulate entrepreneurial initiative with a view to increasing investment by investors of one Party in the territory of the other Party;</p>
      <p>Recognizing the important contribution that investment can make to sustainable development, and seeking to promote and facilitate investment in the respective territories of the&nbsp;in the respective territories of the Parties;</p>
      <p>Recognizing that reciprocal promotion and protection of investment can&nbsp;stimulate entrepreneurial initiative, encourage the flow of capital and technology&nbsp;and increase economic development and prosperity in both States;</p>
      <p>Convinced that these objectives can be achieved without weakening generally applicable health, safety, labor and environmental standards;</p>
      <p>Affirming the mutual support of investment, environmental and labor policies in this regard;</p>
      <p>Reaffirming their commitment to the principles and objectives set forth in the Charter of the of the United Nations and the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, including democracy rule of law, human rights and fundamental freedoms ;</p>
      <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <div type="chapter" num="I" title="Definitions and Scope of Application">
        <div type="article" num="1" title="Definitions">
          <p>For the purposes of this Agreement: </p>
          <p>(1) The term "freely convertible currency" means a currency that is widely traded on the international exchange market and widely used in international transactions. </p>
          <p>(2) "ICSID" means the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes. </p>
          <p>(3) The term "ICSID Additional Facility Rules" means the Rules Governing the Additional Facility for the Administration of Proceedings by the Secretariat of the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes, as amended and in force as of April 10, 2006. </p>
          <p>(4) "ICSID Arbitration Rules" means the Rules of Procedure for Arbitration Proceedings (Arbitration Rules), as amended and in force on April 10, 2006.</p>
          <p> (5) "ICSID Convention" means the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of Other States, signed in Washington on March 18, 1965. </p>
          <p>(6) "Investment" means any asset that an investor owns or controls, directly or indirectly, and that has the characteristics of an investment, including the commitment of capital or other resources, the expectation of gain or profit, the assumption of risk, or a certain period of time. An investment may take the form of: </p>
          <p>(a) an enterprise; </p>
          <p>(b) shares and other forms of equity in an enterprise; </p>
          <p>(c) bonds, secured or unsecured, other debt obligations and loans; (1), (2) </p>
          <p>(d) intellectual property rights; </p>
          <p>(e) monetary claims and rights to contractual performance in connection with a business and having a financial value; (3)</p>
          <p> (f) turnkey contracts, construction, management, production, concession, revenue sharing and other similar contracts having financial value;</p>
          <p> (g) licenses, authorizations, permits, and similar rights granted in accordance with the laws of the Party; (4) an</p>
          <p>(h) other tangible or intangible property, whether movable or immovable, and related property rights such as leases, mortgages and pledges. The term "investment" does not include orders and judgments rendered in the context of judicial or administrative proceedings or arbitration awards rendered in arbitration proceedings. For the purposes of the definition of investment in this section, any uninvested income shall be considered an investment and any change in the form in which assets are invested or reinvested shall not affect their status as an investment. </p>
          <p>(7) The term "investor" means: </p>
          <p>(a) an individual who, in accordance with the law of a Party, is a national of that Party, or </p>
          <p>(b) a corporation, company, partnership or other organization that is incorporated or otherwise organized in accordance with the law of that Party and has its principal place of business and actual economic activities in the territory of that Party that has made an investment. </p>
          <p>(8) The term "locally established enterprise" means an enterprise owned or controlled, directly or indirectly, by an investor of a Party that is established in the territory of the other Party. An enterprise is:</p>
          <p> (a) owned by individuals or enterprises of a Party if more than 50 percent of its capital stock is wholly owned by individuals or enterprises of that Party; or </p>
          <p>(b) controlled by individuals or enterprises of a Party if such individuals or enterprises have the capacity to appoint a majority of the directors or otherwise have the legal right to direct its operations. </p>
          <p>(9) The term "New York Convention" means the Convention on the Recognition and Enforcement of Foreign Arbitral Awards adopted at the United Nations in New York on June 10, 1958. (10) The term "income" means amounts generated by or derived from an investment, including, but not limited to, profits, interest, capital gains, dividends, royalties and remuneration. </p>
          <p>(11) The term "territory" means the territory of a Party as defined by the laws of the Party concerned in accordance with international law. </p>
          <p>(12) The term "UNCITRAL Arbitration Rules" means the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law, as adopted by the General Assembly of the United Nations on 15 December 1976. </p>
          <div type="foot_note">(1) Some forms of debt, such as bonds, secured or unsecured, and long-term promissory bills, are more likely to have the characteristics of an investment, while other forms of debt, such as claims for payment due resulting from the sale of goods or services, are less likely.</div>
          <div type="foot_note">(2) A loan from one Party to the other Party is not an investment.</div>
          <div type="foot_note">(3) For greater certainty, the term investment does not include liquidated claims arising solely from: (a) commercial contracts for the sale of goods or services, or (b) the extension of credit in connection with such commercial contracts.</div>
          <div type="foot_note">(4) Whether a particular type of license, authorization, permit, or similar instrument (including a concession, to the extent that it is in the nature of such an instrument) has the characteristics of an investment depends on such factors as the nature and extent of the rights that the law of the Party confers on the holder. Instruments that do not have the characteristics of an investment include those that do not create rights protected under the law of the Party. For greater certainty, the foregoing is without prejudice to the question of whether any assets associated with such instruments have the characteristics of an investment.</div>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="2" title="Scope of the Agreement">
          <p>(1) This Agreement applies to investments established or acquired in the territory of a Party, and, where applicable, admitted (5) in accordance with its laws and regulations, by investors of the other Party, whether before or after the entry into force of this Agreement. </p>
          <p>(2) This Agreement does not apply to claims or disputes arising out of events that occurred (6) before its entry into force. </p>
          <p>(3) This Agreement does not apply to government contracts.</p>
          <p> (4) Article 5 (National Treatment) does not apply to any subsidy or contribution provided by a Party, including government-supported loans, guarantees and insurance, or to any condition attached to the receipt or renewal of such subsidy or contribution, whether or not such subsidy or contribution is offered exclusively to investors of the Party or to investments of investors of the Party. </p>
          <div type="foot_note">(5) For greater certainty, in the case of Indonesia, "admitted in accordance with its laws and regulations" may include the requirement for specific written approval.</div>
          <div type="foot_note">(6) For greater certainty, this Agreement does not bind a Party with respect to any act or occurrence that occurred prior to the date of entry into force of this Agreement for that Party or any situation that ceased to exist prior to that date.</div>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="3" title="Fiscal Measures">
          <p>(1) Except as provided in this Article, nothing in this Agreement shall apply to fiscal measures. </p>
          <p>(2) This Agreement grants rights or imposes obligations in connection with tax measures only if such rights or obligations are provided for in: </p>
          <p>(a) Article 7 (Expropriation), or </p>
          <p>(b) Article 9 (Transfers).</p>
          <p> (3) Where paragraph 2(a) or (b) applies, Chapter III, Section One (Settlement of Disputes between a Party and an Investor of the other Party), shall also apply with respect to tax measures. </p>
          <p>(4) If an investor alleges that the Responding Party has violated Article 7 (Expropriation) or Article 9 (Transfers) through the adoption or enforcement of a tax measure, the competent authorities of the Responding Party may request consultations with the competent authorities of the non-party to the dispute at the time the Responding Party receives the investor's notification of intent under Article 19 (Filing a Complaint). The competent authorities of the Parties shall hold consultations to determine whether the tax measure constitutes an expropriation under Article 7 (Expropriation) or whether Article 9 (Transfers) has been violated. Any arbitral tribunal that may be established under Chapter III, Section One (Settlement of Disputes Between a Party and an Investor of the Other Party) to consider tax measures shall be bound by the decision of the competent authorities under this paragraph. If the competent authorities of the Parties are unable to determine whether Article 9 (Transfers) has been violated or whether the tax measure constitutes an expropriation referred to in Article 7 (Expropriation) within 360 days from the date of receipt of the request for consultations by the Party not party to the dispute, the investor may refer its claim to arbitration in accordance with Article 19 (Filing a Claim). </p>
          <p>(5) In determining whether a tax measure constitutes an expropriation, the following considerations shall be taken into account:</p>
          <p> (a) the imposition of taxes does not generally constitute an expropriation. The mere introduction of new tax measures or the levying of taxes in more than one jurisdiction in connection with an investment does not in itself constitute an expropriation; </p>
          <p>(b) tax enforcement activities, including the seizure of property for the purpose of collecting taxes, generally do not constitute an expropriation; and </p>
          <p>(c) tax measures that are consistent with internationally accepted tax policies, principles and practices generally do not constitute an expropriation. In particular, tax measures aimed at preventing tax evasion or avoidance should not be considered expropriatory; and </p>
          <p>(d) tax measures applied on a non-discriminatory basis, as opposed to those targeting investors of a particular nationality or specific individual taxpayers, are not likely to constitute expropriation. A tax measure should not constitute an expropriation if it was already in force at the time the investment was made and information about the measure had been published or otherwise made available to the public.</p>
          <p> (6) Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and obligations of either Party under any tax treaty. In the event of any inconsistency between this Agreement and any such tax convention, the latter shall prevail to the extent of the inconsistency. The determination of whether there is an inconsistency between this Agreement and any such convention shall be made by the competent authorities under that convention alone. </p>
          <p>(7) For the purposes of this Article:</p>
          <p>(a) the term "tax convention" in paragraph 6 means a convention for the avoidance of double taxation or other international agreement or arrangement in tax matters to which the Parties are parties; (b) the term "competent authorities" in paragraph 4 means: </p>
          <p>(i) in the case of Indonesia, the Minister of Finance or his authorized representative, and </p>
          <p>(ii) in the case of Switzerland, the Head of the Federal Department of Finance or his authorized representative. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" num="II" title="Protection of Investments">
        <div type="article" num="4" title="Treatment of Investments">
          <p>(1) Each Party shall accord in its territory fair and equitable treatment and full protection and security to investments of investors of the other Party in accordance with this Article. </p>
          <p>(2) A Party is in breach of the obligation to accord fair and equitable treatment under paragraph 1 where a measure or series of measures constitutes: </p>
          <p>(a) a denial of justice in criminal, civil or administrative proceedings;</p>
          <p> (b) a fundamental violation of due process, including a fundamental violation of transparency, in judicial and administrative proceedings; </p>
          <p>(c) manifest arbitrariness; </p>
          <p>(d) targeted discrimination based on manifestly impermissible grounds, such as sex, race or religious belief; or </p>
          <p>(e) abusive treatment, such as coercion, duress and harassment. </p>
          <p>(3) At the request of a Party, the Parties shall review the content of the obligation to provide fair and equitable treatment in accordance with the procedure set out in Article 44 (Entry into Force, Duration and Termination) for amendments to the Agreement, and in particular shall determine whether treatment other than that listed in paragraph 2 may also constitute a violation of that obligation. </p>
          <p>(4) The term "full protection and security" implies that each Party shall take such measures as may be reasonably necessary to ensure the protection and security of investments.</p>
          <p> (5) In applying the obligation of fair and equitable treatment, the Arbitral Tribunal may take into account whether or not a Party has made a specific written commitment to an investor to encourage an investment, which has created a legitimate expectation and motivated the investor's decision to make or maintain the investment, but which the Party has failed to act upon. </p>
          <p>(6) The mere fact that a Party acts or refrains from acting in a manner that may be inconsistent with an investor's expectations does not constitute a violation of this Article, even if it results in loss or damage to the investment. </p>
          <p>(7) A finding of a violation of another provision of this Agreement or another international agreement does not establish a violation of this Article. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="5" title="National Treatment">
          <p>(1) Each Party shall accord in its territory treatment no less favorable to investments of investors of the other Party than it accords in like circumstances (7) to investments of its own investors. (8)</p>
          <p>(2) Each Party shall accord in its territory treatment no less favorable to investors of the other Party than it accords in like circumstances to its own investors with respect to the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment, increase or disposition of their investments. </p>
          <p>(3) For greater certainty, the treatment to be accorded by a Party under paragraphs 1 and 2 means, in the case of a regional level government, treatment no less favorable than the most favorable treatment that such regional level government accords, in like circumstances, to investors of the Party of which it is a part and to the investments of such investors.</p>
          <div type="foot_note">(7) For greater certainty, whether treatment is accorded in "like circumstances" under Article 5 (National Treatment) or Article 6 (Most-Favored-Nation Treatment) depends on the totality of the circumstances, including the economic or commercial sector(s) involved and whether the treatment in question discriminates among investments on the basis of legitimate public welfare objectives.</div>
          <div type="foot_note">(8) For greater certainty, this Article does not apply to measures relating to the disposition of an investment if the foreign investors were notified at the time of or during the registration of their investment that their investment would be subsequently disposed of in accordance with the domestic law of the host Party.</div>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="6" title="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment">
          <p>(1) Each Party shall accord in its territory treatment no less favorable to investments of investors of the other Party than it accords, in like circumstances, to investments of investors of any third party. </p>
          <p>(2) Each Party shall accord in its territory treatment no less favorable to investors of the other Party than it accords in like circumstances to investors of any third party with respect to the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment, increase or disposition of their investments. </p>
          <p>(3) The treatment provided for in paras. 1 and 2 does not apply to: </p>
          <p>(a) existing bilateral or regional investment agreements that were signed or entered into force prior to the entry into force of this Agreement;</p>
          <p> (b) arrangements with a third party in the same geographic region for the promotion of regional economic, social, industrial, monetary or employment cooperation in respect of specific projects; </p>
          <p>(c) existing or future agreements establishing a free trade area, customs union or common market that provide for a Party to grant preferential treatment to investors from third states; or </p>
          <p>(d) existing or future agreements for the avoidance of double taxation and other tax conventions. </p>
          <p>(4) For greater certainty, paragraphs 1 and 2 do not apply to international dispute resolution procedures or mechanisms contained in other international agreements and shall not be construed to provide investors with dispute resolution procedures or mechanisms other than those provided for in Chapter III (Dispute Settlement), Section One (Settlement of Disputes Between a Party and an Investor of the Other Party). </p>
          <p>(5) For greater certainty, substantive obligations in other international investment agreements entered into by a Party do not in themselves amount to most-favored-nation treatment referred to in paragraphs 1 and 2, and thus may not give rise to a violation of this Article, absent concrete measures adopted or maintained by that Party in accordance with those obligations. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="7" title="Expropriation">
          <p>(1) No Party shall expropriate or nationalize an investment of an investor of the other Party, directly or indirectly, by means of measures amounting to expropriation or nationalization (hereinafter referred to as "expropriation"), except where such expropriation is effected: </p>
          <p>(a) on public interest grounds; </p>
          <p>(b) in a non-discriminatory manner; </p>
          <p>(c) upon prompt payment of adequate and effective compensation, in accordance with paras. 3 and 4, and </p>
          <p>(d) in accordance with the principle of due process. </p>
          <p>This paragraph shall be interpreted in accordance with Schedule A on Expropriation. </p>
          <p>(2) At the request of an investor, any expropriation or appraisal measure shall be subject to review by a judicial or other independent authority in accordance with the procedure provided by the laws of the Party taking the measure. </p>
          <p>(3) The compensation referred to in paragraph 1, letter (c), shall:</p>
          <p> (a) be paid without delay; (9)</p>
          <p>(b) is equivalent to the fair market value (10) of the expropriated investment immediately before the expropriation takes place (the date of expropriation) or the imminence of the expropriation becomes public knowledge, whichever is earlier; </p>
          <p>(c) does not take into account any change in value resulting from the fact that the proposed expropriation was already known, and (d) is effectively realizable and freely transferable in accordance with Art. 9 (Transfers). </p>
          <p>(4) Interest at the appropriate market rate shall be paid on the compensation between the date of expropriation and the date of payment. Valuation criteria used to determine fair market value may include going concern value, asset value including declared tax value of tangible property and other criteria as appropriate. </p>
          <p>(5) Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraphs 1, 3 and 4, any direct expropriation of land that is set out in the legislation of the expropriating Party shall be carried out for reasons of public interest and on payment of compensation at fair market value in accordance with that legislation. </p>
          <p>(6) This Article does not apply to the issuance of compulsory licenses granted in respect of intellectual property rights, or to the revocation, restriction or creation of intellectual property rights, to the extent that such issuance, revocation, restriction or creation is consistent with the Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights in Annex 1C of the WTO Agreement. (11)</p>
          <div type="foot_note">(9) The Parties understand that there may be legal or administrative proceedings to be observed before payment can be made.</div>
          <div type="foot_note">(10) The assessment of the fair market value of the expropriated investment excludes special or windfall profits.</div>
          <div type="foot_note">(11) For greater certainty, the Parties have recognized for the purposes of this Article that the term "revocation" of intellectual property rights includes forfeiture or cancellation of those rights, and the term "restriction" of intellectual property rights includes exceptions to those rights.</div>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="8" title="Compensation for Losses">
          <p>(1) Investors of a Party whose investments in the territory of the other Party suffer losses as a result of war or other armed conflict, civil strife, national emergency, revolt, insurrection, riot or other similar situations in the territory of the latter Party shall be granted compensation by the latter Party, with respect to restitution, compensation, indemnification or other forms of settlement, if any, treatment no less favourable than that accorded by the latter Party to its own investors or to the investors of any third party, if the latter is more favourable.</p>
          <p>(2) Notwithstanding paragraph (1), an investor of a Party that suffers a loss in the territory of the other Party in any of the circumstances referred to in that paragraph as a result of:</p>
          <p>   (a) the requisition of all or part of its investment by the forces or authorities of the other Party, or </p>
          <p>(b) the destruction of all or part of its investment by the forces or authorities of the other Party, when the situation did not require it, shall be granted by the other Party either restitution of its property or compensation. In the case of compensation, the value shall not exceed the loss suffered. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="9" title="Transfers">
          <p>(1) Each Party shall permit all transfers relating to investments of an investor of the other Party in its territory to be made freely and without delay to and from its territory. Such transfers shall include: </p>
          <p>(a) capital contributions, including initial contributions, profits, capital gains, dividends, royalties, technical assistance fees, management and technical fees, interest and other current income from an investment;</p>
          <p> (b) proceeds from the sale or liquidation of all or part of an investment; </p>
          <p>(c) payments made under a contract entered into by the investor or its investment, including payments made under a loan agreement; </p>
          <p>(d) payments made under Art. 7 (Expropriation) and Art. 8 (Compensation for Losses); </p>
          <p>(e) earnings and other remuneration of personnel engaged abroad for the purposes of that investment; and</p>
          <p> (f) payments arising from the settlement of a dispute under Chapter III (Dispute Resolution). </p>
          <p>(2) Unless otherwise agreed with the investor, each Party shall permit such transfers to be made in a freely convertible currency at the market rate of exchange prevailing at the time of transfer. </p>
          <p>(3) Nothing in this Article shall be construed to prevent a Party from applying, in a fair and non-discriminatory manner and in good faith, its laws relating to: </p>
          <p>(a) bankruptcy, insolvency or protection of creditors' rights;</p>
          <p> (b) the issuance, trading or dealing in securities, futures, options or derivatives;</p>
          <p> (c) criminal or penal offenses; </p>
          <p>(d) financial reports or accounting entries on transfers where necessary to assist law enforcement or financial regulatory authorities; </p>
          <p>(e) compliance with orders or judgments in judicial or administrative proceedings; </p>
          <p>(f) social security, public pension or mandatory savings plans;</p>
          <p> (g) employee severance payments; or </p>
          <p>(h) taxation.</p>
          <p> (4) Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and obligations of members of the International Monetary Fund under the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund, including the use of exchange measures that are consistent with the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund. </p>
          <p>(5) A transfer shall be deemed to have taken place "without delay" if it was effected within the time period normally required for the completion of transfer formalities imposed by the central bank and other competent authorities of a Party. This period shall begin on the day on which the request for transfer is made and shall in no case exceed 2 months. These formalities shall apply without discrimination to investors.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="10" title="Restrictions to Protect Balance of Payments Equilibrium">
          <p>(1) If a Party encounters or is likely to encounter serious balance of payments or external financial difficulties or if, in exceptional circumstances, payments and capital movements cause or threaten to cause serious difficulties in macroeconomic management, particularly with respect to monetary and exchange rate policies, it may adopt or maintain restrictions on payments or capital movements related to investments. </p>
          <p>(2) Restrictions adopted or maintained under paragraph (1) shall: </p>
          <p>(a) be consistent with the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund; </p>
          <p>(b) avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial, economic, and financial interests of the other Party; </p>
          <p>(c) not go beyond what is necessary to address the circumstances described in paragraph (1); </p>
          <p> (d) are temporary and shall be phased out as the situation contemplated in paragraph 1 improves;</p>
          <p>(e) are applied on a national treatment basis;</p>
          <p> (f) ensure that the other party is treated as favorably as any third party; and </p>
          <p>(g) do not apply to payments or transfers relating to current transactions, unless the establishment of such measures is consistent with the procedures provided for in the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="11" title="Subrogation">
          <p>(1) If a Party, or an agency, institution, governmental entity or corporation designated by it, makes a payment to an investor of that Party under a guarantee, insurance contract or other form of indemnity that it has entered into on non-commercial risks in connection with an investment, the other Party, in whose territory the investment was made, shall recognize the subrogation or transfer of any right that the investor would have had under this Agreement in connection with that investment. The investor may not exercise such rights to the extent of the subrogation. </p>
          <p>(2) The rights or claims subrogated or transferred shall not exceed the original rights or claims of such Investor.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="12" title="Right to Regulate">
          <p>(1) For purposes of this Agreement, the Parties reaffirm their right to regulate in their respective territories to achieve legitimate public policy objectives, such as the protection of public health, welfare, public education, safety, the environment, public morals, social or consumer protection, privacy and data protection, and the promotion and protection of cultural diversity. </p>
          <p>(2) For greater certainty, the mere fact that a Party exercises its right to regulate, including by amending its laws, in a manner that adversely affects an investment or that frustrates an investor's expectations, including its expectation of profit, does not constitute a breach of an obligation under this Agreement. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="13" title="Corporate Social Responsibility">
          <p>Each Party shall encourage legal persons operating in its territory or subject to its jurisdiction to voluntarily incorporate into their internal policies internationally recognized standards, guidelines and principles on corporate social responsibility that are supported or endorsed by that Party. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="14" title="Measures Against Corruption">
          <p>(1) An investor of a Party and its investments shall not, before or after the establishment of an investment in the territory of the other Party, offer, procure or provide any undue pecuniary or other advantage directly or through intermediaries, to a public official of the other Party, for the benefit of that official or a third party, to cause that official or third party to act or refrain from acting in the performance of official duties, in order to obtain any favor in connection with an investment. </p>
          <p>(2) An investor of a Party and its investments shall not be complicit in the territory of the other Party in any act described in paragraph (1), including by instigation or assistance.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" num="III" title="Settlement of Disputes"/>
      <div type="section" num="1" title="Settlement of Disputes between a Party and an Investor of the other Party">
        <div type="article" num="15" title="Scope">
          <p>(1) This Section applies to disputes between a Party and an investor of the other Party ("disputants") regarding an alleged breach by the Party of an obligation under this Agreement that results in loss or damage to the investor (hereinafter referred to as an "investment dispute"). </p>
          <p>(2) This Section does not apply to investment disputes that arose prior to the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</p>
          <p> (3) A natural person who is a national or citizen of a Party may not bring a claim against that Party under this Section.</p>
          <p> (4) A juridical person of a Party and its subsidiaries may not bring a claim against the other Party under this Section if that juridical person is owned or controlled by an investor of a third party and the other Party does not maintain diplomatic relations with that third party.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="16" title="Transparency of Arbitration Proceedings">
          <p>(1) Subject to paragraph (2), the responding Party shall make all awards and decisions of the arbitral tribunal publicly available. </p>
          <p>(2) Any information specifically designated as confidential that is transmitted to the arbitral tribunal or to the parties to the dispute shall be protected from public disclosure. </p>
          <p>(3) Any party to the dispute who intends to use information designated as confidential at a hearing shall notify the Arbitral Tribunal. The Arbitral Tribunal shall take the necessary steps to prevent disclosure of the information. </p>
          <p>(4) The hearings of the Arbitral Tribunal shall be held in private when the discussions involve confidential information. Otherwise, they shall be open to the public, unless the parties to the dispute decide otherwise. </p>
          <p>(5) The arbitral tribunal shall not require a party to the dispute to disclose confidential business information or other confidential information the disclosure of which would impede law enforcement or otherwise be contrary to the security interests of the responding Party or would prejudice the legitimate business interests of public or private enterprises. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="17" title="Consultations">
          <p>(1) In the event of an investment dispute, the parties to the dispute shall first seek to resolve the dispute through consultations with a view to reaching an amicable settlement. Such consultations shall be initiated by a written request for consultations from the investor party to the disputing Party.</p>
          <p> (2) For the purpose of resolving a dispute through consultations, the written request for consultations shall contain information on the legal and factual basis for the investment dispute, including the name and address of the claimant, the provisions of this Agreement alleged to have been breached, the relief sought, the estimated amount of damages claimed, and evidence that the claimant is an investor of the other Party and owns or controls the investment.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="18" title="Mediation">
          <p>(1) If an investment dispute cannot be resolved through consultations, a party to the dispute may request the other party to the dispute to resort to a non-binding third party process such as good offices, conciliation or mediation. This process shall be initiated by a written request from one disputing party to the other disputing party and shall require the consent of both disputing parties.</p>
          <p> (2) The process referred to in this section may only be initiated by a disputing party within 6 months from the date of receipt of the written request for consultations by the responding party. </p>
          <p>(3) The costs of the process referred to in this section shall be borne equally by the disputing parties. Each party to the dispute shall bear its own costs arising from its participation in the process. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="19" title="Filing a Complaint">
          <p>(1) If an investment dispute cannot be resolved within 12 months of receipt of the written request for consultations by the Respondent Party, and unless the parties to the dispute agree otherwise, the investor party to the dispute may submit the dispute, on its own behalf or on behalf of its locally established enterprise, (12) to the courts or administrative tribunals of the Party concerned or to international arbitration. In the latter case, the investor has the option of :</p>
          <p>(a) the ICSID Convention and the ICSID Arbitration Rules, provided that the Respondent Party and the Investor Party to the dispute are parties to the ICSID Convention; </p>
          <p>(b) the ICSID Additional Facility Rules, provided that the Respondent Party or the Investor Party to the dispute is a party to the ICSID Convention; </p>
          <p>(c) the UNCITRAL Arbitration Rules; or (d) any other arbitration institution or arbitration rules, if the parties to the dispute so agree.</p>
          <p> (2) In the event of a conflict between the provisions of this Agreement and the provisions of the applicable arbitration rules, the provisions of this Agreement shall prevail to the extent of the conflict. </p>
          <p>(3) Each Party shall consent to the submission of any dispute to arbitration referred to in paragraph (1) in accordance with the provisions of this section, subject to the requirements for such submission set out in this article.</p>
          <p>(4) The consent referred to in paragraph (3) and the submission of a claim to arbitration under this section shall satisfy the requirements of:</p>
          <p> (a) Chapter II (Jurisdiction of the Centre) of the ICSID Convention and the ICSID Additional Facility Rules with respect to the written consent of the parties to the dispute, and </p>
          <p>(b) Art. II of the New York Convention with respect to the existence of a "written agreement". </p>
          <p>(5) A claimant may submit its claim to arbitration only if, cumulatively: </p>
          <p>(a) the claimant provides written notice to the respondent of its intention to submit the dispute to arbitration at least 90 days prior to the filing of the claim, which notice shall include information on the legal and factual basis for the investment dispute provided by the investor party to the dispute in its request for consultations and any changes to the information contained therein;</p>
          <p> (b) at the time the complaint is filed, the respondent consents to the dispute being resolved by arbitration in accordance with the procedures set out in this section; and </p>
          <p>(c) the respondent has failed to state in the complaint any action that was not stated in the request for consultations; or </p>
          <p>(d) it withdraws or discontinues any proceeding pending before a tribunal or court under domestic or international law relating to a measure alleged to be a violation covered by its complaint; and</p>
          <p> (e) it waives its right to submit a complaint or initiate a proceeding before a tribunal or court under domestic or international law relating to a measure alleged to be a violation covered by its complaint.</p>
          <p> Letters (d) and (e) above shall not apply to actions against injunctive, declaratory and non-pecuniary relief, provided that the action is brought solely to preserve the rights and interests of the claimant or the enterprise during the arbitration proceedings.</p>
          <p> (6) A claim may be submitted to arbitration under this Chapter only if a final award with respect to the same measure alleged to violate the provisions of Chapter II (Investment Protection) has not been rendered with respect to a claim filed by the investor party to the dispute before another arbitral tribunal established under this Section or any other agreement containing investment protection provisions.</p>
          <p> (7) Where the investor has not submitted the dispute to international arbitration under paragraph (1) within 24 months from the date of receipt by the responding Party of the written request for consultations, the investor shall be deemed to have withdrawn its request for consultations and shall not be entitled to refer the same dispute to international arbitration under paragraph (1). This period may be extended if the parties to the dispute so agree in writing before it expires. </p>
          <p>(8) The consent of the Parties to the submission of a dispute to arbitration under paragraph (1) pursuant to this section is subject to the condition that the investment dispute be submitted within 5 years after the investor party to the dispute knew or reasonably should have known of a breach of an obligation under this Agreement causing loss or damage to the investor party to the dispute or to its investment. This period may be extended if the parties to the dispute so agree in writing before it expires.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="20" title="Third Party Financing">
          <p>(1) If the parties to the dispute receive third party financing, they shall notify the arbitral tribunal of the name and address of such third party. </p>
          <p>(2) Such notification shall be made at the time of filing the statement of claim or without delay after the conclusion of the third-party funding agreement or the award of the grant or subsidy, as the case may be. </p>
          <p>(3) If the parties to the dispute fail to disclose the existence of third-party funding under this section, the arbitral tribunal may take the conduct of the parties to the dispute into account in awarding costs or suspend or terminate the proceedings by order.&nbsp;</p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="21" title="Constitution of the Arbitral Tribunal">
          <p>(1) Unless the parties to the dispute agree otherwise, the arbitral tribunal shall consist of three arbitrators who are not nationals or permanent residents of either party. Each party to the dispute shall appoint one arbitrator; the appointed arbitrators shall agree on a third arbitrator, who shall be the chairman of the arbitral tribunal. The chairman of the arbitral tribunal shall be a national of a third party that has diplomatic relations with both parties. </p>
          <p>(2) If no arbitral tribunal has been established within 90 days from the date on which the claim was submitted to arbitration, either because a party to the dispute has not appointed an arbitrator or because the appointed arbitrators have not agreed on the choice of the chairman, the Secretary-General of ICSID shall, at the request of one of the parties to the dispute, appoint the arbitrator or arbitrators who have not yet been appointed. If the Secretary-General is a national or permanent resident of one of the Parties or is otherwise prevented from serving, the Deputy Secretary-General of ICSID who is not a national or permanent resident of one of the Parties may be invited to make the necessary appointments. </p>
          <p>(3) The arbitrators shall have extensive experience and knowledge of public international law, international investment law and the resolution of disputes under international investment law. The arbitrators shall be independent of the Parties and the investor party to the dispute and shall not be connected with or take instructions from any of them. </p>
          <p>(4) If an arbitrator appointed pursuant to this section resigns or is no longer able to serve, a successor shall be appointed in the same manner as the original arbitrator was appointed, and the successor shall have the same powers and duties as the original arbitrator. </p>
          <p>(5) Arbitrators appointed under this section shall comply with the code of conduct for arbitrators set forth in Appendix B to this Agreement. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="22" title="Applicable Law and Joint Interpretation">
          <p>(1) An arbitral tribunal established under Article 21 (Constitution of Arbitral Tribunal) shall decide the issues in dispute on the basis of the provisions of this Agreement interpreted in accordance with applicable rules of international law. In addition, it may apply other rules of international law and rules of domestic law whenever appropriate to the issues in dispute.</p>
          <p> (2) Where there are concerns regarding the interpretation of a provision of this Agreement, the Parties may adopt a joint interpretation. Such a joint interpretation of the provision in question shall be binding on any arbitral tribunal established under Chapter III of this Agreement. The Parties may decide that such a joint interpretation shall be binding as of a specified date.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="23" title="Seat of Arbitration">
          <p>Unless the parties to the dispute agree otherwise, the arbitral tribunal shall determine the seat of the arbitration in accordance with the applicable arbitration rules, provided that such seat is located in the territory of a State which is a party to the New York Convention. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="24" title="Arbitration Procedure">
          <p>(1) Where preliminary objections relating to questions of jurisdiction or admissibility are raised, an arbitral tribunal shall rule before proceeding on the merits. </p>
          <p>(2) The responding Party may, not later than 45 days after the constitution of the arbitral tribunal, raise a preliminary objection that a claim is excluded under Article 15 (Scope of the Agreement). The Respondent may also raise a plea that the arbitral tribunal lacks jurisdiction over the matter or venue, or raise any other plea, such as that a claim is frivolous or manifestly unfounded, even if the facts alleged are found to be true. The Respondent shall state as precisely as possible the basis for the objection it raises. The foregoing provision shall be without prejudice to the Respondent's ability to raise such a plea at a later stage of the proceedings. </p>
          <p>(3) The arbitral tribunal shall consider such objections on a preliminary basis, separately from the merits of the claim. The parties to the dispute shall be given a reasonable opportunity to present their views and observations to the arbitral tribunal. If the arbitral tribunal finds that the claim is excluded under Article 15 (Scope of the Agreement) or is otherwise outside its jurisdiction by reason of location or subject matter, or any other exception, it shall make an award or decision to that effect. </p>
          <p>(4) The Arbitral Tribunal shall rule on any preliminary objection raised under this section on an expedited basis. The arbitral tribunal shall suspend all proceedings on the merits and shall render a decision or award on the objection, stating the reasons therefore, not later than 150 days after the date of the request. However, if a party to the dispute requests a hearing, the arbitral tribunal shall have an additional 30 days to render its decision or award. Regardless of whether a hearing is requested, the arbitral tribunal may, where extraordinary reasons are shown to exist, defer its decision or award for a short additional period of time, which shall not exceed 30 days. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="25" title="Diplomatic Protection">
          <p>No Party shall grant diplomatic protection or make an international claim in respect of a dispute that one of its investors and the other Party has agreed to submit or has submitted to arbitration pursuant to this Section, unless the other Party fails to comply with the award in the dispute. For the purposes of this paragraph, diplomatic protection does not include informal diplomatic exchanges intended solely to facilitate the resolution of the dispute.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="26" title="Awards">
          <p>(1) Where the tribunal makes a final award against the respondent Party, it may award, separately or in combination, only:</p>
          <p>   (a) monetary damages and applicable interest, and </p>
          <p>(b) restitution of property, provided that the responding Party may pay, in lieu of restitution, monetary damages representing the fair market value of the property at the time immediately preceding the ex-propriation, or before the impending expropriation became known, whichever occurs first, and applicable interest. </p>
          <p>(2) An Arbitral Tribunal may also award costs and expenses of legal representation and assistance in accordance with this section and the applicable arbitration rules. </p>
          <p>(3) An Arbitral Tribunal shall not award punitive damages. </p>
          <p>(4) The award shall be binding and shall not be subject to any recourse mechanism other than those provided for in the ICSID Convention or any other applicable arbitration rules on which the arbitration procedure chosen by the investor is based. </p>
          <p>(5) A party to the dispute may seek enforcement of a final award only when the following conditions are met:</p>
          <p> (a) in the case of a final award made under the ICSID Convention: </p>
          <p>(i) 120 days have elapsed from the date on which the award was made and none of the parties to the dispute has applied for review or annulment of the award, or </p>
          <p>(ii) the review or annulment proceedings have been completed; </p>
          <p>(b) in the case of a final award made pursuant to the ICSID Additional Facility Rules, the UNCITRAL Arbitration Rules, or any other arbitration rules chosen under Art. 19 (Filing of a Claim), para. 1(d): </p>
          <p>(i) 90 days have elapsed from the date of the award and no party to the dispute has commenced proceedings to have the award reviewed, set aside or annulled; or</p>
          <p> (ii) a court has rejected or granted an application to have the award reviewed, set aside or annulled and its decision is no longer subject to appeal. </p>
          <p>(6) Subject to paragraph (5) and the applicable review procedures, the parties to the dispute shall comply with the award without delay.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="27" title="Costs">
          <p>(1) The arbitral tribunal shall order the unsuccessful party to the dispute to pay the costs of the proceedings. In exceptional cases, the arbitral tribunal may apportion the costs of the proceedings between the parties to the dispute if it considers it appropriate in the circumstances of the case. Other reasonable costs, including the costs of legal representation and assistance, shall also be borne by the unsuccessful party to the dispute, unless the arbitral tribunal considers it inappropriate in the circumstances of the case. If the claimant's claims have been upheld only in part, the costs shall be awarded in proportion to the number or extent of the successful claims. </p>
          <p>(2) The arbitral tribunal shall ensure that all decisions on costs are reasoned and form part of the award.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="28" title="Security for Costs">
          <p>(1) At the request of a party to the dispute, the Arbitral Tribunal may order any party to the dispute that submits a claim or counterclaim to provide security for costs. </p>
          <p>(2) In determining whether to order a party to the dispute to provide security for costs, the arbitral tribunal shall consider all relevant circumstances, including </p>
          <p>(a) the ability of that party to the dispute to comply with a cost award adverse to it; </p>
          <p>(b) the willingness of that party to the dispute to comply with a cost award adverse to it;</p>
          <p> (c) the effect that the provision of security for costs may have on that party to the dispute's ability to maintain its claim or counterclaim, and</p>
          <p> (d) the attitude of the parties to the dispute.</p>
          <p> (3) The arbitral tribunal shall specify the relevant terms and conditions in an order for security for costs and shall fix a time for compliance with the order. </p>
          <p>(4) If a party to the dispute fails to comply with an order for security for costs within 30 days of the order or within such other period as the arbitral tribunal may specify, the arbitral tribunal may stay the proceedings. If the proceedings are stayed for more than 90 days, the Arbitral Tribunal may, after consultation with the parties to the dispute, terminate the proceedings by order. </p>
          <p>(5) A party to the dispute shall promptly disclose any material change in the circumstances on the basis of which the arbitral tribunal has ordered the provision of security for costs. </p>
          <p>(6) The arbitral tribunal may at any time modify or revoke its order for security for costs, either on its own initiative or at the request of a party to the dispute. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="29" title="Consolidation">
          <p>Where two or more claims have been submitted to arbitration separately under Art. 19 (Submission of a Claim) and the claims relate to the same issue of law or fact and arise out of the same or similar events or circumstances, all parties to the dispute concerned may agree to consolidate these claims. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="30" title="Withdrawal">
          <p>If, after the filing of a Complaint under this Section, the investor party to the dispute does not take any action in the Proceeding for a period of 180 days or such other period as may be agreed by the parties to the dispute, it shall be deemed to have withdrawn its Complaint and to have discontinued the Proceeding. At the request of the Respondent and after notice to the parties to the dispute, the arbitral tribunal shall issue an order acknowledging the withdrawal. After such order has been issued, the jurisdiction of the arbitral tribunal shall cease. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="31" title="Notification of Documents">
          <p>(1) Notices and other documents relating to disputes under this section shall be notified to Indonesia at the following address Director General for Legal Affairs and International Treaties</p>
          <p> Ministry of Foreign Affairs </p>
          <p>Jl. Taman Pejambon No. 6</p>
          <p> Jakarta 10110 </p>
          <p>INDONESIA </p>
          <p>(2) Notices and other documents relating to disputes under this section shall be notified to Switzerland at the following address </p>
          <p>State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO </p>
          <p>Holzikofenweg 36 </p>
          <p>3003 Bern </p>
          <p>SWITZERLAND </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="section" num="2" title="Settlement of Disputes between the Parties">
        <div type="article" num="32" title="Scope">
          <p>This Section applies to the settlement of disputes between the Parties arising from the interpretation or application of the provisions of this Agreement. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="33" title="Consultations">
          <p>(1) Either Party may request in writing consultations on the interpretation or application of this Agreement. If a dispute arises between the Parties concerning the interpretation or application of this Agreement, it shall, to the extent possible, be settled amicably through consultations. </p>
          <p>(2) In the event that the dispute is not settled by the above means within six months from the date on which such consultations were requested in writing, and unless the Parties agree otherwise, either Party may refer the dispute to an arbitral tribunal established in accordance with this section or, if the Parties so agree, to any other international tribunal. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="34" title="Establishment of the Arbitral Tribunal">
          <p>(1) The arbitration proceedings shall be initiated by a written notification sent by a Party (hereinafter referred to as "the claimant Party") to the other Party (hereinafter referred to as "the respondent Party") through diplomatic channels. The notification shall identify the specific measure at issue and set forth in sufficient detail the legal and factual basis for the claim (including the provisions of this Agreement to be considered by the arbitral tribunal) to clearly state the issue. </p>
          <p>(2) Each Party shall appoint an arbitrator; the two arbitrators so appointed shall appoint a chairperson who shall be a national of a third party having diplomatic relations with the Parties. If one of the Parties has not appointed its arbitrator and has not complied with the invitation of the other Party to do so within two months after the notice of arbitration, the arbitrator shall be appointed, at the request of the latter Party, by the Secretary-General of ICSID. If the arbitrators cannot agree on the choice of the chairman within two months of their appointment, the chairman shall be appointed, at the request of either Party, by the Secretary-General of ICSID. </p>
          <p>(3) If the Secretary-General of ICSID is prevented from exercising this function or if he is a national of one of the Parties, the President of the International Court of Justice shall act as appointing authority. If the President of the International Court of Justice is unable to act or is a national of one of the Parties, the appointments shall be made by the Vice-President and, if the Vice-President is unable to act or is a national of one of the Parties, by the most senior member of the Court who is not a national of any of the Parties. </p>
          <p>(4) The arbitrators shall have extensive experience and knowledge of public international law, international investment law and the resolution of international investment law disputes. The arbitrators shall be independent of the Parties and shall not be connected with or take instructions from any Party.</p>
          <p> (5) In the event that an arbitrator appointed pursuant to this section resigns or is no longer able to serve, a successor shall be appointed in the same manner as the original arbitrator was appointed and shall have the same powers and duties as the original arbitrator. </p>
          <p>(6) Each Party shall bear the expenses of the arbitrator appointed by it and of any legal representation in the proceedings. The costs of the chairman of the arbitral tribunal and the other costs of the arbitration proceedings shall be borne equally by the Parties, unless the arbitral tribunal decides otherwise. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="35" title="Seat of Arbitration">
          <p>Unless the Parties agree otherwise, the seat of the arbitration shall be determined by the arbitral tribunal. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="article" num="36" title="Arbitration Procedure">
          <p>(1) An arbitral tribunal established under this Section shall decide all issues submitted by the claimant Party and, subject to any agreement between the Parties, shall determine its own procedure.   At any stage of the proceedings, the arbitral tribunal may suggest to the Parties that they settle the dispute amicably. </p>
          <p>(2) An arbitral tribunal established under Article 34 shall decide the issues in dispute on the basis of the provisions of this Agreement interpreted in accordance with the applicable rules of international law. In addition, it may apply other rules of international law and rules of domestic law whenever appropriate to the issues in dispute. </p>
          <p>(3) The award shall be in writing and shall contain the applicable findings of fact and law. The award shall be final and binding on the Parties and each arbitral tribunal constituted under this Agreement. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" num="IV" title="General Provisions, Exceptions and Final Provisions">
          <div type="article" num="37" title="More Favourable Conditions">
            <p>If the laws of one of the Parties or international obligations now existing or hereafter established between the Parties in addition to this Agreement result in a situation in which the investments of investors of the other Party are entitled to more favourable treatment than that accorded to them under this Agreement, this situation shall not be affected by this Agreement. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="article" num="38" title="Denial of Benefits">
            <p>(1) A Party may deny the benefits of this Agreement to an investor of the other Party that is a juridical person of that other Party and to the investments of that investor if the juridical person is owned or controlled by an investor of a third party or of the Party denying benefits and has no substantial business activities in the territory of that other Party. </p>
            <p>(2) A Party may deny the benefits of this Agreement to an investor of the other Party that is a juridical person of that other Party and to the investments of that investor if the juridical person is owned or controlled by persons of a third party and the denying Party adopts or maintains with respect to that third party or a person of that third party, measures relating to the maintenance of international peace and security that prohibit transactions with that juridical person or that would be violated or circumvented if the benefits of this Agreement were extended to that juridical person or its investments. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="article" num="39" title="Transparency">
            <p>(1) Each Party shall promptly publish or otherwise make publicly available its laws, regulations and international agreements that may affect investments of investors of the other Party. </p>
            <p>(2) Each Party shall, at the request of the other Party, respond within a reasonable period of time to specific questions from the other Party and provide information on the matters referred to in paragraph 1. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="article" num="40" title="Disclosure of Information">
            <p>(1) Notwithstanding Article 5 (National Treatment), a Party may require an investor of the other Party or its investment to provide information relating to that investment solely for informational or statistical purposes. The Party shall protect business information that is confidential from disclosure that would prejudice the competitive position of the investor or its investment. Nothing in this subparagraph shall be construed to prevent a Party from otherwise obtaining or disclosing information in the fair and good faith application of its law. </p>
            <p>(2) Nothing in this Agreement shall require either Party to disclose confidential information the disclosure of which would impede law enforcement or otherwise be contrary to the public interest, or would prejudice the legitimate commercial interests of particular enterprises, public or private. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="article" num="41" title="General Exceptions">
            <p>Provided that such measures are not applied in a manner that would constitute either a means of arbitrary or unjustifiable discrimination against the other Party or its investors where like conditions prevail, or a disguised restriction in the territory of a Party on investment by investors of the other Party, nothing in this Agreement shall be construed to prevent the adoption or enforcement by a Party of measures:</p>
            <p> (a) necessary to protect public morals or to maintain public order; (13) </p>
            <p>(b) necessary to protect human, animal or plant life or health; </p>
            <p>(c) necessary to secure compliance with laws or regulations that are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Agreement, including those relating to: </p>
            <p>(i) the prevention of deceptive and fraudulent practices or the remedying of a breach of contract, </p>
            <p>(ii) the protection of the privacy of individuals with respect to the processing and dissemination of personal data and the protection of the confidentiality of personal records and accounts, </p>
            <p>(iii) security ; </p>
            <p>(d) imposed for the protection of national treasures of artistic, historic or archaeological value, or </p>
            <p>(e) relating to the conservation of exhaustible natural resources, if such measures are applied in conjunction with restrictions on domestic production or consumption. </p>
            <div type="foot_note">(13) The public order exception may be invoked only where there is a genuine and sufficiently serious threat to one of the fundamental interests of society.</div>
          </div>
          <div type="article" num="42" title="Prudential Measures">
            <p>(1) Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent a Party from adopting or maintaining, on a non-discriminatory basis, measures relating to financial services for prudential reasons, (14) including for </p>
            <p>(a) the protection of investors, depositors, policyholders, policy beneficiaries, financial market participants or persons to whom a custodial right is owed by a financial institution; and </p>
            <p>(b) ensuring the integrity and stability of a Party's financial system.</p>
            <p>(2) Measures taken by a Party under paragraph 1 shall not be used by that Party as a means of avoiding its commitments or obligations under this Agreement.</p>
            <div type="foot_note">(14)&nbsp;The Parties understand that the term "prudential reasons" includes maintaining the safety, soundness, integrity and financial accountability of individual financial service providers and the safety and financial and operational integrity of payment and clearing systems.</div>
          </div>
          <div type="article" num="43" title="Investment Promotion and Facilitation">
            <p>(1) Subject to its laws and regulations, each Party shall endeavor to cooperate to facilitate investment between the Parties by, inter alia:</p>
            <p> (a) creating the necessary environment for all forms of investment; </p>
            <p>(b) simplifying procedures relating to investment applications and approvals; </p>
            <p>(c) encouraging the dissemination of information relating to investment, including investment rules, regulations, policies and procedures; and </p>
            <p>(d) establishing an appropriate mechanism, to the extent practicable, to provide assistance and advisory services to investors, including the facilitation of business licenses and permits. </p>
            <p>(2) Subject to its laws and regulations, the cooperative activities referred to in paragraph 1(d) may build upon existing agreements or arrangements for economic cooperation. </p>
            <p>(3) Nothing in this Article shall be construed to affect any obligation under the provisions of Chapter II (Investment Protection), or otherwise subject to or affecting any dispute resolution procedures under this Agreement. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="article" num="44" title="Entry Into Force, Duration and Termination">
            <p>(1) This Agreement shall enter into force on the date of receipt through diplomatic channels of the second notification that both Parties have complied with their legal requirements for the entry into force of international agreements. </p>
            <p>(2) Notwithstanding Art. 2 (Scope of this Agreement), a complaint may be filed under the provisions of the Convention of February 6, 1974 between the Government of the Swiss Confederation and the Government of the Republic of Indonesia on the Reciprocal Promotion and Protection of Investments, which was terminated effective April 8, 2016 (hereinafter referred to as the "Prior Agreement"), in accordance with the rules and procedures established by the Prior Agreement, and provided that not more than one year has elapsed since the date of entry into force of this Agreement. </p>
            <p>(3) This Agreement may be amended by written agreement between the Parties. Amendments shall enter into force by the same procedure as set out in paragraph 1. </p>
            <p>(4) This Agreement shall enter into force for a period of 10 years and shall remain in force thereafter unless either Party notifies the other Party in writing of its intention to terminate it. This Agreement shall terminate one year after receipt of the notification of termination by the other Party. </p>
            <p>(5) With respect to investments made prior to the date of termination of the Agreement, the provisions of this Agreement shall continue to apply for an additional period of 10 years from that date.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <conclusion>
      <p>  In witness whereof, the undersigned, being duly authorized by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement. </p>
      <p> Done at ..., on ..., in two original copies, each in the French, Indonesian and English languages, all texts being equally authentic. In the event of a difference of interpretation, the English text shall prevail. </p>
      <p>For the Swiss Federal Council </p>
      <p>For the Government of the Republic of Indonesia </p>
    </conclusion>
    <attachments>
      <div type="annex" num="Annex A" title="Expropriation">
        <p>The Parties confirm their common understanding that:</p>
        <p> (1) A measure or series of measures taken by a Party shall not constitute an expropriation unless it affects a tangible or intangible property right or interest in property forming part of the investment. </p>
        <p>(2) Article 7 (Expropriation), paragraph 1, covers two situations. The first is direct expropriation, i.e. where the investment is nationalized or otherwise directly expropriated by formal transfer of title or unconditional seizure. </p>
        <p>(3) The second situation referred to in Article 7 (Expropriation), paragraph 1, is indirect expropriation, i.e. where a measure or series of measures taken by a Party has an effect equivalent to that of direct expropriation without a formal transfer of title or unconditional seizure.</p>
        <p> (a) In determining whether an action or series of actions taken by a Party, in a given factual situation, constitutes an indirect expropriation, it is necessary to conduct an examination of the facts that takes into account, among other things, the following factors:</p>
        <p>   (i) the economic impact of the governmental measure, although the fact that a measure or series of measures taken by a Party adversely affects the economic value of an investment does not in itself establish that an indirect expropriation has occurred; </p>
        <p>(ii) the duration of the measure or series of measures taken by a Party;</p>
        <p> (iii) the extent to which the governmental measure impairs the specific and reasonable expectations underlying the investment; (15) and </p>
        <p>(iv) the nature of the governmental measure, including its objective and whether the measure is disproportionate to the public interest. </p>
        <p>(b) For greater certainty, except in rare circumstances where the impact of a measure or series of measures is so severe in relation to their purpose as to appear manifestly excessive, non-discriminatory regulatory measures of a Party that are designed and implemented to protect legitimate public welfare objectives, such as public health, safety and the environment, do not constitute indirect expropriation. </p>
        <div type="foot_note">(15) It is understood that whether the expectations underlying the investor's investment are reasonable depends, to the extent relevant, on such factors as whether the government has provided the investor with binding written assurances and the nature and extent of any governmental regulation or the potential for governmental regulation in the relevant industry.</div>
      </div>
      <div type="annex" num="Annex B" title="Code of Conduct for Arbitrators">
        <p>
          <i>Responsibilities in the Process </i>
        </p>
        <p>(1) Arbitrators shall avoid any breach or appearance of breach of ethics, be independent and impartial, avoid direct and indirect conflicts of interest, and observe high standards of conduct so that the integrity and impartiality of the dispute resolution process is preserved. Former arbitrators shall comply with the obligations set out in paragraphs 17, 18 and 20. </p>
        <p>
          <i>Duty to Disclose </i>
        </p>
        <p>(2) Prior to confirmation of selection as an arbitrator under this Agreement, the candidate shall disclose all interests, relationships and matters that may affect the candidate's independence or impartiality or that may reasonably create an appearance of impropriety or bias in the proceedings. To this end, the candidate shall make every reasonable effort to ascertain the existence of such interests, relationships and matters. </p>
        <p>(3) Once selected, the arbitrator shall continue to make every reasonable effort to ascertain the existence of interests, relationships and matters referred to in subsection (2) and shall declare them by communicating them in writing to the parties to the dispute. The duty to disclose is a continuing duty that requires the arbitrator to disclose all interests, relationships and matters that may arise at any stage of the proceedings.</p>
        <p>
          <i>Performance of duties by arbitrators</i>
        </p>
        <p> (4) The arbitrator shall comply with the provisions of Chapter III (Dispute Resolution) and the applicable rules of procedure. </p>
        <p>(5) Once selected, an arbitrator shall perform his or her duties fully and effectively throughout the proceeding in a fair and expeditious manner.</p>
        <p> (6) The arbitrator shall not prevent the other arbitrators from participating in all aspects of the proceeding. </p>
        <p>(7) The arbitrator shall not go beyond the request of the parties to the dispute and shall not delegate to any person the responsibility of making decisions. </p>
        <p>(8) The arbitrator shall take all appropriate steps to ensure that the arbitrator's assistant and staff are aware of and comply with paragraphs 1, 2, 3, 18, 19 and 20.</p>
        <p> (9) Once the arbitral tribunal is constituted, the arbitrator shall have no ex parte contacts concerning the proceedings. </p>
        <p>(10) The arbitrator shall not communicate about actual or potential violations by another arbitrator unless the communication is intended for both parties to the dispute or is necessary to determine whether the arbitrator has violated or is likely to violate this Annex. </p>
        <p>
          <i>Independence and Impartiality of Arbitrators </i>
        </p>
        <p>(11) An arbitrator shall be independent and impartial. He or she shall act fairly and avoid any appearance of impropriety or bias. </p>
        <p>(12) An arbitrator shall not be influenced by self-interest, outside pressure, political considerations, public protest, loyalty to a Party or a party to the dispute, or fear of criticism. </p>
        <p>(13) An arbitrator shall not, directly or indirectly, assume any obligation or accept any benefit that would in any way interfere or appear to interfere with the proper performance of his or her duties. </p>
        <p>(14) An arbitrator shall not use his office in the Arbitral Tribunal to further any personal or private interest. He shall refrain from any action which might give the impression that others are in a position to influence him. He shall do everything possible to prevent or dissuade anyone from claiming to be in such a position. </p>
        <p>(15) An arbitrator shall not allow his or her conduct or judgment to be influenced by past or present financial, business, professional, family or social relationships or responsibilities.</p>
        <p> (16) An arbitrator shall not enter into any relationship or acquire any financial interest that is likely to affect the arbitrator's impartiality or that might reasonably create an appearance of impropriety or bias.</p>
        <p>
          <i>Obligations in certain situations</i>
        </p>
        <p>(17) An arbitrator or former arbitrator shall not do anything that would create the appearance of bias in the performance of his or her duties or that he or she would benefit from the decision or award made by the arbitral tribunal.</p>
        <p>
          <i>Respect of confidentiality</i>
        </p>
        <p>(18) An arbitrator or former arbitrator shall not at any time disclose or use any non-public information concerning the proceeding or obtained in the course of the proceeding except for the purposes of the proceeding and to the extent that disclosure may be required by legal or constitutional requirements, and shall not in any case disclose or use such information for his or her own benefit or for the benefit of another person or to prejudice the interests of another person. </p>
        <p>(19) An arbitrator shall not disclose an award of the Arbitral Tribunal, in whole or in part, until the award has been published. </p>
        <p>(20) An arbitrator or former arbitrator shall not at any time disclose the substance of the deliberations of an Arbitral Tribunal or the opinion of an arbitrator except as required by legal or constitutional requirements.  </p>
      </div>
    </attachments>
  </main>
</treaty>
